<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Coales from the altar; or Foure religious treatises to kindle deuotion in this colde age. Written in French by Mounsieur du Moulin: and translated into English by N.M.</title>
            <author>Du Moulin, Pierre, 1568-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622-1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 237 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 139 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20939</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7318</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118640</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853847</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853847</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19245</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20939)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19245)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1095:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Coales from the altar; or Foure religious treatises to kindle deuotion in this colde age. Written in French by Mounsieur du Moulin: and translated into English by N.M.</title>
                  <author>Du Moulin, Pierre, 1568-1658.</author>
                  <author>Metcalfe, Nicholas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 57, [1]; [2], 50; [2], 75, [1]; [2], 76 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Thomas Snodham] for Thomas Pauier, and are to be sold at his shop in Iuie lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed by translator: Nich. Metcalfe.</note>
                  <note>In four parts, each with separate dated title page, separate register, and separate pagination: "The boldnesse and confidence of a Christian"; "The comfort of a communicant"; "A heauenly alarum. Or the holy spirituall awakening"; and "Comfortable instructions for the sicke". All are printed by T. Snodham for Pavier and dated 1623, but "A heavenly alarum. Or the holy spirituall awakening", which is printed by J. Haviland for Pavier and dated 1622.</note>
                  <note>"A heavenly alarum" is a translation of: Le sainct réveil spirituel; "Comfortable instructions for the sicke" is a translation of: Familière instruction pour consoler les malades.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Part 3 (A heavenly alarum. Or the holy spirituall awakening) formerly also STC 7324.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Transubstantiation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sick --  Prayer-books and devotions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19245:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19245:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>COALES FROM THE ALTAR; OR, Foure religious TREATISES to kindle Deuotion in this colde AGE.</p>
            <p>Written in <hi>French</hi> by <hi>Mounſieur du Moulin:</hi> And Tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>N. M.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Pauier,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Iuie lane.</hi> 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19245:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19245:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, the Lady <hi>Elizabeth Norriſſe,</hi> the onely Daughter and heire of the Right Honourable <hi>Francis,</hi> Earle of <hi>Berkeſhire,</hi> and Wife to the Right Worſhipfull M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Edward Wray,</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAME,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O great is my Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to your Honour; that your Honour may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the beſt ſeruices of my tongue, or pen, as due to your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhip for thoſe brighteſt beames of your bounty lately caſt vpon me: whereby you haue comforted, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiued my languiſhing and drooping
<pb facs="tcp:19245:3"/>
fortunes. The leſſe I am able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge ſo great a debt, the more I am bound to acknowledge it. <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> finding <hi>Perides</hi> very ready to make vſe of his learning in Philoſophy, but ſlow to contribute any thing to his maintenance, brake with him in the end after this manner: Sir, if you deſire to ſee by my light, you muſt miniſter oyle to my lampe. I muſt confeſſe, and I willingly profeſſe it (Right Noble and vertuous Lady) that you haue poured oyle into my Lampe in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant meaſure; and therefore by <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> his <hi>Apophthegne,</hi> the light of my Lampe is yours by right. A Lampe that burneth dimly at the firſt kindling, yet afterwards yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a cleare and comfortable light; which putteth me in ſome good hope that my labours, how obſcure ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they are now, yet hereafter by more induſtry, and practiſe in this kinde, may ſerue not only to illuſtrate
<pb facs="tcp:19245:3"/>
my Authors, but alſo your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips name. For the preſent, I muſt intreate a fauourable glance of your Ladiſhips eye vpon the worke I haue now aduentured to Tranſlate and Dedicate to your Honour. It conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth of foure rare pieces, drawne by an excellent hand. The firſt preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to your view the liuely image of a Chriſtians confidence in the word; the ſecond, of his deuotion at the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament; the third, of his patience in aduerſitie; the fourth, of his watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe in proſperity. All the parts and lineaments of theſe beautifull pictures, I haue entirely repreſented in my tranſlated draught: but our language did not alwayes afford mee colours anſwerable to my Authors: Which defect in them, if your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip will diſpenſe with, I doubt not but that they will ſeeme very agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to your Honour, and not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnworthy to be laid vp in your
<pb facs="tcp:19245:4"/>
Ladyſhips rich Cabinet of ſpirituall rarities and diuine Treatiſes in this kinde, which you rightly value a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all other precious things in the world: For, iewels and precious ſtones adorne but the body, theſe beautifie the minde, and repaire the image of God in the hidden man of the heart. The firſt of theſe will diſpoſe you to the diligent hearing of the Word; the ſecond will prepare you to the worthy receiuing of the Sacrament; The third wil offer you comfort in ſicknes and diſtreſſe; The fourth will giue you wholeſome counſell in proſperity. Before you goe to Sermon, to ſet an edge vpon your ſpirituall appetite for the foode of your ſoule, I commend to your deuout meditations, the firſt of them, which diſcourſeth of the excellency of the Goſpell. When you are bid to the Lords Table, to take your Sauiour, with <hi>Simeon,</hi> into your hand, peruſe the ſecond Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:19245:4"/>
being wholly of that ſubiect. And if God at any time ſhake his rod ouer you, and you feare a fit of ſickneſſe, or any grieuous trouble and affliction, make vſe of the cordiall contained in the third Treatiſe. Laſtly, when you find your ſelfe dull and heauy in your deuotion, &amp; in a manner lulled a ſleep by the ſweet enchantments of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comforts and delights, then take the ſiluer Larum-Bell in the fourth Treatiſe, into your hand, and ring it out to awake you. So ſhall your proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity be ſecure, your affliction cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, your receiuing the Sacrament moſt comfortable, and your hearing the Word moſt delightfull and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Which he neuer ceaſeth to pray for, who remaines</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladyſhips humbly deuoted, and perpetually obliged ſeruant, NICH. METCALFE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:19245:5"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 6. <hi>line</hi> 14. <hi>reade</hi> a happy newes; <hi>p.</hi> 7. <hi>l.</hi> 17. <hi>r.</hi> declaring, <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>l.</hi> 11. <hi>r.</hi> acknowledge, <hi>p.</hi> 9. <hi>l</hi> 21 <hi>r.</hi> driuing, <hi>p.</hi> 15. <hi>l.</hi> 13. <hi>r.</hi> ſpirit, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 17. <hi>r.</hi> we, <hi>p.</hi> 17. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>r.</hi> being oppoſite to the courſe, <hi>p.</hi> 18. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>r.</hi> it ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of God that he, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 19. <hi>r.</hi> it, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>r.</hi> they, <hi>p.</hi> 19. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>r.</hi> his Kingdome, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 2. <hi>r.</hi> deliuered, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 11. <hi>r.</hi> to the, <hi>p.</hi> 20. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>r.</hi> by a, <hi>p.</hi> 21. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>r.</hi> ſhed his bloud for vs? <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 20. by the ſword, or of, <hi>p.</hi> 22. <hi>l.</hi> 17. <hi>r.</hi> he, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 23. <hi>r.</hi> plainneſſe, <hi>p.</hi> 23. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>r.</hi> elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. <hi>p.</hi> 24. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>r.</hi> it, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 19. <hi>r.</hi> diſcourſe, <hi>p.</hi> 5. <hi>l.</hi> 19. <hi>r.</hi> riſeth, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 24. <hi>r.</hi> how hardly they can ſtand. <hi>p.</hi> 6. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>r.</hi> beareth out or vp, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 24. <hi>r.</hi> growne, <hi>p.</hi> 27. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>r.</hi> weake are ſcandalized at our prophanneſſe, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 3. <hi>r.</hi> our, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 17. an, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 18. <hi>r.</hi> darke, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 20. <hi>r.</hi> the bottomeleſſe pit, <hi>p.</hi> 28. <hi>l.</hi> 81. <hi>r.</hi> will, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 22. Shepheards, <hi>p.</hi> 29. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>r.</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimer, <hi>p.</hi> 30. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>r.</hi> couered, <hi>p.</hi> 31. <hi>l.</hi> 21. thoſe good things, <hi>p.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>r.</hi> glorieth in being, <hi>p.</hi> 33. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>r.</hi> that, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 10. <hi>r.</hi> it, <hi>p.</hi> 34. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>r.</hi> it, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 14. <hi>r.</hi> ſtrike, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 18. <hi>r.</hi> it, <hi>p.</hi> 37. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>r.</hi> within, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 7. <hi>r.</hi> on, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 23. <hi>r.</hi> The, <hi>p.</hi> 38. <hi>l.</hi> 20. <hi>r.</hi> Wherefore, <hi>p.</hi> 39. <hi>l.</hi> 12. <hi>r.</hi> life, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 13. <hi>r.</hi> implicit, <hi>ib. l.</hi> 20. <hi>r.</hi> by an Atturney or a proxy, <hi>p.</hi> 40. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>r.</hi> his, <hi>p.</hi> 41. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>r.</hi> being, <hi>p.</hi> 42. <hi>l.</hi> 22. <hi>r.</hi> ſtrengthen, <hi>p.</hi> 43. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>r.</hi> who, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 2. <hi>r.</hi> who, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 11. <hi>r.</hi> needles, <hi>p.</hi> 44. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>r.</hi> prohibition which Chriſt gaue, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 17. <hi>r.</hi> wherefore, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 18. <hi>r.</hi> that he was ſent, <hi>p.</hi> 45. <hi>l.</hi> 21. <hi>r.</hi> Goſhen, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 23. <hi>r.</hi> was, <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 24. <hi>r.</hi> palpable.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19245:5"/>
                  <p>THE BOLDNESSE AND CONFIDENCE OF A Chriſtian.</p>
                  <p>In a SERMON, made by <hi>Mounſieur du Moulin,</hi> Miniſter of the Reformed Church at PARIS.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Pauier,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Iuie lane.</hi> 1623.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19245:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19245:6"/>
                  <head>A SERMON, Made by <hi>Mounſieur du Moulin,</hi> Miniſter of the Reformed Church at PARIS: Expounding the firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Epiſtle of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the Romanes.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>ROM. 1. VER. 16.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>I am not aſhamed of the Goſpell of Chriſt, ſeeing it is the power of God to ſaluation to euery one that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ven as the Walles of <hi>Ieri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co</hi> fell at the ſound of <hi>Ioſuahs</hi> Trumpets; So did the Walles of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19245:7"/>
fall at the ſound of the Trumpet of the Goſpell. For the preaching of the Goſpell is the meanes by which God eſtabliſheth his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome amongſt men, and maketh the Kingdome of the Diuell to tremble. For euen as death entred into the world by the eare, ſo God hath wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led that life ſhould enter in by the ſame meanes: and as man is fallen by beleeuing the word of the Serpent, ſo man ſhould be raiſed againe by beleeuing the Word of God. It is no wonder then if Sathan oppoſe himſelfe at the preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and enforce himſelfe to make it ſeeme odious, becauſe it is the means to diminiſh his Empire. Hee hath ſtitched the skinne of the Foxe to the skinne of the Lyon: adding ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty to force, coupling together with perſecution the ſtings of Philoſophy; Euen as the Sunne that bringeth in the Spring, with Flowers and new
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19245:7"/>
Verdure, begetting thouſands of flies and vermine, which ſerue to no end, but loſſe and dammage. Alſo in like ſort, ſo ſoone as God hath powred out his bleſſings vpon a Countrey, with the Sun-ſhine of the Goſpel, preſently there ariſeth a thouſand lyes, trickes and conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, to extinguiſh the growing truth, and to ſtifle the Church of God in the Cradle. Before the preaching of the Goſpell, publiſhed by the Apoſtles, there was a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull confuſion of contrary Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, and yet there was neuer any contention or fighting for Religion amongſt themſelues. When the Romanes conquered any Countrey, they carryed triumphantly away with them their Captiuates Gods of ſtrange Religions, and made Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples for their impriſoned Gods, and ſo brought in into their Citie all ſorts of Religion. They neuer diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19245:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
with any but the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, onely againſt it haue they enlighted their fire, and vnſheathed their ſwords: for many and diuers lies may dwell together, but there is no accord between a lie &amp; the truth: two falſe Religions agree much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter together then the falſe with the true.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pilate</hi> and <hi>Herode,</hi> although they were enemies, yet agreed together againſt Ieſus Chriſt. Alſo one may ſee at this preſent in <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Iewes</hi> (who maintaine that Chriſt Ieſus was a diſſembler) are ſuffered to dwell there with Greeks and Turks likewiſe: Our Religion onely, is not ſuffered there, becauſe that it alone ruinateth the Empire of Sathan, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Ieſus Chriſt onely for the purgation of all our ſinnes, and his death onely for ſacrifice, and his Word for the onely rule of our faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:19245:8"/>Now although Sathan worke all that is poſſible againſt vs, yet ſhall he neuer come to the end of his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. For euen as the Rayes of the Sunne cannot be mooued with the winde out of their proper lines, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their nature is heauenly; ſo the world and the Diuell neuer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh the light of the Word of God, becauſe it commeth from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and is of a ſpirituall nature.</p>
                  <p>Hee which could ſpeake of theſe things with more experience then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other was, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſuffered ſo many trauailes, runne ſo many dangers, endured ſo many ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies for the teſtimonie of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: And being ſtrengthened with vertue from aboue, loſeth no courage, but diſgeſteth his bitterneſſe, miſpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth their miſpriſes, and glorifying himſelfe in their contempt of him, ſaying, <hi>I am not aſhamed of the Goſpel of Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19245:9"/>The vnderſtanding of theſe words, depend vpon the Expoſition of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> three points: Firſt, what the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> of Chriſt is: Secondly what the cauſes are that make men aſhamed of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the Goſpell: Thirdly, what haue beene the conſiderations which haue encouraged our Apoſtle not to bee aſhamed of the Goſpell, whereof hee propoundeth, vnto vs the principall, that is to ſay, <hi>That it is the power of Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To begin with the firſt point. This word <hi>Goſpell,</hi> ſignifieth a new man and a happy; the Goſpell of Chriſt is the good newes, which not onely declareth Ieſus Chriſt vnto vs, but alſo is declared vnto vs by Ieſus Chriſt: It is a happy newes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Ieſus Chriſt is not onely the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect and the ſubſtance, but alſo the bringer, and the reuealer. To make vs vnderſtand what the ſubſtance of this good newes is, you ought to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19245:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
put for foundation, that the good of the Creature dependeth vpon the Creator, and that the felicitie of man proceedeth not from his owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per vertue, but from the grace of God, which was the cauſe why God did not create <hi>Adam</hi> in the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Paradiſe, but onely introduced him in, to the end hee might learne that he was not heire of Paradiſe by nature, but it was God that by his grace led man in, euen as it were by the hand. In this earthly Paradiſe, God had planted two Trees, which ſerue for two aduertiſements, the one ſetting out human infirmity, the other claring the grace of God: the Tree <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> of knowledge of good and euill, was a figure of the Law, which gaue man to vnderſtand the knowledge of good and euill: and the Tree of life <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> was the figure of the Goſpell, which preſented vnto vs the fruit of life, that is to ſay, Ieſus Chriſt, as hee
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19245:10"/>
himſelfe expoundeth it, in ſpeaking of his graces; <hi>Whoſoeuer ſhall ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, I will giue him to eate of the Tree of life, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now wee ſee, that if before the fall of man, God would by theſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuments make man know and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, he did not ſubſiſt at all by his owne proper vertue, but onely by the grace of God: How much more muſt he now ſubiect and confeſſe his weakeneſſe, ſeeing he is fallen away from this grace by his ſinnes? For, if a liuing man ſubſiſt not of himſelfe, much leſſe can a dead man raiſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vp by his proper vertue: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon God promiſed to <hi>Abraham</hi> the poſſeſſion of the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> which was a figure of the Kingdome of Heauen; yet he would not put him into the poſſeſſion thereof, although he were the naturall Father of all the people of God, to the end man might learne, that the poſſeſſion of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19245:10"/>
the inheritance of Heauen, commeth not by Nature, but by the grace of God: And moreouer, God would not that <hi>Moſes,</hi> the bearer of the Law, ſhould introduce the people in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> purpoſely to declare vnto vs, that it is not by the Law, or by our workes, that wee can come to the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
                  <p>What then? The charge to bring in the people of God into the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed inheritance, was giuen to <hi>Ioſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> who was alſo called <hi>Ieſus,</hi> and a Sauiour, being onely a figure of Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Moſes</hi> led the people to the borders of the Land, and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them into the hands of <hi>Ioſuah,</hi> becauſe the law leadeth vs to the Goſpell, and is a Schoolemaſter to bring vs vnto Chriſt, chaſing vs on our way by threatnings, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting it vnto vs by ſhadowes and figures. Man then being ſo caſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19245:11"/>
downe, and fallen into death, could not get vp againe, but by the onely aſſiſtance and grace of God. Hee that did blow vpon the face of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> Reſpiration of life, is he onely from whom man can receiue inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of ſpirituall life. For as <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius</hi> reciteth of thoſe that trauai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the deſarts of <hi>Siria,</hi> where are nothing but miſerable Mariſhes and Sands, deſtitute of all commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; if it hapned that their fire went out by the way, then they lighted it againe at the Sunne, by ſome deuice; euen ſo, if man haue ſuffered the ſparkes of diuine grace to dye in him, he hath no other meanes to inlighten himſelfe againe, but at the Sunne of Iuſtice, there to haue reliefe at the Sunne of Iuſtice, and Father of lights.</p>
                  <p>The meanes that God vſed to raiſe man from his fall, is that which he hath declared vnto <hi>Adam; The
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19245:11"/>
ſeed of the Woman ſhould bruiſe the Serpents head, Gen.</hi> 3.15. God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe being pleaſed to be the firſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt; and as Woman brought to man the fruit of death, Woman ſhould bring to man againe the fruit of life, the meanes is, that in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of times, he hath ſent his Sonne, his eternall Word, <hi>and taken vpon him our fleſh,</hi> allying by this meanes God with man, making the Sonne of God our Brother, to the end, we might be the Sonnes of God. He hath taken our humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vpon him, to the end we ſhould participate of his diuine nature; hee hath taken our fleſh, for to giue vs his ſpirit; hee hath made himſelfe a ſtranger here below, to the end wee ſhould be domeſticke with God; he which is Father of eternitie was well pleaſed to haue it ſo; and hath ſent his word amongſt vs, to the end we might ſpeake to God with aſſurance;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19245:12"/>
making himſelfe a ſeruant, to the end we might raigne with him.</p>
                  <p>By this meanes we haue familiar acceſſe to God, ſeeing he hath taken away the rayes from his face, and that Maieſty that would haue ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed and aſtoniſhed vs, ſhewing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in a familiar and acceſſible faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in his Sonne, who is our <hi>Emanu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> that is to ſay, God with vs.</p>
                  <p>In ſtead of the Prouerbe which was vſed in <hi>Iſraell, Wee dye, for wee haue ſeene God;</hi> now we ought and may ſay, <hi>Wee liue,</hi> for God hath made himſelfe viſible and acceſſible by his Sonne.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond Perſon of the Trinitie hath bin imployed in this work: For by what means could we be made the Children of God, but by him who is his onely Son? which bringeth vs to vnderſtand that he is the wiſedome of the Father; by whom hee telleth vs, that he is the Word it ſelfe, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19245:12"/>
all things into order by him, by which he hath created all things? Yet this is not all, for in this ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame fleſh, he would haue him ſuffer the paine which wee haue merited, and to ſatisfie for vs the diuine iuſtice, as he ſaith of himſelfe, <hi>I paid them the things that I neuer tooke, Pſalme 69.5.</hi> For Ieſus Chriſt had not wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall to hide his head, to the end we might haue where to repoſe our conſciences: Hee which is the bread of Life was hungry, to the end, wee might be filled.</p>
                  <p>Hee is dead, to the end to giue vs life; hauing drunke the <hi>Cup of the wrath of God,</hi> to the end we ſhould drinke at the Riuer of his pleaſures, and as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>1 Pet. 2. Verſe 24. Hee hath borne our ſinnes vpon his Body, vpon the Tree,</hi> to the end that being dead to ſinne, wee ſhould liue to righteouſneſſe, by the breach whereof, wee haue beene
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19245:13"/>
healed, for ſaith Saint <hi>Paul, Col. 1.19. the good pleaſure of the Father, that all fulneſſe ſhould dwell in him, and to reconcile by him euery thing to himſelfe, hauing made peace with the bloud of his Croſſe,</hi> &amp;c. Death ſwallowed him vp, but it was like the fiſhes, that ſwallowing the Baite are taken: ſo Death, in taking Ieſus Chriſt, is ſurmounted and ouercome by him, for he is life it ſelfe, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo becauſe of his righteouſneſſe and innocencie death hath no power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him.</p>
                  <p>There is nothing ſo admirable as this death, by the which hee hath triumphed ouer the power of Hell, and of the Diuell, by the which God hath puniſhed and pardoned our ſinnes, declaring in one onely Action his ſoueraigne iuſtice, and his infinite mercy: all the triumphes of Emperours are of no value in compariſon of the death of Chriſt;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19245:13"/>
the life of all men are of no value in regard of the death of Ieſus Chriſt; all the Crownes of Kings are not comparable to the Croſſe of Ieſus Chriſt, and all the glory of the world is inferiour to his opprobrie; as it is the ground of our faith, ſo it is the ſumme of our knowledge, to know Ieſus Chriſt crucified.</p>
                  <p>This death taketh away the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe and malediction of our own, and maketh it, that although a farre off it ſeemeth a fantaſie which wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vpon the waters, when it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proacheth and commeth nearer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, we ſhall confeſſe that it is Ieſus Chriſt that commeth vnto vs, and haue by the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, liberty to ſpeake to God, with aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that not onely wee may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore his mercy, but alſo wee may call for iuſtice, ſaying, <hi>Lord, thou are iuſt, and therefore take not two payments for one debt, and correct
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19245:14"/>
me not in thine anger for my ſinnes, for which thy Sonne hath beene puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</hi> By this meanes the iuſtice of God changeth nature towards vs, and of iuſtice iudging, becommeth iuſtice iuſtifying, and of iuſtice which puniſheth ſinne, it becommeth a iuſtice which maketh vs iuſt.</p>
                  <p>And conſider what the Aduocate is, who not onely pleadeth for vs, but payeth for vs; who not onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercedeth for ſinners, but of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners maketh them iuſt: Where is the Phiſitian which taketh the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, and by it healeth his Patient? Hauing ſo indured death for vs, for vs alſo hath ouercome death; as the combat of his death is for vs, ſo the victory of his Reſurrection is ours, after the which hee aſcended into Heauen, from whence he ſendeth his graces; there hee receiueth our ſoules, which he hath bought with his owne bloud: Hee is our onely
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19245:14"/>
aſſurance in the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, to whom wee aſpire and tend vnto, as ſtrangers in this world, but domeſtickes with God; as dying, but heires of eternall life, hauing to reſiſt the Courts of this world, to publique iudgements, to cuſtomes receiued, to the ouer flowing of vices and idolatrie; like vnto diuers kindes of Fiſhes, which alwaies ſwimme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſtreame, and tend towards the Fountaine; attending his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to iudge the quicke and the dead, and raiſe our bodies from the earth, to the end, that in body and ſoule we may raigne with him eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally.</p>
                  <p>Behold my Brethren the ſubſtance of the Goſpell of Chriſt, whereof Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>that hee is not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but glorifieth himſelfe,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding humane iudgements and contradictions, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions wee haue to ſpeake of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19245:15"/>
in the ſecond place, and of the meanes wherewith Sathan and the fleſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ue themſelues, for to make men diſtaſte and be aſhamed of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Chriſt: for Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>that the Goſpell is a ſcandall to the Iewes, and folly to the Greekes,</hi> that is to ſay, that the <hi>Iewes</hi> were offended with it, and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> mocked at it: They were offended to heare ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that God became man, of a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified God, of one that was called the Sonne of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he ſaid, <hi>he was before Abraham was;</hi> They were offended to heare in the Goſpell, where the firſt clauſe thereof begun with <hi>Bleſſed are thoſe that weepe,</hi> and which promiſeth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions to thoſe that follow them, as if it had beene to chaſe away the Hearer; found it ſtrange that Ieſus Chriſt had ſent Diſciples that were Idiots, to confound Philoſophers, poore Fiſhers for to eſtabliſh him
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19245:15"/>
throughout a Kingdome; alſo that the Goſpell is hidden in tearmes ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry ſimple and without eloquence, in a world where humane knowledges were in their height, and humane eloquence was come vp to the top of perfection: theſe things which ſeemed to be of ſo hard digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to humane ſence, neuertheleſſe being more carefully conſidered, they are agreeable to wiſedome, and the power of God.</p>
                  <p>For to ſpeake of the humilitie of the Incarnation of Ieſus Chriſt the Sonne of God, we need not thinke it ſtrange although he were ſo hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, becauſe he was come to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie for our pride; ſeeing that man had ſo farre precipitated himſelfe in deſiring to make himſelfe like vnto God; it was needefull that God ſhould make himſelfe like vnto man for to ſaue him; it was needfull that he ſhould become man to dye, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19245:16"/>
God for to vanquiſh, and that hee might be infinite in riches, becauſe he was to pay an infinite debt.</p>
                  <p>As for the reſt, be not ye ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized for the humilitie of his Birth; but behold the ſtar that then appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, &amp; the Angels that ſung, and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rode</hi> who was afraide. If you thinke it ſtrange that he was hungry, of the other part, behold how he fed fiue thouſand people with a few loaues; if it be a thing vnworthy for the King of Kings to pay Tribute to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> conſider how he cauſed it to be paid with Fiſh. Briefly ſaith the Apoſtle in the ſame Chapter, and the fourth Verſe, <hi>Hee is dead, but hee hath declared himſelfe to be the Sonne of God, &amp;c.</hi> And his diuine vertue appeared more euidently in his infirmitie, euen as the ſplendor of a lightening appeareth better during the Night, then at Noone-day.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:19245:16"/>We haue no cauſe to be offended that he would haue vs take vp his Croſſe after him and prepare our ſelues for ſufferings: For what is there more iuſt then to be partaker of the afflictions of Chriſt, ſeeing we deſire to be partakers of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? Theſe are faire ſpots, and an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable opprobrie for to carry in his Body the wounds of our Lord Ieſus. Is it ſo great a matter to looſe our goods for him that hath loſt his life for our ſaluation? to let fall our teares for him that hath loſt his bloud? to ſuffer corporall death for him that hath purchaſed eternall life for vs? What matter is it to the faithfull, whether hee looſe his life by the mouth, or by a wound, if he dye of a Sword, or a Feauer, ſeeing he dyeth the death of the iuſt, and that his ſoul enters into the promiſed repoſe, with the Children of God?</p>
                  <p>Concerning the condition of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19245:17"/>
Apoſtles, who were Fiſhers and Idi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots, it ſerueth to make Gods worke more admirable, then did the vertue of the Lord appeare better, when humane helpe failed: To vanquiſh ignorance by knowledge, is no ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable thing, but to conuince the knowledge of wiſe men with the ſimplicitie of Idiots, is a worke which none but God could doe, who in an inſtant gaue to ignorant men the knowledge of all Tongues, who changed the Barke of the Apoſtles, into the Church, their Fiſhes into Men, their Nets into Sermons: and of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who was a Wolfe, in an inſtant made him a Lambe; and of a Lambe, an excellent Shepheard; to the end he ſhould know that his vocation came not from Men but God.</p>
                  <p>Concerning ſcandale taken at the rudeneſſe and ſimplicity of the ſtile of the Goſpell, this ſimple ſtile is the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19245:17"/>
ſtile of the Lawes, which ſhould looſe their force, if they were written with the flowers of Rhetoricke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that Kings will not ſhew their eloquence but their authoritie. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it is not reaſonable to apparell a chaſte Virgine in the faſhion of a Strumpet, nor to clothe heauenly wiſedome in fantaſticall and humane knowledge.</p>
                  <p>It may be you thinke, that all this that is ſpoken, is not ſpoken but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Perſecutors and Tyrants, or againſt Pagans and Infidels, who ſtriue to defame the Doctrine of the Goſpell. Let vs not abuſe our ſelues: for euen amongſt our ſelues, there are many to bee found that are aſhamed of the Goſpell of Chriſt. How few are there amongſt vs, that reioyce in the Croſſe of Ieſus Chriſt? who lay all their greatneſſe at the feete of his Croſſe, and glorifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in his approbic? hold it for
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19245:18"/>
certaine, that whoſoeuer reioyceth more in his riches, or in his noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or in his honours, then in the alliance of Ieſus Chriſt, not eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming his true greatneſſe to be one of the children of God through Ieſus Chriſt, ſuch an one is aſhamed of the Goſpell of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Is it not too true that in Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and amongſt our pleaſures, wee are aſhamed of the Goſpell of Chriſt, for at any of theſe meetings, who is he at any time that prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth any ſpeach of Religion, tending to edification, but if ſo happen, hee haue any thought thereof, feare pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently conuerteth him, leaſt he ſhould be thought to bring in an imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent kinde of wiſedome, where men loue better to ſpeake vnciuilly or filthily, or any euill of his friend or Neighbour? which truely decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them to be aſhamed of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell of Chriſt. But if theſe people
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19245:18"/>
ſhould dwell in a Countrey where they ſhould ſuffer perſecution for the cauſe of the Goſpell, how quickely would they turne their backs on Chriſt? For he that is aſhamed of Ieſus Chriſt amongſt his friends, how will he acknowledge him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his enemies? Hee that in a garden, or in company at Table dare not ſpeake of Ieſus Chriſt, how dare he defend him being tortured, or in the fire? how can he ſuſtaine aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, that is thus corrupt in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie?</p>
                  <p>In like ſort, when a ſtormy winde bloweth vpon a Tree that is laden with fruits, and rotten at the heart, it preſently falleth: So when the winde of perſecution getteth vp, we ſee preſently thoſe which haue their hearts thus corrupted with hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, or which hold not of Ieſus Chriſt, but by cuſtome, or for humane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, how can they ſtand. And
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19245:19"/>
thereupon when I read the Hiſtory of Martyrs, the vertue of whom, euen at this day ſuſtaineth our vices, who in our Anceſtors times haue beene ſo liberall of their bloud, and ſo thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty for Gods glory; I finde that they dyed more willingly then wee now ſpeake of the Goſpell; and that they powred out their bloud more willingly for the glory of God, then we at this day ſpend our money for his ſeruice: In ſuch ſort, that if any one of thoſe good ſeruants of God, which haue planted the Church, during perſecution, ſhould now come againe, he could not know his flocke, but would be aſtoniſhed, how in ſo ſhort a time, they are ſo much degenerated. He ſhould finde riches encreaſed, and zeale diminiſhed: more repoſe, but much leſſe vertue. From whence it commeth that the Goſpell is become odious, and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery inſenſibly gotten vp.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:19245:19"/>The infirme ſcandalize our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane humour, and impute our vices to Religion, but God grant you long to preſerue this peace and proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and preſerue your King, vnder whoſe wiſe conduct you liue quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: But you muſt vnderſtand, that the ſecurity of the Kings life, is the piety and innocency of his ſubiects: and the meanes long to preſerue that grace which God hath giuen you, is not to abuſe it, but to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage the time and the Commodity which God hath giuen you, which he hath not giuen to neighbour Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but hath rather ſet before your eyes, as it were for example of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude and obſcure ignorance, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Sathan hath powred out a fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſmoake, euen out of the pits of the <hi>Abiſme,</hi> whileſt that in our owne Countrey ſhineth the clearneſſe of the truth of the Goſpell: to the end that by this compariſon, you may
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19245:20"/>
learne to glorifie God, and not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe and corrupt his bleſſings with ingratitude.</p>
                  <p>Out of all this you are to learne two poynts; Firſt, what the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell of Chriſt is, and next, what it is to be aſhamed of the Goſpell: Now let vs learne the third, which is the reſolution of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> by which he glorifieth himſelfe in the reproch of the Goſpell, and contemneth the miſpriſe of men, ſaying, <hi>I am not aſhamed, &amp;c.</hi> which is the exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he maketh to his diſciple <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, Be not aſhamed of the teſtimony of the Lord Ieſus, but participate of the afflictions of the Goſpell, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the power of God.</hi> This holy Apoſtle knew what the hatred of the world was againſt the Goſpell. Hee knew the <hi>Egyptians</hi> naturally hated the Paſtors, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſaid to his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. He eſteemed it no ſhame to doe that which <hi>Dauid</hi> did; which
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19245:20"/>
is to feed the flocke of his Father, principally thoſe which Ieſus Chriſt hath bought with his bloud; and glorified himſelfe to be Heralde of the Miniſtery of reconciliation, ambaſſadour for Chriſt, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of peace betweene God and men, <hi>2 Cor. 5.</hi> and as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaint af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Iſaiah, Rom. 10.</hi> Oh how faire are the feete of thoſe which declare peace, which ſay to <hi>Sion,</hi> thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome come? He was not aſhamed to beare that burthen which hee himſelfe had carried. For euen as a King maketh a company of Knights of his owne order, of which order he himſelfe is the principall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt hath inſtituted the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the Goſpell, of which or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der he himſelfe is the chiefe, &amp; hath vouchſafed to participate of the ſame charge. Hee was not aſhamed to publiſh to men the Diuine Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, which the Angels themſelues
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19245:21"/>
admired, and were diligent to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold with admiration, euen to the very bottome, as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith: hauing regard to the ſtructure of the Arke of allyance, called the <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,</hi> whereupon the Propitiator was placed, as a figure of Ieſus Chriſt our propitiation: alſo there were put two Cherubins, hauing their heads curled, and their eyes blinded towards the propitiatory, for to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure out vnto vs the attention of the Euangelicall ſpirits, and to admire the myſteries of our Redemption in Ieſus Chriſt: whereupon we need not be diſmayed, if in the firſt of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> the <hi>Bethſemites</hi> hauing taken away the propitiatory for to looke within the Arke, (that is to ſay, to approch to God without Ieſus CHRIST) were conſumed with wounds and mortality.</p>
                  <p>To be ſhort, our Apoſtle was not aſhamed to declare the myſtery of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19245:21"/>
our Reconciliation, which is aboue all other myſteries, euen ſurpaſſing the worke of the creation: For if it be an admirable thing that the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor hath made the creature, it is alſo a thing much more admirable, that the Creator was made a creature. And as for the goods which God hath giuen vs; ſo much difference is there betweene the earthly and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall Paradiſe, betweene the Tree of life, and betweene Ieſus Chriſt; betweene thoſe foure Riuers which runne by the Garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> and theſe other foure, which proceede from Ieſus Chriſt, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> numbreth vnto vs, that he hath been made for vs, <hi>Wiſedome, Iuſtice, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification</hi> and <hi>Redemption;</hi> So much difference is there betweene the goods which wee haue loſt in <hi>Adam,</hi> and thoſe which wee haue offered vnto vs in Ieſus Chriſt: In ſuch ſort, that I dare ſay, this fall of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19245:22"/>
                     <hi>Adam,</hi> hath beene happy for Gods children, and that there was happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in this vnhappineſſe, and if we had not fallen into death, we ſhould not haue come to ſo happy a life.</p>
                  <p>But the principall reaſon why the Apoſtle glorifieth himſelfe to be a meſſenger of the Goſpell, is, that which he expreſſeth in this Text, that it is <hi>the power of God to ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to all beleeuers,</hi> that is to ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the ſauing vertue of God, by which hee ſaueth all beleeuers. For the Goſpel is the meanes which ſerueth to purifie mens harts. <hi>Now you are cleane through the Word of God which I haue ſpoken vnto you, Ioh. 15.</hi> As the Spettle comming out of mans mouth makes Serpents dye, ſo that which commeth out of the mouth of faithfull Paſtors, maketh wicked de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires dye, which are a legion of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticall ſpirits that hold correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency with the Diuell. It is by the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19245:22"/>
Word of God, which God toucheth the hearts of the repentant, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printeth Faith in them. For <hi>Faith is by hearing, and hearing by the Word of God.</hi> It is a powerfull means which by a ſweet violence, and by a neceſſity vnconſtrained, directeth the hearts and draweth them into the way of ſaluation, by reaſon of the efficacy, whereof he is called the arme of the Lord, becauſe God by this meanes handleth the ſoules, and pulleth them out of the power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, leading them into the way of ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle in the fourth to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> compareth it to a two edged ſword, becauſe of the double vertue. <hi>Ieremy</hi> calleth it a fire and a Trowell which breaketh the ſtones, for it warmeth the hearts with zeale, and tameth the hardneſſe thereof. For as God writ with his finger the Law in ſtone, ſo he engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19245:23"/>
his Goſpell in our hard and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious hearts, by the efficacy of his holy Spirit, which is the <hi>finger of God.</hi> Which I ſpeake of the rather, fearing that ſome ſhould thinke by their eloquence to giue efficacy to the Word of God; Beleeue it not in any ſort: for that vertue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto him, and to euery man al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, euen from the Spirit of God, which giueth it efficacy, without the which the Word of God is but a dead letter, &amp; a tinkling ſound in the ayre. We beat your eares, but God toucheth your hearts; we caſt the ſeed, but God ſendeth the raine, and maketh the Sunne of benediction light vpon him: He which <hi>plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth,</hi> and hee which <hi>watereth</hi> is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but hee that giueth <hi>the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Who was euer more eloquent then <hi>Iſay?</hi> and his quality alſo ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to enforce attention; for hee
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19245:23"/>
was of the blood-royall; neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, he complaineth that he labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in vaine, and none would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in his preaching; to the end that thoſe whom God employeth in this worke, if they would haue their labour to proſper, they muſt impute all to the bleſſing of God, and not to their owne induſtry and ſufficiency. Beſides, they muſt looke well about them, and not apply themſelues to the proud diſtaſte of their Auditors, who in this Age deſire eloquence, more then ſolidity; who would haue words without matter, and ſawces without meate; who would haue their eares tickled, and not their conſciences pricked: like vnto a wicked Porter, who will not let an honeſt man enter in at the gate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is not well apparelled.</p>
                  <p>In the meane while, this is not the way to profit in the Word of God. Doe you thinke with the flowers of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19245:24"/>
eloquence you can perſwade a man to ſuffer Martyrdome? or with fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures &amp; faire words, you can comfort a man at the houre of death? Is not the Goſpell the medicine of our ſoules? What auaileth it for the Phiſitian to be eloquent, if his medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine be wholeſome? Is not the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell the letter of grace and abolition of our crime? then what matter is it in what termes it be written, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it bringeth vs out of capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie?</p>
                  <p>God in the Olde Teſtament com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded that his Altar ſhould bee built with vnpolliſhed ſtones, to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie that he loued ſimplicity in his ſeruice, be aſſured of it, that hee that hath moſt profited in a Sermon, is not he that ſaith, This man ſpoke ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well: but he that ſaith, Oh I haue led an euill life: how farre am I from the rules that this man hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded? It is not he that wayeth
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19245:24"/>
periods of ſpeeches, but hee that ſoundeth his own conſcience: Thoſe that ruminated were marked for cleane beaſts: you ſhall be cleane and agreeable ſacrifices to God, if you ruminate and meditate in your ſelues the Word of God.</p>
                  <p>I am certainely perſwaded that all my Brethren and Companions in the worke of the LORD would wiſh with me that we were without words, ſo you were without vices; and that wee were deſpiſed, ſo God might be glorified. If they would haue efficacie in their Sermons, they muſt ſpeake with a holy boldneſſe, as God ſpeaking by their mouth, that they flatter not ſinners, but in good earneſt, make them feele their ſinnes, without exception of perſons, or flattering the great ones.</p>
                  <p>A rich man is taught no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then a poore. Selfe-ſame me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines ſerue for little and great.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19245:25"/>
Euen ſo it is in ſpirituall medicines. Sermons without reprehenſions, are like Swords without points, or Lampes where Oyle is powred in without enlightening of them: To feare to touch the ſinner, leſt hee ſhould offend him, is a cruell reſpect, like vnto him that feareth to ſaue a man that is in drowning, leſt hee ſhould hurt his arme, or pull ſome of his haire away.</p>
                  <p>Theſe wholeſome effects of the Word of God, are not without faith, without which the Word can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not take roote, or fructifie in our ſoules, as the Apoſtle in the fourth to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> ſaith, that <hi>hearing of the Word hath not profited them, becauſe it was not mingled with faith.</hi> Whereof S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo after he hath ſaide, that the Goſpell is the power of God, addeth to <hi>euery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuer.</hi> This faith is not an hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call faith, as that is of the Church of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19245:25"/>
                     <hi>Rome,</hi> which onely beleeueth in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, that all that which is contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the word of God is true; but it is a faith which hath knowledge added to beliefe; which beſides the generall knowledge, applyeth the word of God in particular, not onely ſaying that Ieſus Chriſt dyed for ſinners, but alſo addeth with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> the ſecond to the <hi>Galat. Ieſus Chriſt hath loued me, and hath giuen his ſoule for me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Neither is it an inforced, or cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumuenting faith, by the which they beleeue what the Church beleeueth, or what the Curate beleeueth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowing what they ought to beleeue, neither wherefore this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of the Church is the better. One cannot beleeue by Aduocate, neither is a man ſaued by the beliefe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; He that is perſwaded that ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can beleeue for him, is in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that another ſhall be in Paradiſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19245:26"/>
for him. <hi>Habacucke</hi> telleth vs, <hi>The iuſt ſhall liue by faith;</hi> then he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not liue by the faith of another.</p>
                  <p>Alſo it is not a faith of Miracles, whereof the greatneſſe of a graine of Muſtard-ſeede can tranſport moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, but the greatneſſe of a Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of this faith cannot remoue a ſoule out of hell into heauen, which chaſeth into another, wicked ſpirits, but cannot chaſe from it ſelfe wicked deſires; which healeth corporall maladies: in another, but cannot heale his owne ſoule from ſpirituall maladies: but it is a faith which receiueth the promiſes of Ieſus Chriſt with ioy, which imbraceth him as good newes ſent from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, who applyeth himſelfe to the words which the Apoſtle ſaid to the blinde Man that Ieſus called, be of good courage, the Maſter calleth thee: it is a faith that disburdeneth his ſinnes vpon Ieſus Chriſt, which
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19245:26"/>
giueth repoſe and peace to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which beholdeth the Booke of the Goſpell with the ſame eye that a faithfull husband beholdeth his contract in marriage, or a good Sonne that beholds the will of his Father, who by it is incited to loue God, and to glorifie him in workes and words, iuſt in his actions, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in proſperity, patient in aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, charitable to the Church, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in zeale of the houſe of God.</p>
                  <p>For without theſe things, faith is a name without a thing, a ſhadow without a Body, and in ſtead of a beliefe, a confuſion and ſpirituall le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargie: without this faith wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pleaſe God, <hi>Heb. 11.</hi> without this faith, wee make God a lyar, as doubting of the truth of his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; without this faith wee expoſe our ſelues naked to the temptations of the aduerſary, for it is a Buckler to beate backe the fiery darts of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19245:27"/>
Be not yee then amazed that the bleſſings of Ieſus Chriſt are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for all; yet neuertheleſſe all cannot be ſaued, becauſe that all haue not faith: for misbeliefe reiecteth the remedies which God preſenteth, and ouerthroweth the medicine. This faith ought to be nouriſhed and fortified by prayer, by the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the word of God, by holy companies, by all ſort of good workes; and although after all that, infirmitie remaineth in you, feare not your ſaluation, with a trembling hand giue not ouer taking of Almes.</p>
                  <p>All thoſe which beheld the braſen Serpent, had not their ſights equally good, and neuertheleſſe were equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly healed. God requireth not of vs a perfect faith, but true without hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, and which indeauoureth to fortifie it ſelfe, and ſaith as the father of him that was poſſeſſed, <hi>I beleeue Lord, but helpe my infirmitie.</hi> God
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19245:27"/>
which hath put theſe Treaſures in a Veſſell of earth, which perfecteth his grace in our infirmitie, in time of neceſſitie ſuſtaineth our feebleneſſe, aboue all at the houre of death, there he drieth vp the drops of bloud, he ſaith to the faithfull ſoule, <hi>feare not, Chriſt Ieſus is beſides thee, which ſheweth thee a Crowne.</hi> The faith of the faithfull cannot be confounded, like the Nodes of Compaſſes in the middeſt of the ſea remaine vnmoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able amidſt the Tempeſt, becauſe they gouerne themſelues not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the windes, but according to heauen: euen ſo the faith of the faithfull remaineth firme amongſt the moſt rude agitations, becauſe it gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it ſelf not according to the inſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie of the affaires of this world, but according to the promiſes of God.</p>
                  <p>But to the end, that euery one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inuited to receiue this grace, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme himſelfe not excluded, by his
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19245:28"/>
quality, his kindred, or his condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> addeth, that this ſaluation <hi>is addreſſed to the Iewes firſt, and afterwards to the Greekes;</hi> leauing vs by this example to gather this generall Rule that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> propoundeth, <hi>Acts</hi> the tenth, and thirty foure, <hi>God hath no reſpect of perſons:</hi> for Ieſus Chriſt by the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Gentiles, hath broken the partition betweene the <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles;</hi> yet neuertheleſſe Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> putting the <hi>Iewes</hi> in the firſt place, as hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the defence which God made to his Diſciples; <hi>Goe not into the way of the Gentiles.</hi> Whereof alſo hee ſaid, were ſent <hi>to the loſt ſheepe of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell.</hi> Following the ſame example, Saint <hi>Paul, Acts 13.46.</hi> ſpeaketh alſo to the incredulous <hi>Iewes, It was neceſſary that the word of God ſhould firſt haue beene ſpoken vnto you, but ſeeing you put it from you, &amp;c.</hi> By
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19245:28"/>
this meanes, the firſt haue beene the laſt, and the eldeſt Sonne hath beene made inferiour to the prodigall childe returned to repentance.</p>
                  <p>Then happened that to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> which happened to <hi>Gedeons</hi> fleece, which in the beginning was onely watered, whileſt all the land beſides was dry; but the day after the fleece was dry onely, and all the earth wholy watered; for vpon the <hi>Iewes</hi> onely in former times, the dewe of the grace of God rained downe, but afterwards it hath ſo come to paſſe, that they are depriued of this grace, and other Nations receiued into Gods fauour. For this purpoſe, the holy Scripture ſpeaking of thoſe which are out of the Church of God, ſaith, <hi>that they are in outward darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> becauſe in <hi>Egypt</hi> onely God gaue light to his people, whileſt all <hi>Egypt</hi> beſides round about were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uironed with outward darkeneſſe.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19245:29"/>
But at the death of Ieſus Chriſt there happened the contrarie: for darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was onely ouer all <hi>Iudea,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, whileſt the reſt of the earth was inlightned; then at that time, the darkeneſſe was interiour, and the light exteriour; God ſignifying by this miracle the reiecting of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and reception of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> which is a great aduertiſement vnto vs: For if they did ſo with greene wood, what ſhall become of the dry wood? If the naturall branches haue beene ſo handled, what will become of wilde branches ingrafted in their places, if we ſinne with like incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie? For, hath God bound himſelfe alwaies to protect his Churches which abuſe his grace, and bring blame vpon the doctrine of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell? Let vs tremble at ſuch exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and preuent Gods iudgements by repentance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:19245:29"/>It remaineth my Brethren, to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fruit from this doctrine, for our inſtruction &amp; conſolation. Firſt, this excellencie of the Goſpell of Chriſt, wherewith God declareth his incomprehenſible loue in giuing his Sonne for mortall man, for ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, for his enemies, for the ſlaues of the Diuell, to the end to make them his ſeruants, euen his friends, and euen his Brethren, a Body and a Spirit with him, and by it, heires of eternall life; ſo many ſweet inuite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which biddeth vs come to him; ſo many promiſes to giue vs all that which we ſhal aske in his Sonnes Name, ſerueth for the comfort of all conſciences that are oppreſſed with the burthen of their ſinnes, to the end, that when the horrour of the iudgement of God, preſenteth it ſelfe before their eyes, they preſently turne their eyes towards the ſacred bleſſing of Ieſus Chriſt, towards the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19245:30"/>
bloud of allyance, which cryeth bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things then that of <hi>Abell,</hi> which cryeth vengeance, but this crieth peace and reconciliation.</p>
                  <p>If the Conſcience take ſome by the throat, and dragge him before the Iudiciall Throne of God, it will bring forth before God this acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ſuſtained with the bloud of the Sonne of God, by which God declareth that he is fully content and ſatisfied.</p>
                  <p>If Sathan produceth before God his accuſations againſt vs, and bringeth in a long ſedule of our ſinnes, ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, I doe not excuſe my ſelfe, but ſet downe vnderneath, <hi>The bloud of Ieſus Chriſt doth cleanſe vs from all our ſinnes, 1 Ioh. 1.7.</hi> and alſo theſe ſinnes which thou bringeſt in againſt mee, are not my ſinnes, but the ſinnes of Ieſus Chriſt, ſeeing hee hath taken them vpon him: as on the other part, his righteouſneſſe is
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:19245:30"/>
ours, for hee is our eternall righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, <hi>and by the obedience of a Man, many ſhall be made iuſt, Rom. 5.19.</hi> Hee who is dead for his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, will he not heare his friends? He that prayed vpon the Croſſe for thoſe that crucified him, will he not intercede in his glory for thoſe which put their truſt in him? God which vnderſtandeth the cry of the little Crowes in their neſts, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaith in the 147. <hi>Pſ.</hi> will he not heare his Children that call vpon him? Should his promiſes be falſe, or the death of his Sonne without effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie towards thoſe that beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt?</p>
                  <p>In the ſecond place, the Miniſters of the word of God haue here a faire leſſon, for the Apoſtle exhorteth them; by his example, not to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but to reioyce that they are the Miniſters of the Goſpell of Chriſt, and to make account of their charge:
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19245:31"/>
not becauſe it giueth them occaſion to be well apparelled, and plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fed with ſmall trauaile, whileſt they leaue to others the care of their flocke, which afterwards is often negligently taught and inſtructed; but becauſe they mannage the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Kingdome of Heauen, which is his Word, and that God hath conſecrated their mouthes to ſignifie vnto men his holy will.</p>
                  <p>In the third place, that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Goſpell of Chriſt which they deliuer, to the end, they mingle not humane inuentions, nor vaine ſubtilties, nor diuerſities of tongues, to eſtabliſh their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; if they would haue their prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching effectuall to touch mens hearts, &amp; to retaine this power of God to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation to thoſe that heare; and that they offer not to God a ſtrange fire, like <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu;</hi> that they remember themſelues of the Law,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19245:31"/>
which forbiddeth to ſow two kindes of Corne in one field, or to make a ſtuffe of diuers ſorts of matter: God teaching vs thereby, that he will not haue an artificiall mingling in his ſeruice, and alſo they muſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that which they preach be the Goſpell of Chriſt. Euen as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles which had fiſhed all the night and got nothing; but when at the word of the Lord they caſt their Nets, they got great ſtore of Fiſh: Euen ſo, if you caſt the nets of your ſermons by the word of Ieſus Chriſt, and follow his commandements, you ſhall draw ſoules vnto you, and ſee fruit of your labour. If you diſtribute nothing but the bread of Chriſt which hee hath put into his hands, you ſhall perceiue it to increaſe, and to multiply it ſelfe in your hands, and the bleſſing of God to be pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out vpon your trauaile.</p>
                  <p>Seeing that the Goſpell is the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19245:32"/>
ſauing-power of God, let let vs take heed aboue all, we take not away this efficacie by a wicked life, contrary to our preaching. For as the ſtaffe of <hi>Elizeus</hi> had not the ſame vertue in the hand of <hi>Gehazi,</hi> that it had in <hi>Elizeus</hi> hand; ſo the inſtructions that are in the mouth of a man fearing God, are full of force, but in the mouth of a prophane Miniſter they haue no vertue at all; and therefore the eternall hath ſaid to the wicked: <hi>Wherefore doſt thou take my words in thy mouth?</hi> And Ieſus Chriſt commanded Sathan to hold his tongue, when he cryed, <hi>thou art the Chriſt, the Sonne of God:</hi> knowing that the Goſpell in the mouth of the Diuell loſeth the authority. For the people will neuer truely beleeue the Paſtor, as long as they ſee him do the contrary, and be like the Trumpets, who incourage to the Combat, and keepe themſelues out of the Battaile,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19245:32"/>
or like him thar carrieth the Lantern, and ſeeth the leaſt. How will you that the people ſhould come to be ſober and modeſt in apparell, to be chaſt and holy in words, if the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters be diſordered, ſumptuous in apparell, and contemners of the name of God? How would you that the people ſhould be turned from their idleneſſe, and from Theaters, and vnchaſte loues and lechery, if the Paſtor himſelfe be giuen to it? Wherefore, as in the time of <hi>Heli</hi> the ſacrificer, becauſe of the ſinnes of his Children, the Oblation was not accepted: Euen ſo becauſe of the vices of Preachers, the people miſpriſe Preaching. For which cauſe howſoeuer eloquent and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned they be, they cannot eſcape the Iudgement of God; they ſhall be like the Carpenters which builded the Arke, and yet were drowned in the floud; or like the Tirrians, Sido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19245:33"/>
who furniſhed <hi>Salomon</hi> with Materials for the building of the Temple, and yet notwithſtanding were ſtrangers of the houſe of God, and his allyance.</p>
                  <p>In generall Brethren, wee exhort you in the name of God, and for the compaſſion of the Lord, by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious bloud of his allyance, by the honour which you haue to be the Children of God, for that you are deſirous of Gods glory, and your owne ſaluation, that you cheriſh and eſteeme the Goſpell of Chriſt, and not be careleſſe of this grace of God, to haue made ſhine in this Country ſo clearely the cleareneſſe of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell; for it is arriued in theſe quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that which happened in <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> then when the Law was hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the Temple, and they thought it to be loſt, it was found againe and came to light: As to the wiſe men, who reioyced with great ioy at the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19245:33"/>
ſight of the blaſing Starre which brought them to Ieſus Chriſt: As to Saint <hi>Iohn, Apoc. 5.</hi> who wept that there was none found worthy to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the booke becauſe of the ſeales, but afterwards hee was comforted, for that the Lambe of God, which was alſo called the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Iuda,</hi> came before and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the booke, to manifeſt to men the will of God. You are of thoſe to whom it was manifeſted with moſt cleareneſſe, with leaſt trouble and incommoditie: But take heede that you be not of the number of thoſe that Saint <hi>Iude</hi> ſpeaketh of, who turne the grace of God into diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and with Gods patience are become idle and negligent.</p>
                  <p>Take heed that the eaſe of the world do not make you forget what the Croſſe of Chriſt is. Know that although God exempt you to flie from your Countrey for the Goſpel,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19245:34"/>
ſo it is that you ought to liue like Trauellers and Strangers on the earth; for as much as God exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth you from the Croſſe, that you ought to crucifie your fleſh, and mortifie euery affection. Although you looſe not your goods for Chriſts Goſpell, yet ought you to be ready to looſe and to poſſeſſe, as not poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, being charitable to the poore, making you friends of vniuſt riches which will receiue you into euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Tabernacles.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things are repreſented vnto you by your Paſtors, with more Doctrine both of grace and famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity. But it is good that God bee glorified in euery tongue, and that you acknowledge the ioy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light which the Stranger Churches doe receiue of Gods benedictions poured out vpon you, and the vnion which is betweene you in the ſame Doctrine and vnion of Faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:19245:34"/>The God of Heauen, who hath giuen his Sonne for our Sauiour, poure downe his graces from aboue, vpon your gracious King, &amp; inſpire him more and more with holy reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions for the good of his Church; and conduct by his holy Spirit, the Paſtors of his flocke; abundantly bleſſe the people which is choſen for his inheritance, to the end that after hee ſhall bee ſerued of you, to glorifie his Name in this world, he may glorifie you in Heauen. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19245:35"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19245:35"/>
                  <p>THE COMFORT OF A Communicant: Jn a Sermon made before the receiuing of the COMMVNION; By <hi>Peter Moulin,</hi> Miniſter in the Reformed Church at PARIS.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T.S.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Pauier,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Iuie lane.</hi> 1623.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19245:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19245:36"/>
                  <head>A SERMON, made before the receiuing of the COMMVNION.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>LVKE 2. VER. 28.29.30.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>28</bibl> Simeon tooke the Child in his armes, and bleſſed God, and ſaid,</p>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>29</bibl> Lord, now letteſt thou thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant depart in peace, according to thy Word.</p>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>30</bibl> For mine eyes haue ſeene thy ſaluation.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OV know that in all Contracts of Marriage, there is ſpeach of death: but the alliance of Ieſus Chriſt with vs is a ſpirituall marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age: The contract of this marriage,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19245:37"/>
is that which we call the Goſpell; a Contract, whereof the Apoſtles haue beene the Writers, and Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe hath ſealed it with his bloud. Let it not ſeeme ſtrange vnto you then, if we ſpeake of death to day, and of the preparation to die, becauſe we are to ſpeake vnto you of a contract of marriage, and of our coniunction with the onely Sonne of the Eternall God.</p>
                  <p>For theſe Sacraments which wee adminiſter vnto you at this Holy Table, are kinds of aſſurances, which ſerue vs as pledges of the aſſurance that Ieſus Chriſt is ours.</p>
                  <p>Now although the conſummati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this marriage, ſhall not fully be made but in the kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; and that no man can enter in but at this gate, which is called death, which in times paſt was the gate of Hell, but Ieſus Chriſt hath altered and tranſported it from that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19245:37"/>
place, and hath made it the port of Heauen; from whence it followeth that no man can thinke of Ieſus Chriſt and our coniunction with him, but he muſt alſo thinke of death.</p>
                  <p>There is nothing more neerely conioyned together, then the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of life, and the preparation to death: it is impoſſible for vs to thinke of Ieſus Chriſt, but preſently we muſt thinke that by his death, he hath taken away the bitterneſſe and malediction of death, like vnto that wood that being caſt into the water of <hi>Mara,</hi> it maketh it ſweete and wholeſome. It is impoſſible to loue Ieſus Chriſt as wee ought, but preſently this life muſt needs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come vnpleaſant, which hindereth vs from going to him, vntill death put an ende to our baniſhment, and bring vs neere vnto his preſence.</p>
                  <p>Know then my Brethren, that theſe benefits, by which God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19245:38"/>
you liue, teacheth you happily to dye; and with this foode of life alſo teacheth you the preparations and conſolations to die. You haue not meanly profited, if at your going away from the Sacrament, you ſay with <hi>Simeon, Lord, now let thou thy ſeruant depart in peace, according to thy Word: For mine eyes haue ſeene thy ſaluation:</hi> and if you carry from hence a full confidence, it will make you victorious againſt the terrours of death, for if you haue this ſaluation which <hi>Simeon</hi> ſpeaketh of, it will bring you vnto a great peace of conſcience, which is a beginning of that peace whereinto <hi>Simeon</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth to enter.</p>
                  <p>Of this (my Brethren) you eaſily conceiu what the Text meaneth, for although it ſeemeth not to ſpeake of the Holy Supper, yet it is not very farre from the meaning thereof: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that this Sacrament renueth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19245:38"/>
vnto vs the Contract of marriage, and that the promiſes which are heere propounded, are certaine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies and preparations againſt death.</p>
                  <p>Whereof the Ancients were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to ſend to the ſicke, from the Holy Table, and at the ſame time of the action and adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Simeon</hi> who dyed when Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt was borne, who being full of yeeres, waited with impatience the comming of Chriſt Ieſus, to the end to raiſe himſelfe from the ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinell, and to ſet his ſoule at libertie; teacheth vs with what firmeneſſe, we ought to attend death, and with what deſire to receiue him.</p>
                  <p>The life of man is not long la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting; ſome commeth weeping, ſome commeth in labour, ſome with paine, and the abiding is ſo ſhort, that man ordinarily dyeth then, when hee
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19245:39"/>
hath but newly learned what it is to liue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaid that his dayes had been ſhort and euill, although hee liued vntill he was a hundred thirtie and three yeeres: how ſhort are ours then, who rarely come to the halfe of that age, and neuertheleſſe ſleepe and ſorrow muſt likewiſe be taken away; for in that time we liue not? and moſt people die in the flower of their age, with their Candle extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed before it be halfe burnt out.</p>
                  <p>The Holy Scripture calleth death, the way of all the earth: it is a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall debt, which if a man ſhould deny, it were as much as pleading a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his owne deed: to ſtriue to be exempt, is to deſire to be exempt from the generall Law, and to deſire, that God for the loue of thee, ſhould change the Lawes of the world, and make for thee another humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:19245:39"/>When death commeth it is in vaine to ſay any thing; as Pope <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> ſaith in his Dialogues, of one whoſe name was <hi>Stephen,</hi> that tolde Death being ſicke, he was miſtaken, and it was not he. The Pagans who haue made Altars and ſeruices to vices and ſickeneſſes, to feare an euill happe neuer adreſſed any to death, becauſe they were aſſured that ſhee was alwayes inexorable, and will entertaine no tearmes of compoſition.</p>
                  <p>This neceſſity being ſo ſtrong, and examples ſo frequent in ſuch ſort, that although we daily bury our neighbours, and carry and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany to the earth the one halfe of our ſelues, yet wee looke another way both in minde and heart, ſtill holding on the ſame courſe wee haue beene accuſtomed vnto, as if wee ſhould neuer dye. For our deſignes, wee make large liued, and taske our
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19245:40"/>
ſelues to eſtabliſh our Name vpon earth, ſpending &amp; lauiſhing out the time, as if we had but ouermuch: ſtill taking out by handfuls, out of the ſacke, with an aſſured preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, neuer to be empty. We would haue long life, to looſe it: as if wee ſhould accuſe God, that it is too long, becauſe we employ it in things either vnprofitable or wicked. If any man in company ſpeake of death, it ſhall be eſteemed trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, vnfaſhionable, and imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, as if there were neuer any vſe of ſuch thoughts. Yet being truely conſidered, there is no thought or meditation ſo neceſſary: It is better, ſaith <hi>Salomon, Eccleſ. 7. To enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the houſe of ſorrow, then into the houſe of ioy;</hi> From hence is deriued the placing of Churchyards round about the Churches, to the end that men may paſſe by the Graues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they preſent themſelues before
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19245:40"/>
God: that is, to thinke and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate well of death, before wee come to looke for life, and that firſt wee muſt acknowledge our ſelues mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals and ſinners, before we can come to implore the grace of God. There is a great accord betweene the feare of God, and the remembrance of death: for the thought of death ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs feare God, and the feare of God comforteth vs againſt death. This thought diſpoſeth vs to liue well, becauſe the day of death is the day when wee muſt make our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to God. As Death ſhall finde vs, ſo ſhall the laſt day iudge vs; For it will be too late to ſpeake for our ſelues vpon the gybbet; it will bee too late to iuſtifie our ſelues, when we are encompaſſed with Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; it behoueth therefore to make our peace whileſt we haue time, and to fortifie our ſelues with faith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the terrours of Gods Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19245:41"/>
let vs mannage the time, and liue as the faithfull die; that is, liue as we would haue wiſhed to haue liued, when we muſt die; this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration maketh a man couragious: for what can he feare that feareth not death? whoſoeuer hopeth for death, ſhall not feare the ſorrows of life; The threatnings of a Tyrant threatning death, are promiſes vnto him: He will ſhorten the ſorrowes of the faithfull, hee will open the doore of the priſon of his ſoule to ſet it at liberty. To thinke to looſe a Man that feareth God in killing him, is like him that in anger throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a Fiſh away into a Riuer to drowne it: for it is there where it liueth, and in that death it findeth life.</p>
                  <p>This holy ſeruant of God <hi>Simeon,</hi> carefully prepared himſelfe, becauſe he hath not onely attended death, but alſo runne before to meet it by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19245:41"/>
the way. For hee knew well hee ſhould die, ſo ſoone as hee had ſeene Ieſus Chriſt: and no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner had hee heard tell that Ieſus Chriſt was borne, and carryed to the Temple, without delay or detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the time with himſelfe, in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, although he be borne, yet I haue time enough to ſee him without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any great haſte; and I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce to ſee him great: The deſire to prolong life neuer came into his minde: but without let or ſtaying at all, goes before Ieſus Chriſt: that is to ſay, before death, although that Ieſus Chriſt was the Prince of life: he attendeth not vntill he be entred into the Temple, but meeteth him at the doore, with ioy imbraceth him, and humbleth his olde age be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the infancy of Ieſus Chriſt, and deſireth to dye, ſeeing that hee hath ſeene the beginning of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, which was all hee
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19245:42"/>
could ſee vpon earth: for to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe he ſaide, is Ieſus Chriſt come ſo farre, from the very higheſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uens to viſite me, &amp; wherfore ſhoul-not I goe before him? and how ſweet will death be now vnto mee, hauing ſeene him who is come to take away all malediction?</p>
                  <p>You may ſay peraduenture, that this good man made too great haſte: firſt, for it was ſufficient for Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an conſtancy to attend euils with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out haſtening them, and to forbeare vntill they fall of themſelues. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that it is a loſſe for the Church, that ſuch a holy man as <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon,</hi> ſhould bee taken from the world, whoſe life was an edification to the Church. Thirdly, and that he abandoned his wife and his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, in hauing no more care of them and his family. Fourthly, and in concluſion, that Death is an euill which Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, as man
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19245:42"/>
feared, hauing prayed that the <hi>Cup might paſſe from him;</hi> and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter</hi> was dragged to Martyrdome, after a ſort, againſt his will.<note place="margin">They ſhal lead thee whither thou wouldeſt not. <hi>Ioh.</hi>
                     </note> And Ieſus Chriſt wept for the death of <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> although he had reſolued to raiſe him vp againe. Firſt, to this I anſwere: the faithfull ought not to run to death, but we ought to follow when God calleth: Now God called <hi>Simeon,</hi> and by the promiſe which was made, that he ſhould not dye vntill he had ſeene the Meſſias, hee knew that his houre was come. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, many ſay that the death of a holy man is a loſſe to the Church. I anſwere, that God preſerueth thoſe that he will employ for the ſeruice thereof, as Ieſus Chriſt ſaid when the Souldiers held him, <hi>If you ſeeke for me, let theſe goe;</hi> for he would employ them: if he meane to take any away, he will find other meanes to perfect his worke. <hi>Moſes</hi> did
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19245:43"/>
bring the people out of Egypt, and led <hi>Iſrael</hi> forty yeares, euen to the very border, and conquered ſome part of the land beyond <hi>Iorden,</hi> yet dyed euen at the very entrance thereof: but God raiſed <hi>Ioſuah,</hi> to whom he gaue ſtrength to effect it. <hi>Dauid</hi> had proiected the building of of the Temple, and gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the materials, and made choiſe of the place, but God would not that he ſhould lay the foundation, but ordained <hi>Salomon</hi> for that worke. It is the worke of God, to the which hee prouideth workemen alwayes according to his prouidence. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, may another ſay, but he abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his wife, his children and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. This which ſeemeth to be a kind of cruelty, is farre better then all cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, that ſmothereth all naturall affection to obey God, which was the cauſe that made <hi>Abraham</hi> reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute to ſacrifice his ſonne, which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19245:43"/>
made the Leuites draw their ſwords againſt their brethren and kindred, for to obey the commandements of God. <hi>Simeon</hi> at his death was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to obey him, and to refuſe his family, to follow God: Beſides, hee knew his family in this affliction wanted no conſolation, for it might comfort and arme it ſelfe with theſe conſiderations.</p>
                  <p>How vainely would we reſiſt the will of God, and kicke againſt the prickes? God is wiſe, and doth all for the beſt, and for cauſes onely knowne to himſelfe. Life is not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs in propriety, but lent vs; the Terme is not according to our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, but according to his ordinance: We make vp our account amiſſe, and thinke we enioy our life as if it were our owne; or elſe we doe not looke that God ſhould take it way ſo ſoone: by which meanes the moſt of the ſorrow proceedeth not from
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19245:44"/>
the nature of the euill it ſelfe, but from our ſelues, and our careleſneſſe, and want of attendance. The Holy Scripture ſaith thereupon very well, <hi>That hee hath rendred his ſpirit:</hi> &amp; <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>I render my ſoule in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy hands, for thou haſt bought me.</hi> What would this word of <hi>render</hi> my ſoule ſignifie, but onely to ſhew vnto vs that God demaundeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but that which belongeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him? as Saint <hi>Luke</hi> 12. ſaith, <hi>To morrow ſhall thy ſoule be asked for,</hi> and principally thoſe whom Ieſus Chirſt hath bought with his blood and precious ſufferings. When hee calleth vs away, hee doth like the buyer, that would haue that hee paide for: And wee ought to ſay with <hi>Dauid, I render my ſoule into thy hands, for thou haſt bought it,</hi> and haſt bought it, not to enrich thy ſelfe, but to better it.</p>
                  <p>It will be well done in our dolours
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19245:44"/>
and domeſticke ſorrowes to looke vpon others, and to behold the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of their Countryes and Cities: So many battels, where fifty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men haue beene ſlaine; where ſo many Cities haue beene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed; where Kings haue beene ſlaine in the middle of the Army, or amiddeſt their triumphs: and wee ſhall finde our owne miſeries indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent tollerable in compariſon of theirs, hauing cauſe to accuſe our ſelues of delicacy, liuing but too effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minately, eſpecially, when we come to beholde the wounds of the Church, the forepaſt maſſacres, with the executions &amp; burnings of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny faithfull people in the Kingdome of Sathan, vnder the which the Church breatheth ſo hardly: then I ſay, if we be diſpoſed as we ſhould be, we will be much more grieued with ſuch a generall miſery, then with our owne particular: for it is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19245:45"/>
but of ſmall importance to haue do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticke euils in our owne houſe, in compariſon of the miſeries that the world doth ſuffer. It is a ſmall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter when God taketh one of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants from the world, in compariſon of the ſtreetes when they runne with the blood of the faithfull, maſſacred by blaſphemous and bloody vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines. You who are conſtant in publike afflictions, where God is blaſphemed, wherefore ſhould you be careleſſe in particular, that dwell where Gods name is called vpon? wherefore ſhould you be ſo ſenſible for your domeſticall grieuances, and ſo inſenſible of the wounds of the Church? If any ſorrow more for the loſſe of their owne, then for the affliction of the Church, I ſay, his teares is cruell againſt the Church, and it is a ſigne of his little zeale to the glory of God. When Sathan holdeth the Church by the throate,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19245:45"/>
we ſhould be glad to comfort it; Yet in the affliction of our familie, wee grow ſo paſſionate, that we reiect all conſolation; although with drie eyes, we can be content to ſee for the publike good, millions of people thronging downe to Hell: and if God take away from amongſt vs a ſoule hee loueth, or if he take away a wife, or a ſonne, or a husband, then we looſe all conſtancy, and our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion is to murmure againſt him?</p>
                  <p>It is very neceſſary that theſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticke ſorrowes be maſtred by a greater power, and that the zeale to the houſe of God may command vs and poſſeſſe vs, as <hi>Dauid</hi> in the 66. Pſalme, ſaith, <hi>The zeale of thy houſe hath eaten me.</hi> Aboue all we faile in our Teares; for when we haue ſeene a friend die that was deare vnto vs, and ſeene him die the death of the righteous, with a holy ioy, and goe out of this world, like one that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19245:46"/>
out of priſon, that is to ſay, with cheerefulneſſe, and aſſurance of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation; yet neuertheleſſe wee make too much lamentation for him, which is wrong to Ieſus Chriſt, as if his children were with him in miſery; it is alſo a wrong to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, for if wee ſhould but taſte a few drops, and behold but the ſparkles of the glory and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which they receiue with God, we would ſay, our teares are iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious; and wherfore ſhould we enuy their repoſe? Doubtleſſe if our tears could bring him againe, we ought not, to doe it; for they would ſay, Wherefore haſt thou troubled our reſt, and brought our ſoules againe into this filthineſſe, and put vs againe into the combat, after the victory? They had rather that we would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our ſelues to goe to them; and that we will thinke they are not loſt, but gone before vs; and let our
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19245:46"/>
chiefe worke bee to prepare our ſelues to dye, inſtead of mourning for them: and turne our mourning, with a holy feare, into a holy care, and deepe contemplation. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the reaſon why God ſo ſoone taketh from vs thoſe we ſo much affect, is, that hee would haue a pledge of vs in taking the one halfe of our ſelues vnto him, to the end we may ſo diſpoſe of our ſelues, that he may alſo haue the reſt, and that all our deſires may runne that way; in ſo much that there be nothing in the houſe, nor in the chambers, nor moueables, nor bookes, whereof the dead was owner, but that it may aduertiſe vs to be diſſolued, and in good time, whileſt it is day-light to diſpoſe of our Soules, euer thinking to goe the ſame way, and to follow that currant.</p>
                  <p>Theſe thoughts ought to change our ſorrowes and deſires, and turne
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19245:47"/>
our mindes from the memory of euils paſt, towards the bleſſings to come; and to change ſadneſſe into hope, and forepaſt euils into aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements to come. Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding I find it ſometimes very fit to be ſorrowfull, but with ſuch a kinde of reſpect, as it be alike for thoſe that are without, as for thoſe that are at home. When God ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth any that was an example of vertue, and that was of ſpeciall worth in the Church, we ought to ſay God is angry, hee maketh a breach in his houſe: this world was vnworthy of ſo great vertue; it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſageth our miſerie; as the death of <hi>Ioſias</hi> was preſently followed with the Captiuity of <hi>Babylon;</hi> or like the death of S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> after which preſently ſucceeded the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of the citie where he was Biſhop. For the life of this good man, ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the iudgement of God, and was
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19245:47"/>
a kinde of Rampart to the Church. Alſo <hi>Elizeus</hi> althogh he were old &amp; feeble, &amp; hauing nothing but a ſtaffe to vphold his weakneſſe, yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe it ſerued <hi>Iſrael</hi> for an entire Army; which is called by King <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, The Chariot of Iſrael diſarmed, and his men of War:</hi> As if he ſhould haue ſaide, that by his death <hi>Iſrael</hi> was diſarmed, and all the force it had quite taken away. For euen as we ſee Swallowes remoue their yong from an olde houſe that is like to fall; euen ſo the ſoules of the Saints flie from this earth here below, before the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine thereof. This kinde of dolour is healed with feare, and the euill that one feareth, is cured by amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life: and the death of the faithfull ſhall then greatly profit, if with the ſorrow we learne to forme our ſelues by the example of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed. I thinke good Brethren that ſuch thoughts as theſe, poſſeſſed the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19245:48"/>
kindred and friends of <hi>Simeon,</hi> by which they were not onely comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his death, but alſo inſtructed and edified.</p>
                  <p>But as for <hi>Simeon,</hi> how doe you thinke he prepared himſelfe to dye, and with what reſolution did he goe before? His prayer to God ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſheweth, when hee ſaide; <hi>Lord, now let thy ſeruant depart in peace,</hi> Note well what hee ſaith, <hi>Now,</hi> without asking any delay: He was prepared for it long before, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing nothing elſe to doe in the world, but to die. Like a Ship at Anchor, which is already rigged and trimmed, attending onely the wind, at laſt it came, and that winde was the Meſſias.</p>
                  <p>Hee is not the firſt ſeruant of God nor the laſt, that deſired to die; <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> before him, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19. ſaid to God, he was ſorry to ſee the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of <hi>Iſrael; It is enough O Eternall,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19245:48"/>
now take my ſoule, for I am no better then my Fathers:</hi> And after him, Saint <hi>Paul, Phil. 1. I deſire to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued and to be with Chriſt:</hi> And in another place; <hi>I deſire to dye, and to be with Chriſt.</hi> The end wherefore <hi>Simeon</hi> deſired to dye, was to enter into peace: He calleth death a peace or a repoſe, as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith, <hi>The iuſt is dead, hee ſhall enter in peace; they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe vpon their beds, whoſoeuer ſhall haue walked before him;</hi> and ſo the ſpirit of God ſaith, in the 14. of the <hi>Apoc. Bleſſed are they that dye in the Lord, for they Now,</hi> ſaith the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>reſt from their labours.</hi> Alſo death is called a peaceable ſleepe: as in the 2. of <hi>Iohn, Lazarus our friend ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth, but I goe to awake him:</hi> And Saint <hi>Stephen</hi> ſlept after he had ſaid, <hi>Lord Ieſus receiue my ſpirit. Daniel 12.</hi> ſaith, <hi>That many of thoſe that ſleepe in the earth, ſhall riſe to eternall life.</hi> It is the language of Heauen,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19245:49"/>
the ſtile of the heauenly Court, and the ſaying of the word of God, to call ſleepe that which we call death; from whence it commeth, that the Church-yard, where the dead are <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> buried, is called a Reſting place, or a ſleeping place. For, firſt of all, euen as we put off our cloathes before we goe to ſleepe; euen ſo our ſoules go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> to reſt, put off our bodies. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, if we ſleepe quietly, we muſt put off all care, and lay it vnder the Pillow; euen ſo to dye quietly and peaceably, wee muſt put off all care and earthly thoughts, and hauing diſpoſed of our Houſe, as God ſaid to <hi>Ezechias, for the beſt Will you can make, leaue your Soule to God, who ſhall not be more rich, but you ſhall be more happy.</hi> Himſelfe dying, left his Purſe to <hi>Iudas,</hi> his Body to the earth, but left his Soule to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for of that was his onely care.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Alſo euen as thoſe that are ſober,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19245:49"/>
and liue orderly, ſleepe with quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; but diſordered people, and Drunkards, reſt with terrour and griefe, euen ſo ſhall they dye peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably and religiouſly who haue ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; but thoſe that haue liued diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, and like Swine, are in danger to dye wofully and lamentably.</p>
                  <p>And euen as the King <hi>Aſſuerus,</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> when he could not ſleepe, called for his Chronicle, that after the reading thereof, he might take reſt; ſo ought the faithfull, during their liues, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe themſelues in the reading of the holy Scripture, which is the Hiſtory and the lawes of the hand of their Father; and to ſleepe thereupon in a peaceable and ſweet death.</p>
                  <p>And as in ſleepe, the body is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueable,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> but the ſoule moueth and exerciſeth: ſo whilſt the Body remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in death, the Soule liueth to God, and followeth the Lambe, fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the fulneſſe of the preſence of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:19245:50"/>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> And as one may obſerue of thoſe that ſleepe very ſoundly, yet if they be but called by their Names, they will riſe vp in aſtoniſhment: ſo Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt at the laſt day ſhall call all the faithfull, and they ſhall ſuddenly awake, and come out of the Graue: euen as he raiſed <hi>Lazarus</hi> when hee did riſe, after hee had called him by his name.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> We may alſo ſay, that after ſleepe we finde refreſhment, &amp; our ſtrength renewed; ſo after death our ſtrength ſhall be renewed, with another kinde of vigour, then euer we had before.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Briefly, as the profound ſleepe of <hi>Adam,</hi> brought him forth a Wife: ſo our death will bring vs neare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Ieſus Chriſt our true Eſpouſe, who marrieth vs in Righteouſneſſe and Mercy: for there is nothing but peace in Heauen, &amp; in earth nothing but confuſion. Neare vnto the earth are Windes and Raine, and heat af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19245:50"/>
colde; but high vp in the ayre, nothing moueth: So what peace muſt that be in Heauen, where the King of peace himſelfe raigneth, and where the bleſſed ſpirits ioyne their Songs and affections to praiſe &amp; ſerue God with a holy Harmony?</p>
                  <p>Of the peace of the Bleſſed, the faithfull feele here a kinde of taſte, which is the peace of Conſcience, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them repoſe euen vpon the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which ſuſtaineth Martyrs, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them eaſily digeſt pouertie and miſery, by the inward contentment they feele in the loue of God, to be reconciled vnto him through Ieſus Chriſt. For euen as a man that is in health, will ſleepe vpon a Bench, but he that is ſicke of the Stone, cannot reſt vpon a Bed; euen ſo the tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of conſcience maketh a man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, amidſt the incommodities of this life, but the wicked in proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie finde no reſt. Doe you thinke it
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19245:51"/>
ſtrange that <hi>Iacob</hi> ſlept quietly, albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it he had but a ſtone for his Pillow, ſeeing that God ſpoke to him ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and ſhewed him the gate of Heauen opened? I thinke <hi>Ionas</hi> had more reſt in the Whales belly, then <hi>Iezabel</hi> in her bed, or <hi>Nabuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> vpon his Throne; whereof the Apoſtle in the 4. of the <hi>Phil.</hi> calleth the peace of Conſcience, <hi>the peace of God,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>that it paſſeth all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</hi> Whereupon I gather, that if the firſt Paſtes and ſparkes of eternall peace ſurpaſſe all vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, how much more then the full repoſe, and full peace with eternall contentment? The faithfull ſeruants of God hauing but halfe dipped in the end of the finger into this Hony, as <hi>Ionathan</hi> did, had their eyes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened, and with this ſweetneſſe ouercome the bitterneſſe of death: and Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> before he dyed, taſted of this glory, being rauiſhed in ſpirit
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19245:51"/>
into the third heauens; when hee came to ſpeake of theſe things, hee ſaid, that theſe are things which is not lawfull to expreſſe: and putting his finger in his mouth, glorifyeth himſelfe in his infirmities and in his approbriouſneſſe for the name of Chriſt. And <hi>Dauid</hi> in the 80. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> asketh in this life al the contentment that a man can haue in this world, in asking, <hi>That God would ſhine vpon him with the cleareneſſe of his face:</hi> and yet this clearenes commeth from a-farre: It is but like a little Raye of the Sunne ſhining through a little hole, into a darke plaee; what will this be then when the day ſhall ſhine all out ſo cleare, and that God will ſhine clearely vpon vs ſo neare, that he will ſhew his face vnto vs, which no man did euer ſee and liue, as God ſaith to <hi>Moſes?</hi> Many giue money for olde Coines, and the formes of the buildings of auncient times, but
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19245:52"/>
how much would a man giue to ſee the perſons of thoſe times? and how much more would a man giue to ſee <hi>Abraham, Iſaack, Iacob, Dauid,</hi> the Prophets, and the Apoſtles? To ſee the leaſt of them, you would trauaile a thouſand leagues; and how much more then would you giue to ſee all, to ſee them all, and all free from ſinne and infirmitie, ſuch as they are in the Kingdome of God? And how much more then aboue all the reſt, to ſee this <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> which is declared in the word, and figured by the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments; who hath ſuffered all euill for vs; who deſcended vpon earth for to raiſe vs vp to heauen; who took vpon him our fleſh, to cloathe vs with his holy ſpirit: who made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the ſonne of Man, to make vs the Children of God, who ſuffered death to giue vs life; who daily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth our prayers, preſenteth them to God, ſendeth his Angels from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19245:52"/>
and maketh his bleſſings dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fall downe vpon vs? your eyes ſee it: which is declared vnto you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the troubles and throngs of this world, you ſee it in the peace which <hi>Simeon</hi> did waite for.</p>
                  <p>Truely we doe but lightly eſteeme theſe things: a humane ſpirit mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth but with one wing; we haue a greater deſire vnto it, then capacity to vnderſtand it. For wee ought to be more occupied in keeping on the high way to come to this peace, then in the contemplation of the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie thereof: We ſhall know it one day; now let vs ſtriue, onely, to tend that way.</p>
                  <p>This thought putteth another in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my minde, and maketh me admire many perſons, who know and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue theſe things, and yet are not once moued therewith; who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the truth, being in their decrepit age, and in the bed of death, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19245:53"/>
feare to confeſſe God for the diſpleaſure of men: they would willingly ſay with <hi>Simeon, Lord now let thy ſeruant depart in peace:</hi> but the feare of men hindreth them from making their peace with God: what hope they for, or what feare they in this world? who for an houre of life, that they yet haue in this world; would loſe eternall life? who to pleaſe men in dying, would diſpleaſe God after death? There is certainely beſides hardneſſe and rebellion, a blindneſſe and an eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent folly.</p>
                  <p>Some will ſay, this peace is to be wiſhed for, &amp; I aſpire to it euen with all my heart, but the way to come thereto is very hard to finde out, the paſſage to death is dolorous &amp; feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and Sathan lyeth in Ambuſh euen in the way; and all the feare, and feebleneſſe, and ſorrow that is there, is purpoſely placed to intrap
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19245:53"/>
a man in ſuch extremitie: it is a good thing to be dead, but a grieuous thing to dye.</p>
                  <p>I confeſſe that death is very terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in nature. Men care to dye, when they can deferre it no longer: Many cut off Legges and Armes to ſaue the reſt, and are very glad ſo to liue with the one halfe of their body; there are many troubled with the ſtone that reſolue to be cut; and although the combat be great, yet they hope to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape; but if they were aſſured to die, they would reſolue to be twenty yeares tormented: Neuertheleſſe he ſaith, that death is not ſo terrible as they make it, principally to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, which are prepared for it: It is not death that is ſo grieuous, but the things thereto belonging.</p>
                  <p>He that feareth God, hath where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall to ſuſtaine him in theſe trials: for it is then that God aſſiſteth all thoſe that call vpon him, <hi>call vpon
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19245:54"/>
mee in thy neceſsitie, and I will heare thee:</hi> and what greater Neceſſitie can there be then death? Hee that giueth his Angels charge to defend thoſe that liue in his feare, how can he abandon thoſe that dye, calling vpon him? Hee that openeth his eye ouer the proſperity of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, can hee haue his eare ſhut to the ſighes of the good that call vpon him in their extremitie? and although Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than eſpie him, the Angels watch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him, to whom our defence is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; and beſides, Sathan is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chayned with a chayne, both great and ſtrong, which is called the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God,</hi> hauing his Head wounded to death; and the ſouldiers that he ſetteth to aſſaile vs, which are ſorrow and the figure of death, their Armes and weapons are no better then ſtrawes and pinnes, againſt the faith of the faithfull.</p>
                  <p>Some ſay the Diuell appeared to a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19245:54"/>
dying man, and ſhewed him a Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that was very long, wherein was written on euery ſide the ſinnes of the poore ſicke man, which were many in number: and that there were alſo written the Idle words he had ſpoken, which made vp three quarters of the words that hee had ſpoken in his life; together with the falſe words, the vnchaſte words, and the words of iniurie; afterwards came in rancke, his vaine and vngodly words; and laſtly, his actions; dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted according to the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: whereupon Sathan ſaid, <hi>Seeſt thou? Behold thy vertues, ſee here what thine examination ſhall be:</hi> Whereunto the poore ſinner anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>It is true Sathan; but thou haſt not ſet downe all; for thou ſhouldeſt haue added and ſet downe here below, The bloud of Ieſus Chriſt cleanſeth vs from all our ſinnes; and this alſo ſhould not haue bin forgotten, That whoſoeuer
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19245:55"/>
beleeueth in him, ſhall not periſh, but haue euerlaſting life:</hi> there are none ſo feeble as the Diuell, nor ſo coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when he is to aſſaile a true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: onely name <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and hee flyeth a way: for he wayteth but for the day when hee ſhall be bound in chaynes, and caſt into the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe pit, which made him ſay to <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, art thou come to torment me before my time?</hi> And he praied <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> that he would not ſend him into the <hi>Abiſme.</hi> If we haue the eyes of Faith open, we ſhal not need to feare death, but outface her, &amp; make our ſelues familiar with her; for ſhee annoyeth none but thoſe that ſhee ſurprizeth; and we likewiſe loue her like one that openeth the Priſon doore to thoſe that are in durance: Euen as if the Children which come out of the Mothers wombe, ſhould haue ſome reaſon, they would not weepe, but reioyce to come out of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19245:55"/>
ſuch a noyſome and obſcure place to ſee the Sunne: Euen ſo if our ſoules were inſtructed as they ought to be, and had true reaſon, they would not be ſorry to goe out of the priſon of the Body, to come into the light of God: for this iſſue is another Byrth, whereof we ought not to be amazed, if it be done with ſome ſorrow: it is a meanes to enter into the light. For in the auncient Church, the day of the celebration of the death of the Martyrs, was called the day of Natiuity. Let him feare death, who hopeth not for life: let him feare death, who would not goe to <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> let him feare death, that is a ſlaue to his Belly, and to gormun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing: but as for me, Chriſt is gaine to me to liue and die. Euen then when <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> was reſolued to dye, <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> diſſwaded him, but Chriſt reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Get thee behinde mee Sathan;</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo wee checke the fleſh, which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19245:56"/>
filleth vs with feares; for it knoweth nothing of the things of God.</p>
                  <p>Now you ſee death, which was common to vs, is now become fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, ſhe is nothing fearefull but in ſhew, for life is hidden vnder the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of death: as if one ſhould ſend vs a faire preſent, by a deformed Blackamore; ſo God by the hand of hideous death, preſenteth vnto vs the heauenly life. It is that pale &amp; terrible Horſe, which is ſpoken of in the 6. of the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> which is called Death, wherupon we muſt get vp to goe to God: It is the paſſage of the Red ſea, which is very fearefull to walke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ſwelling waues that hang ouer the head: but by that, God opened the paſſage to the promiſed land. It is the Lyon of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> out of the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion whereof, they got Honie, as <hi>Sampſons</hi> companions ſaid, <hi>That out of that which was bitter, came forth ſweetneſſe:</hi> Indeede there is nothing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19245:56"/>
more bitter then death, when it is accompanied with the malediction of God: when it carrieth with it a terrour of conſcience, an oppreſſion of heart, a trembling of the ſoule, when it feeleth it ſelfe ſummoned to appeare before the iudgement ſeat of God; but theſe things being taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, death is ſweet and bleſſed: for <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> hath borne our maledi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and hath ſuffered all the deeds of the Iudgement of God, nothing now remaining, but onely ſo much euill as is needfull to open the gate, for the ſoule to depart and be at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty: and this little ſorrow that muſt be endured, is not long laſting, wonderfull little in regard of our ſinnes: light in compariſon of the torments of hell which we haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued: light, in compariſon of the ſufferings of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> light in compariſon of the infinite glory, and eternall waight of heauenly glory
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19245:57"/>
which ſtayeth for vs: fleſh is feeble but the ſpirit of God fortifyeth: it mightily ſuffereth vnder ſorrow, but an Angell dryeth vp the droppes of bloud, and <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> ſheweth the Crowne.</p>
                  <p>You may ſay vnto mee, This is true: but wherefore is it that God will haue the death of the faithfull ſo full of dolour? It is becauſe hee will haue vs feele ſinne ſtill to dwell in vs, ſeeing wee perceiue the effects doe ſhew it: alſo hee will by theſe ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, make vs feele what the grace is that he hath done vs, in deliuering vs from eternall death; ſeeing that our death is an eaſie, ſhort, and ſweet death, in compariſon of euerlaſting torments; he would haue vs in dying, pray ardently: which ſorrow ſerueth to inlighten our prayers, quickned with the violency thereof, and enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by Neceſſity: he knoweth, that one cannot come out of an euill, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19245:57"/>
euill; he will not haue vs enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this peace without combat and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance.</p>
                  <p>All this good commeth by Ieſus Chriſt, who by his death hath taken the malediction from ours: who hath changed our ſepulchres into Couches, our death into a peaceable ſleepe, and of the entry into Hell, hath made it the entry into Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe. Shall we feare to enter into this priſon after him. Or to enter into death, where he leadeth the way, and holdeth vs by the hand? <hi>I am,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the reſurrection and the life, whoſoeuer beleeueth in mee, although he be dead, ſhall liue.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is the cauſe alſo why <hi>Sime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> after he deſired to dye, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led death a peace, and a repoſe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to the cauſe of this aſſurance that is to ſay, to Ieſus Chriſt, whom he calleth the ſaluation of God, let (ſaith he) goe thy ſeruant in peace,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19245:58"/>
                     <hi>for mine eyes haue ſeene thy ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> that is to ſay, the ſauing health which thou offereſt vnto vs, and the onely meanes which thou haſt ordained to ſaue vs.</p>
                  <p>For it is he which is our Ieſus, becauſe hee ſaueth the people from their ſinnes: It is he that God hath ordained for a propitiation by the blood of the Groſſe, and there is no other name vnder Heauen, by which we can poſſibly be ſaued: He is the Prince of life, becauſe we draw from him, as from the fountaine of life, euen as the foure firſt dayes of the Creation, all was wholly light of it ſelfe, but the fourth day God created the Sunne, whereto he confined and placed all that that he had of light in the world, that it might after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards flow from the Sunne: euen ſo all life is incloſed in Ieſus Chriſt, to the end that going to him, wee may draw out of his fulneſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:19245:58"/>And euen as the Virgine veſtals of the Pagans (from whence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth the Nunnes of theſe times) had a continuall fire, which if it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened by any miſchance to goe out, they might not giue it light againe but only from the Sun: ſo our Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall cleareneſſe, and our life being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed by the ſinne of <hi>Adam,</hi> we cannot kindle againe, but at the Sunne of Iuſtice, which is our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, to whom belongeth that which is ſaid in the 36. <hi>Pſalme, The Fountaine of life lyeth in thee, and by thy cleareneſſe we ſee clearely.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is ſaluation which is propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in this Table, which is Ieſus Chriſt, now offered vnto you. <hi>Sime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> embraced him in his armes; but you imbrace him by faith: <hi>Simeon</hi> ſaluted his birth in his infirmity; but you adore and contemplate him in his glory: <hi>Simeon</hi> came to dye beſides his Cradle, but you are
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19245:59"/>
made aliue by his kingdome: Come neere vnto him with repentance, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this meate with faith, digeſt it with carefull meditation of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of ſaluation, make this ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation fruitfull, and of ſweet odour, by your good works, that dogs and ſwine come not neere to eate vp chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens bread, &amp; prophane this holy Table. I call them ſwine that wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in the mire of their filthy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, who ſerue their belly more then God, who liue of Gods gifts, and looke not from whence they come: like ſwine that eat Acornes, and neuer looke vp to the Trees.</p>
                  <p>I call them ſwine likewiſe, who do no good to any, till they be dead, who giue nothing whileſt they are aliue, and liue baſely to dye Rich. I call thoſe dogges which are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurious in words, who murmure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all men, who byte the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne of their neighbour, who
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19245:59"/>
barke againſt God blaſphemouſly, and would wrong them that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue and inſtruct them; who after a little leauing of their vices, returne to their vomitting againe. With this company, I ranke thoſe that are negligent in participating of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Supper, as an impertinent thing, and loue not to declare the death of the Lord, contemning the happy helpes which God hath ordained to ſtrengthen faith.</p>
                  <p>Such people make their owne In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditements; and in abſtaining from the Lords Table, acknowledge themſelues vnworthy to be of his Houſhold: they will not receiue the body of the Lord, and the Lord will not receiue their ſoules: they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne his Table, and they ſhall not enter into his Kingdome. As much or more are they to be blamed, that know themſelues ſtained with theſe things, and yet not touched with
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19245:60"/>
repentance, come without a holy purpoſe to doe better hereafter, to take the Sacrament, which is life and ſaluation to the faithfull, but poyſon and death to the vnbeleeuer and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent. Doe you come to receiue the Sacrament of the Lord with prophane hearts? Come you to take with hands full of Vſury and rapine the Body of the Lord? Come you with riots and quarrels to receiue the aſſurance of your peace with God? or with pride to declare the death of the Lord, which is the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of Humiliation? or to pleaſe men with curious apparell, where onely your innocency ought to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before God?</p>
                  <p>But for you that are broken-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and diſpleaſed in your ſelues, this Table is prepared: Doe not ſay, I am too great a ſinner to come neere it: for that is the cauſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou oughteſt to come neere:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19245:60"/>
for the more one is ſicke, ſo much more need is there of the Phyſition. Ieſus Chriſt is not come to <hi>ſaue the Iuſt, but to call ſinners to repentance:</hi> onely be diſpleaſed with your ſelues to haue offended God, and deſire to amend and to doe better, and aske helpe at Gods hands to aſſiſt you to this Combat. He is ſufficiently acceptable to God, who is diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with himſelfe. He is of the moſt perfect, who acknowledging him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe Imperfect, ſeeketh his perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Ieſus Chriſt; whoſe righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is imputed vnto vs. The faithfull will haue fallings and weakneſſes, but he will alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe; Hee will reioyce in trembling, <hi>Pſalme 2.</hi> He will gather on in his way in ſtumbling; He will ſay, I beleeue, but helpe my vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe.</p>
                  <p>This Sacament is a meanes to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine this feebleneſſe, a reſtoratiue
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19245:61"/>
for ſpirituall failings, a ſuccour to a combatted faith, to the end that you repreſenting this ſaluation and this grace, you ſay I am loſt and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and haue merited death, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold God calleth me, and offereth me his grace, and Redemption; hee is no mocker, and his vocation can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be fruſtrated, yet neuertheleſſe I goe bathed with the teares of a holy ſorrow, powring at his feet this precious liquour of repentance; and I doe aſſure my ſelfe, hee will haue mercy vpon mee, becauſe he hath ſo promiſed: I truſt in his promiſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt my afflictions, and for all my ſinnes, I feare not but to find a full Conſolation.</p>
                  <p>And ſo I goe on my way, ſaying with <hi>Simeon, Lord, now let thy ſeruant depart in peace, for mine eyes haue ſeen thy ſaluation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19245:61"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A</hi> HEAVENLY ALARVM.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>OR THE HOLY</hi> SPI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Awakening.</p>
                  <p>By Mounſieur du MOOLIN, <hi>Minister of</hi> PARIS <hi>at</hi> CHARRENTON.</p>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Iohn Hauiland</hi> for THOMAS PAVIER. 1622.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19245:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19245:62"/>
                  <head>THE HOLY SPIRITVALL <hi>Awakening.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is too much ſtill to goe on, and grow old in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie: let not the fooliſh affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall deſires tranſport vs any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: we loue the things here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low but too well; let vs eſtrange our ſelues from them, and addreſſe our ſelues to heauen, without fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrating it of that that belongeth vnto it: the example of Creatures without reaſon (euen without
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19245:63"/>
ſenſe) leadeth vs vnto this reaſon: we ſee the water, come out of the water, returning againe to the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; the earth drawne from the earth, ſeeketh for the earth; and ſo conſequently euery thing tendeth to his place: but wee which are borne for heauen, flie from it. The eternall Beatitude and the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof is our beatitude, which we poſſeſſe alreadie by the aſſurance of our vnion with Ieſus Chriſt, in whoſe death wee haue beene baptiſed to participate at the Reſurrection, and to be at Gods appointed time coheirs of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly inheritance; ſhould not this make vs lift vp our ſelues on high, and entirely vnlooſe our affections from the earth? But alas! we muſt confeſſe, that this knowledge is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt wholly vnknowne to vs; for our conuerſation is little otherwiſe than theirs that neuer knew God,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19245:63"/>
walking without all feare of the Lord, and often doing thoſe things which ought not euen to be ſo much as thought of or named a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs: for wee liue after the common example, euen of the moſt vngodly, wickedly profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that man is not borne but for his fleſh, and to glut himſelfe with his irregular deſires and paſſions: O maruellous brutalitie!</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.1. Where ſhall this knowledge bee? Where is the vnderſtanding and waiting for heauenly ioy? for this Vnion doth no kinde of way exerciſe the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: ſhould wee not walke in feare and trembling all the daies of our life, to mortifie the old Man and our corrupt Nature? Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe where will the fruit of our Baptiſme appeare? And where the efficacie of the paſſions and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of Ieſus Chriſt? And if wee
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19245:64"/>
be depriued of theſe things, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine wee not in death, euen in eternall death?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. Wherefore let vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to be aſtoniſhed, let vs now be afraid, ſeeing the anger of God doth threaten vs if wee ſtill deſiſt: his patience inuiteth vs to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; doe not vnderualue the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of his mercie; euen to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent day he hath ſupported vs, ſhall wee not ſay the mercy of God is great, he will haue pity of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of our ſinnes, although we haue added ſinne to ſinne: let vs not ſtill deferre our conuerſion till to morrow, for Mercy and Anger both come from the Lord, and his day will come when we thinke not of it, no man knoweth the houre: let vs remember that, that is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the euill ſeruant in the Parable,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.48.</note> who ſaying in his heart, My Maſter will be long in comming,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19245:64"/>
and therefore I will leade a wicked life; but when the vnlooked for day doth come, that hee ſhall be ſurpriſed by his Maſter, he ſhall be caſt away where is weeping and gnaſhing of teeth. Let vs feare, let vs feare to be ſo ſurprized; let vs watch to doe good, and ſleepe no longer in our ſinnes.</p>
                  <p>O little better than Atheiſts, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous monſters, who ſay, let vs ſinne that God may pardon vs, for what elſe ſerueth his mercy? Is he not come to ſaue ſinners? Alas how you deceiue your ſelues? And alſo thoſe who glut their beaſtly appetites, and feede their odious and deteſtable deſires, who (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faning likewiſe the mercy of God) promiſe reſt to themſelues after they haue ſpent all their life in ſuch wicked wayes, with ſaying a <hi>Pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caui</hi> at their death, wherein they heape vp as much euill in hoping
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19245:65"/>
for happineſſe after ſuch a ſort, as the moſt wicked can poſſibly doe; wherein they make it to be in mans power to haue repentance, and to aske and obtaine pardon at euery moment when he pleaſeth, and no ſpeciall gift and ſingular Grace of God. As <hi>Ieremie</hi> manifeſteth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ierem.</hi> 31.18.</note> when hee ſaith, <hi>Conuert me and I ſhall be conuerted, for thou art my Lord my God: truly after I haue beene conuerted, I repented.</hi> To the end that it ſhall appeare how grace commeth from God alone, euen out of his owne free will, the holy Ghoſt ſaith, <hi>Act.</hi> 11.18. <hi>God hath giuen repentance to the Gentiles, that they might liue:</hi> which is alſo cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewed by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> charging <hi>Timothie,</hi> 2.25. to teach thoſe of contrarie vnderſtanding, <hi>To ſee if in any time God will giue them repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for to know the truth, and that they may awake and come out of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19245:65"/>
ſnare of the Deuill, Iſaiah</hi> 1.15. as in this wee now vnderſtand, That man ſometimes crieth to the Lord for nothing, and afterwards get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth no anſwer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.41. Conſider then to whom, when, and how is mercy done? And in this behalfe let vs all acknowledge that we haue not to morrow to repent in: let vs no longer grow old in our iniquitie, for feare, as the Wiſe-man ſaith, <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 12.10. <hi>That wickedneſſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing taken root in vs, our heart will neuer change:</hi> Euen as the tree that hath beene planted of old, cannot eaſily be vnrooted: hauing alwaies remembrance of this threatning, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3.3. <hi>If thou doſt not watch I will come againſt thee, like a theefe, and thou ſhalt not know what houre.</hi> But why ſhould we not be wiſe by ſo many examples, which daily we ſee, that the ſtrongeſt man, euen
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19245:66"/>
he that in all his affaires builds far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt from the Tombe, and that thinketh nothing leſſe than of the tribute which hee oweth vnto death; and then at the ſame inſtant hee miſcaries? And therefore no man knoweth the houre, nor how hee ſhall bee taken from this vile earth. Euery moment, night and day, ſhew vs there are a thouſand and a thouſand waies in the hand of God, to cut, when he pleaſeth, the Threed of life, euen of the moſt Robuſt: Which was well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by a graue Author, ſaying: In what Act, or Place, or Time ſoeuer a man is, he is couered with death. Pauſe a little, O thou Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poriſer, that ſtill deferreſt thy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment to another time, let not this preſent time paſſe without thinking of it, and this ſhall be thy entrance in making profit of the aduertiſement which Ieſus Chriſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19245:66"/>
giueth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.42. <hi>That we ought to keepe our ſelues alwaies ready to watch for feare to be ſurpriſed, not knowing the houre of our departing.</hi> Let vs not make our ſelues deafe: if we lend our hearing ſometimes to an Inſtrument which recreateth vs, ſhall wee ſtop it when wee ſhould vnderſtand wholeſome counſell? No, no, this is ſpoken for our good, <hi>Prou.</hi> 1. <hi>I haue called, and you haue refuſed: I haue ſtretched out my hand, and you haue not vnderſtood, you haue contemned all my counſell, and would not be corrected: therefore I wil laugh at your perdition, and will mock at your feare when it ſhall come vpon you: when torment and anguiſh ſhal come vpon you you will call vpon me, but I will not anſwer, becauſe you haue hated knowledge, and haue not choſen the feare of God: you would not hearken to my counſell, but deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed my correction: wherefore you eat
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19245:67"/>
the fruit of your owne waies, and ſhal be glutted therewith: for the fooles ſhall be ſlaine with eaſe; and fooles ſhall be ruined by their proſperity.</hi> O peruerſe people, remember how I dealt with <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah, Eſdras</hi> 2.8. euen ſo I will doe with them that will not heare me, ſaith the Eternall. Let vs be better ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.7, 8. <hi>Prou.</hi> 19.20. <hi>Let vs heare the voice of God, let vs not harden our hearts: but heare counſell and receiue inſtruction, that we may be more wiſe.</hi> And making profit by theſe admonitions, let vs not put off from one day to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <q>(euen euery one) to ſay, I haue ſinned; and let vs repent at this preſent, and no longer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane this ſpeciall gift of God, this gift of Repentance ſo preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous (<hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.17. which <hi>Eſau</hi> asketh with teares, but was not granted him) leſt that the miſery
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19245:67"/>
of the fiue fooliſh Virgins fall vpon vs, who being not furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with oile, which their lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure would haue furniſhed them withall, entred not in with the bridegroome:</q> but let vs keepe watch in walking in newneſſe of life, as already departed from the world, not knowing the houre when we ſhall be called; witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that we are dead to ſinne, and aliue to God through Ieſus Chriſt, in whom we are made new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to ſerue to righteouſneſſe; and now let vs truly ſhew to haue more care of heauenly than of earthly things; the couetous man in renouncing his couetouſneſſe; the ambitious worldling in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing his inſolent ambition; and the voluptuous in hating his vile fleſhly affections; for from thence ſpringeth all our impietie, it is the root and fountaine
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19245:68"/>
which begetteth and bringeth forth all wickedneſſe, which wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked people ſo much eſteeme.</p>
                  <p>Without particularizing the enormitie of theſe vices, where the moſt guiltie will cleare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, in ſaying he is no ſuch man; although indeed he will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare the honour of God, euen to trample it vnder foote as much as he hath power, to fulfill his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate deſires: willingly detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting from the way of ſaluation, and hold againſt his conſcience the wide way of the world, with thoſe that know not God, adoring the Creature for the Creator, not fearing to doe any thing that may pleaſe the appetite. Theſe ſinnes draw after them all iniquitie, and to make warre againſt God, is no better than to renounce him: can man with all the wickedneſſe of the world bee more abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble?
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19245:68"/>
No no, it is impoſſible, it is in the height of iniquitie!</p>
                  <p>But to the end that wee may not condemne the parties without hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them anſwer for themſelues; let vs underſtand what they can ſay: God deſireth the interiour and not the exteriour, that which is within, not that without; and if they ſtriue to be in better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and ſocietie, yet they doe but apply themſelues (in ſhew onely) that is, but to ſeeke outwardly for vnion, and by endeuour to preſerue that which is not, ſtill inwardly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining one &amp; the ſame they were before, which is contrary to the way and walke of a good ſoule.</p>
                  <p>O true ſentence moſt worthy noting, <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.19. <hi>That the way of a foole is right in his owne eies.</hi> Poore blinde fooles, thinke you by your humane wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (folly before the eternall)
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19245:69"/>
to put your ſelues ſafelier vpon the pitch-banke of Gods wrath, than thoſe whom you doe condemne; heare what <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith of thoſe deſiring to be wiſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21.22. <hi>You are become fooles, in this, that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as you haue knowne God, yet haue you not glorified him as God;</hi> let vs learne that he which know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the will of his maſter and doth it not, ſhall be beaten more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly than hee that knoweth it not.</p>
                  <p>Your Hypocriſie is here moſt apparant, in deſiring to be thought of, in better part than that which is within your heart: a deteſtable ſinne, which Ieſus Chriſt neuer ſpeaketh of, but in wonderfull an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: it is the high way of Atheiſme, for he which enforceth himſelfe to faine a religion that hee condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in his ſoule, can haue no quiet in ſoule nor conſcience, vntill hee
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19245:69"/>
come to beleeue that all things are indifferent, and there is no other meanes to vntie himſelfe from the terror of Gods iudgements, and to free his miſerable conſcience, but to perſwade himſelfe that God will not ſo ſtrictly looke to the cariages of men, and then that maketh him a ſpirituall theefe: or hauing loſt the ſenſe and feeling of diuine iuſtice, it is a true teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, he knoweth God no more; for to deny God and to deny his iuſtice is all one. Doe we not ſee that theſe for the moſt part, who fainingly adhere but to idolaters, in the end wholly become idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or fall into the blindneſſe of being of no religion, hauing whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forgot God, and liue as if there were none? who becauſe men ſhould thinke better of them, are like the Camelion, according as they meet withall, ſometimes this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19245:70"/>
and ſometimes that: ſuch the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Elias</hi> crieth againſt in the 3. of <hi>Kings</hi> the 18. <hi>Wherefore do you halt of both ſides? if God be God, wherfore doe you not follow him? if Baal, Baal.</hi> But if yet they haue any ſparke of knowledge that there is a God, a terrible God, that is to be feared in his iudgements when hee is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie; ſhould they not be loth to heare the Eternall ſay in his anger, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3.16. <hi>They being neither hot nor cold, but luke-warme, hee will ſpue them out of his mouth.</hi> And <hi>Ier.</hi> 48.10. ſaith, <hi>Hee is accurſed that doth the worke of the Lord looſely;</hi> what can be more terrible, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the execution?</p>
                  <p>And you that ſay ye are the beſt; you that agree with the Spirit in what you doe: Lamentable wiſe fooles, whoſe wiſdome is folly, do not you know that he that is Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the ſoule, is alſo of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die?
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19245:70"/>
Can wee with the one ſerue God, and <hi>Mammon</hi> with the other? Wherefore did not <hi>Daniel</hi> faigne as you vſe, when he was to be caſt into the Lions den, or <hi>Sidrack, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſack</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> when they were to be caſt into the furnace? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue not all other Martyrs ſpoken your language, and made a faire ſhew to haue eſcaped ſuch horrible torments, euen of death it ſelfe? But what was the cauſe that made many of them euen with a yea or a no, without any profeſſion of religion (being deſired by thoſe which thought to doe friendly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices for their eſcape) rather chuſe death, and ſo abandon their liues, than they would heare one word in hope thereof?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10. No, no, we muſt, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, not only beleeue with the heart to be iuſtified, but confeſſe with the mouth to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19245:71"/>
haue ſaluation; for God deſireth the outward with the inward, and would haue our light ſo ſhine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, to the end that ſeeing our good workes he may be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied: this is the doctrine of Ieſus Chriſt: let vs ſtriue to doe this, for otherwiſe we ſhall finde as in the <hi>Apocal.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Repent, or elſe I will come vnto thee quickly, and will fight againſt them with the ſword of my mouth:</hi> But let vs take vp with our ſelues, and at laſt ſing with <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 35. <hi>Our tongues ſhall ſing high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the iuſtice of the eternall, and the humble ſhall heare that our ſoules ſhall glorifie the Lord, whereat they will reioyce:</hi> and as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth vs, <hi>Let vs glorifie our God not only in our ſpirit, but alſo in our bodies which are Gods;</hi> and let vs giue one another a good ſigne of our adoption, that we haue in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; which all men may wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19245:71"/>
that by him we are inheritors of the kingdome of heauen; let vs reioyce in this glory, which no glory can compare with, and ſo pretious a bleſſing that no man can value with any price.</p>
                  <p>Let our pietie ſhine cleerely for the inſtruction of our families, and not ſhew our ſelues careleſſe, but carefull to make them know the riches of ſaluation, with the means how it muſt be attained: otherwiſe we are no better than the executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of their ſoules, worſe than bruit beaſts, who but for a while care for their young ones; or like thoſe that ſacrificed their children to <hi>Baal;</hi> I ſay if we conſent that they be nouriſhed with the milke and venome of ſpirituall whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, we doe as much as we can to make them one day participate of the malediction of the eternall, euen as if we had vowed to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19245:72"/>
to deliuer them vp into the hands of Satan: which we do teſtifie, if againſt our knowledge and conſcience we nouriſh them not vp in the waies of the Lord. Let vs apply our whole ſtudie to that, after a ſort doing as God hath committed to our charge, for their holy conuerſation, to publiſh to euery one the truth of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, as a thing that we make moſt eſteeme of.</p>
                  <p>I pray you where is he that is borne of a noble familie, who is not iealous to be acknowledged for one of that race? What Lord will not ſet out his Titles? and will not weare his Armes? euen in the beſt places for to be moſt beheld? although it be but of ſmall conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, and little better than pure vanitie! yet can it hold no compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon with this Title, ſo high aboue all, ſo full of glory, the top of all
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19245:72"/>
Honour, this Title, I ſay, of the childe and ſeruant of God, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heire with Chriſt; dignities (O the moſt Noble and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent!) which make Monarks hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, not for a while but eternally, in regard whereof all other things, be they neuer ſo pretious, which are vnder Heauen, are much leſſe than nothing, euen moſt vnhappy, if this other be not adioyned vnto it: and moreouer if the noble man of the family, in his Armes will not ſuffer to take away or adde any thing, leſt the world ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract from his dignitie; how much more ſhould we be carefull to commit any thing that is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, who are truly the children and ſeruants of God? and in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the world enforce our ſelues to walke in integritie, and ſtriue to be ſo eſteemed? which if we doe not, how can we be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19245:73"/>
to be in the grace and fauour of Heauen? let vs not then be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of the truth of Chriſts Goſpell, which is the vertue of God to ſaluation vnto all belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers; for alas! if it be ſo that we are become ſo bruit and beſtiall, that to poſſeſſe the world, or for feare of it, we will diſſemble the knowledge that is in vs; the Sonne of God himſelfe ſaith vnto vs, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.26. euen as we haue deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him before men, he will alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie vs before his Father, and there will be aſhamed of vs, and very iuſtly: Let vs then hold the confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our hope without varying for any thing, according as <hi>S. Paul</hi> teacheth vs, <hi>That that which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and to come,</hi> height, depth, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, nakedneſſe, perſecution, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, nor death, nor life, ſhall not ſeparate vs from the loue of Chriſt: alwaies prepared in euery
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19245:73"/>
place, and before all to render a reaſon to euery one of the hope that is in vs; and as truly faithfull let vs take our neighbours by the hand and ſay, let vs goe vp to the Mountaine of Sion, into the houſe of the God of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and there will he teach vs his waies: and let vs one ſtirre vp another to Charitie and good Workes, without ſwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing from the companie of the faithfull: for <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>If we willingly ſin after we haue receiued the knowledge of the truth, there is no more ſacrifice for ſinne, but a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible looking for iudgement, and a furie of fire, which ſhall deuoure the aduerſaries:</hi> Repreſenting vnto vs, that if any haue miſpriſed the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> he was without all mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie put to death: from thence then conclude, how much greater tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doe they deſerue who haue the bloud of IESVS CHRIST
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19245:74"/>
in no reuerence or holineſſe, by which they haue beene ſanctified, doing this iniurie euen to the ſpirit of grace? afterwards that this commeth to be knowne, the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom is to depriue ſuch odious peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of great mens fauours, which maketh all faire deſignes proue abortiue; this is no true nor faire proceeding, but rather an incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement ſtill to continue in their wicked waies. Here muſt the place be of the wraſtling, behold the Combat, but before we enter the liſts let vs know our enemies, they are the World and the Fleſh: ſhall we aske of our enemies conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent things to deſtroy them? No, that would be worſe than to caſt flaxe into the fire to quench it.</p>
                  <p>For to defend our ſelues from the firſt aſſault, let vs ranke our ſelues like <hi>Daniel, Sidrack, Miſack,</hi> and <hi>Abednego;</hi> let vs march their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19245:74"/>
pace, and we ſhall ſerue our ſelues with the like Armes of Martyrs which they did: hauing our reines girt with the girdle of Truth, cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with the breſt-plate of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and our feete with the preparation of the Goſpell of peace, in euery thing taking the buckler of Faith, the helmet of Saluation, and the ſword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God; renouncing our ſelues to follow IESVS CHRIST, as euery true Chriſtian ought: ſo ſhall we paſſe a greater conflict than this we haue at this preſent, if we meete it, and ſhall remaine conquerers as they haue done, which haue not only knowne, but alſo followed the will of the Eternall, and not the ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alitie of the Fleſh, of the World <hi>(a gift of God which he giueth to all that aske it of him with confidence)</hi> knowing that the Almightie cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19245:75"/>
the man that putteth his truſt in Man, and in the fleſh of the arme, for the greateſt is but vanitie and lies, and whoſoeuer ſhould weigh al the great ones of the earth againſt nothing, yet ſhould they all be found more light than nothing. But they haue not waited for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation from any other ſoueraigne, but repoſed wholly in him; Doe we not ſee that there neuer was any Monarch in the world that diſpleaſed God, but preſently was reduced to nothing? doe we want any proofes that God euer failed in his promiſes? neither hath it beene euer knowne but the wrath of God followed him that truſted in his owne arme and power; were it neuer ſo powerfull? let vs at laſt renounce it, for he that hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but earthly force, hath none at all. Let vs therefore follow the counſell of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and put our truſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19245:75"/>
alwaies in God, for he is good, and will giue vs all that is conuenient; mightie in power and truth, and vnmoueable in all his promiſes for to bring euery thing to paſſe; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs all ſay with him, God is my force, and my hope, neither is there any other helpe but from him, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 28. Thou that fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt thy Honours, and feareſt that the goods of the earth will leaue thee, which when they haue done ſo, thou art ſo hartleſſe and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope, that thou confirmeſt all this to be true; that it is impoſſible to ſerue God and Riches, which is pronounced by the very Truth it ſelfe. But it behooueth thee to ſet the looking glaſſe before thy face, to ſee how much thou art diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured, and if thine eyes be not offuſcated, behold thy deformitie. O foole, that ſo much eſteemeſt the glory and treaſure of the earth,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19245:76"/>
as if in that conſiſted thy felicitie. Horrible idolate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> if thy ſoule had beene asked for this night, what would haue become of all? and ſuppoſe thy life ſhall continue euen to the vtmoſt of old age, it proueth but a moment: what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit haue they carried away that thou haſt knowne, of all thoſe that are now in their graues? doeſt thou thinke if they died rich, that they were more happy? alas there is much danger to thinke the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: <hi>Luke</hi> 18.24. <hi>It is a hard thing for a rich man to enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen:</hi> What hope canſt thou draw from <hi>S. Iames</hi> 5.1. <hi>You rich men, weepe, crying for your ſinnes, and your miſeries: your ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are rotten, your cloathes are full of mothes, your gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is ruſtie, and their ruſtineſſe ſhall witneſſe againſt you, and ſhall eate your fleſh like fire.</hi> Now where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19245:76"/>
wouldeſt thou deſire abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance? 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9. for <hi>Thoſe that would be rich fall into temptation, into the ſnares of the deuill, and into many fooliſh and filthie deſires, which plunge men into deſtruction and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition:</hi> Which the Wiſe man vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood well, when he prayed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, not to giue him riches, but only his daily bread.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iames</hi> 1.2. What is all this but Vanitie vpon Vanitie, which haue no ſooner taken their being, but preſently ſlide away, as if they had neuer beene at all? no more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance left to be ſeene, than of the bird that hath flowen in the ayre, which no man can finde out the tract: He that with ſuch gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe heaped it vp, at his death left it behinde him, and to whom? alas, he knoweth not, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaith, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 15.39.</p>
                  <p>But if it ſhould be of ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19245:77"/>
wouldeſt thou baſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize and ſhorten thy felicitie, to fix thy ſoueraigne good there? tell me how many yeares haſt thou liued, and in what part of thy life didſt thou firſt delight in theſe riches? hath thy life ſince that time beene ſo bleſſed? if thou thinke ſo for a little; at what a value wouldeſt thou haue prized all the World? But liſten, and conſult with Ieſus Chriſt a while. We muſt know, that whoſoeuer ſearcheth and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth theſe things, cannot pleaſe God: for they haue his heart, and not the Lord, and therefore let vs beware whileſt it is light, and learne to miſpriſe and contemne them; following the counſell of IESVS CHRIST, Let vs <hi>lay vp treaſure in Heauen, where neither ruſt nor the mothes can corrupt,</hi> and let vs <hi>thinke of things aboue, and not of thoſe that are below: for whoſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19245:77"/>
euer is not ready to renounce all things that are of this world, and that he poſſeſſeth in the earth,</hi> euen as he himſelfe ſaith, <hi>He cannot be his.</hi> But if once that come to be found in vs, we wil then ſtriue rather to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God, than to poſſeſſe all the riches of the world that are ſo wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: preferring the riches of Chriſt aboue all the treaſures of Egypt, after the example of <hi>Moſes:</hi> and let vs no longer depriue our ſelues from the hearing of the word of God, and of the meanes of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him according to his knowne will, for to heape vp happineſſe more commodiouſly than hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we haue beene accuſtomed: deſiring with <hi>Dauid</hi> to be rather a doore keeper in the houſe of God, than to enioy all the pleaſures and delights of the fleſh that may be: for happy are they that dwell in Gods houſe, and thoſe that are far
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19245:78"/>
from it moſt vnhappy; <hi>Amos</hi> 8.2. <hi>There is no greater miſery than to haue a famine of Gods word.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There are, I feare, too many that to pleaſe themſelues and their owne humors turne away from God, as if it were a diſgrace to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, preferring the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall life before the Spirituall, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing more care of the body than the ſoule, like thoſe that loue their apparell better than themſelues; neuertheleſſe, ſuch are ſometimes put to their proofe, becauſe of the defects that are in Men, of their infirmitie and baſeneſſe, hauing not yet taſted the promiſes of God: yet there cannot any thing be more deteſtable, and more to be condemned: No; and we may ſay what we will, to colour ſuch an offence; but it is (to ſpeake properly) no other than to put man in Gods place; for we make
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19245:78"/>
lying man true, and God which is Truth it ſelfe, falſe: we make man who is altogether feeble, mightie; and God who is Power it ſelfe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powerfull, in putting our truſt in man (as it is in this behalfe) and vpon his promiſes: and of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, we doe nothing but diſtruſt that which is promiſed vnto vs by God, and hold our ſelues ſtrong enough to the buſineſſe: although this is his voice, <hi>Math.</hi> 6.25. <hi>Take no care for your life what you ſhall eat or drinke, nor for what you ſhall put on.</hi> If God, ſaith <hi>Ieſus Chriſt, feed the fowles of the aire, and clotheth the graſſe of the field, will he not doe more for you, O ye of little faith: Aske then,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and ſeeke firſt the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God and the righteouſneſſe thereof, and all theſe things ſhall be giuen vnto you: and be not carefull for to morrow.</hi> This is the Word of God, theſe are his promiſes, yet
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19245:79"/>
notwithſtanding, for all this, in ſted of turning to him, who hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed neuer to leaue vs, nor to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon vs (from whence <hi>S. Paul</hi> argueth, that we muſt <hi>be content with things preſent</hi>) we turne to men, and hope in them for all our neceſſities: and if any rich man haue made a profeſſion of amitie, &amp; promiſed vs that his purſe ſhall be open in our needes, preſently we make account as of a moſt ſure poſſeſſion, and we doe cheriſh it in ſuch ſort that we will not by any meanes diſpleaſe ſuch a friend: euen to the great diſhonour of God, whom we leaue euen as he from whom we can receiue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or hope for any benefit: who is he (except it be with a maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and deteſtable ingratitude) dare accuſe God, and ſay he is not powerfull, or that he will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh that which he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19245:79"/>
and ſo to make him a lyar? a thing infinitely (as the offence is infinite) horrible to thinke vpon: attributing that to man which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth only to God, He to whom euery thing belongeth, who brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the rich to pouertie, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the poore into glory, making him to abound in all happineſſe.</p>
                  <p>Here may ſome take occaſion to ſay, we will henceforth labour no more, and caſt away all care, and put our truſt only in God and his promiſes: but we muſt know that that would be but only to tempt him; who hath not made vs to ſhew our ſelues careleſſe in our vocation: we haue ſhewed our ſelues careleſſe in not employing our ſelues to that which we are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto, ſince that he himſelfe hath ordained (as a marke and cauſe of our iniquitie) <hi>that we ſhall eat our bread in the ſweat of our brow
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19245:80"/>
all the daies of our life:</hi> which made <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſay, that <hi>he that laboured not ſhould not eat:</hi> which is the reaſon why the Pſalmiſt ſaith, conſidering we are conſtrained to it (ſpeaking to him that feareth God and wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in his waies) <hi>Of thy labour thou ſhalt liue, and thy buſineſſe ſhall happily goe forward:</hi> but the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall end of theſe promiſes, is to the end that we be not loſt, when by Gods prouidence, we ſhall want all poſſeſſions, and alſo be depriued of receiuing fruit from any thing we can doe; a trauell ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vaine if God giue not his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, without the which, wherefore doe we watch ſo late, and riſe ſo early, and after all this, yet <hi>we know from mans helpe commeth nothing, but only from God,</hi> who raiſeth and pulleth downe whom he liſt; of him I ſpeake who wanteth nothing to giue to thoſe that are in need:
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19245:80"/>
and ſo let vs bee brought to walke in his obedience and feare, as wholly depending vpon him, euen the moſt mighty and great aboue all creatures.</p>
                  <p>But let vs returne, and a little fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcouer our filthineſſe: doe we not ſee that neuertheleſſe that God aſſureth vs, that none can take a haire from our head without his will; and that it is that which <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>If God be for vs, who can be againſt vs?</hi> and although hee ſay, he will preſerue his people as the apple of his eye (inticing vs, as it were, to embrace his loue) yet how much is our diſtruſt notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding? and if it happen, that we bee either threatned with baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or to bee apprehended for the profeſſion of God and his truth, at the firſt wee are wholly terrified, euen to diſauow him, and to be diſpoſed to yeeld to any
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19245:81"/>
thing that the aduerſarie will haue vs confeſſe: the moſt part of theſe that follow the great and wide way (euen of perdition) and who (as they ſay) howle like wolues; doe they not with a kinde of feare foreſee it, even before it commeth? although Chriſt doth teach vs, that we ſhould not feare him which can kill the bodie, and not hurt the ſoule, but feare him that can kill the ſoule, and put the bodie into Hell: wee hauing ſpoken before, that whoſoeuer would ſaue his life ſhall loſe it; but hee that for the loue of God would loſe it, ſhall ſaue it.</p>
                  <p>If we be not ſufficiently confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to leade vs to condemnation: let vs imagine ſome ſilly body that hath offended a greater than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who deſireth to be reuenged; if the offender finde ſome fauour with the Prince, that he will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19245:81"/>
him from all danger whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he can be ſubiect vnto, the Prince declaring to all his ſubiects his loue to this man, and that he will defend him euen as himſelfe; will we not ſay, that this is a good warrant? ſhall we not eſteeme him out of all danger of feare? and will we not eaſily beleeue the power of the Prince will preſerue him? But this great God, who is the Prince of Princes, who hath power aboue all power (more ſoueraignly pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull without all compariſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all Princes, than any earthly Prince hath power ouer the poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt vaſſall in the world) to whom nothing is impoſſible, the only True, the Vnmouable, cannot hee keepe vs? and wherefore? ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny innumerable benefits haue we receiued, and daily doe receiue of him, fulfilling his promiſes, ought not theſe to bee ſufficient to make
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19245:82"/>
vs put all our truſt and confidence in him, and no way to doubt the ſure effect of his word?</p>
                  <p>O! peruerſe diſtruſt, and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience more than vnthankfull! to preferre the truſt in men before the truſt in God, to haue more feare to pleaſe men than God, euen to the turning backe from God, to follow <hi>Baal;</hi> as <hi>Balaam</hi> did, who for vnjuſt hire put himſelfe out of the right way.</p>
                  <p>Many will not confeſſe the debt, but will ſay (although their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſpeake to the contrarie) without feare of malediction pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by the Eternall, againſt thoſe that will ſay, and make men beleeue the euill to bee good, and the good to bee euill, that they walke according to God in all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity without diſſimulation, who for hiding ſo much more their hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, they will bee carefull to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19245:82"/>
obſerue greateſt idolatries and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, and will bee glad to make knowne to euery one that they omit nothing of that which is neceſſary for ſuch a one as they feigne to bee: and to the end they may not bee doubted at all, but to bee truly ſincere, they make their children take this poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and nouriſh them in this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nome, which one day they will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for before God: wherein they openly make warre againſt the truth: alſo wee may ſee how ſuch impieties and iniquities plunge them into a reprobate ſenſe, <hi>Sap.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Man being puniſhed by the ſame things wherein he ſinned,</hi> which alwayes happeneth to thoſe that mocke God, 4. <hi>Ezdr.</hi> 16, <hi>who knoweth the intentions of men,</hi> what they thinke in their hearts, in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and in deſiring to hide their ſinnes: alas, the condition of ſuch
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19245:83"/>
people had better neuer to haue knowne the way of righteouſneſſe and truth, than after they haue knowne it, to turne behinde the holy Commandement: ſinfull people, people rooted in iniquity, corrupt children, to leaue the Lord in ſuch a ſort, prouoking the Holy one of Iſrael! alas, what will the recompence be of ſuch idleneſſe?</p>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.39. Thoſe that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit theſe impieties, can deceiue men, but not God, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.24. <hi>who is the only ſearcher of all hearts, from whom nothing is hid.</hi> He will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt them in their due time; <hi>for there is nothing ſo ſecret, but when he pleaſeth, it ſhall come to be reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, Matth.</hi> 10.26. <hi>and ſeene euen on the houſe tops,</hi> euen when it is leaſt expected: and ſhall ſay vnto them one day, (it may be much ſooner than they expect) if they repent not preſently, without abuſing of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19245:83"/>
his mercy, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.41. <hi>Goe yee accurſed into euerlaſting fire, which is prepared for the Deuill and his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels:</hi> and then will they crie out in vaine, <hi>Lord,</hi> but it will be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 2. <hi>I neuer knew you, yee workers of iniquity, who haue loued the glory of men more than of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>O! how horrible it is to fall into the hands of the liuing God; hee which not only ſeeth our actions, but alſo is Iudge of our intentions, and indeed to whoſe eies all things are knowne and diſcouered. Let vs not any longer defer our repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; let vs ſtriue to doe well, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to walke before the eternall, who contemplateth all our deeds, and ſearcheth the reines, and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineth the thoughts, hauing nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wiſdome, force, prudence, or ſecret place vnknowne to him, knowing that he will neuer deale
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19245:84"/>
better with vs, for hiding our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities from men, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding we ordinarily thinke hee ſeemeth to ſuffer or forget, yet doth nothing leſſe, for without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance hee will be confeſſed to our wofull condemnation, that he forgetteth nothing; and therefore in all feare, let vs apply our mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to righteouſneſſe, and with <hi>S. Paul, Rom.</hi> 12.1 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18, 19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.4. <hi>Let vs offer our bodies as a liuing ſacrifice, holy, pleaſing to God, which is our reaſonable ſeruice: Let vs ſleepe no longer in our vaine conuerſation, from whence we are redeemed, neither with gold nor ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, but with the precious bloud of the Sonne of God.</hi> And now let vs awake, let vs awake, I ſay, to ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification and newneſſe of life, leſt that it ſhould proue the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſlumber of eternall death. Let not the world nor the things of the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19245:84"/>
world any longer hinder our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, to conſtraine our continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in this horrible hypocriſie; being content with the condition which it hath pleaſed the Lord to call vs vnto, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. ſeeing that all things turne to good to thoſe that feare God: So that pouerty when it findeth vs, may not affright vs, nor perſecution aſtoniſh vs, when wee muſt beare it for the name of the Eternall; but let vs ſuffer with Chriſt cheerefully, to the end to reigne with him eternally: And let not the workes of the worldly, which are ſeruile, euer trouble vs, nor any thing, no not the very loſſe of life, may make vs decline from the way of the Lord; for <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18. <hi>The ſufferings of the time preſent, are not worthy to be compared to thoſe bleſsings which are to come, which are reſerued for vs in Chriſt,</hi> which <hi>S. Paul, Philip.</hi> 1.21.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19245:85"/>
ſaith, <hi>It is not only gaine for vs to liue, but to die;</hi> and hereafter let vs not run to any vnlawfull meanes, but only to God, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.14. <hi>who giueth bleſsings and curſes, life and death, pouerty and riches,</hi> and who, I ſay, hath ſo loued vs, that he hath giuen his only Sonne to die for vs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3. will he ſuffer vs to want thoſe things that are infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely leſſe? No, he will let vs want nothing that is fitting for our good: his eye watcheth ouer them alwayes that feare him and truſt in him; for he is our ſtrength, our hope, and our ſure fortreſſe: and let vs chaſe away all vanitie, and caſt away the fooliſh &amp; curſed confidence which wee ordinarily haue in the arme of man, and in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and from henceforth let vs not looke for any other thing in all the reſt of our pilgrimage, but to glorifie God, and to edifie our
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19245:85"/>
neighbours, putting our whole truſt in him; as <hi>Dauid</hi> did, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 40.4. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that maketh the Lord his truſt, and reſpecteth not the proud, nor ſuch as turne aſide to lies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let vs renounce our owne wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome which is but follie, for ſo the Spirit of God calleth it, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 5.2. <hi>Woe vnto them that are wiſe in their owne eies, and prudent in their owne ſight:</hi> and let vs no longer thinke our felicitie dependeth in the deſires of the fleſh (which is the all in all of bruit beaſts, who die together both in ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy) but that there is a ſoueraigne and eternall good for thoſe that walke in the feare of the Lord: let vs eſteeme this aboue all other things, knowing that the world and the deſires of it vaniſh away, and that <hi>all the glory of man is like the flower of the graſſe which is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19245:86"/>
but the word of God remaineth for euer,</hi> and therefore let vs ſay with <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 62. <hi>That our ſoule only repoſeth in God, for from him only is our ſaluation,</hi> euery day re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring this prayer, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 90. <hi>O Lord teach vs to number our daies, that we may apply our hearts vnto wiſdome;</hi> waiting for the full en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying of all the benefits which are purchaſed for vs, by the Death and Reſurrection of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> to the participation of this eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall beatitude, and of the vnion which we haue by him in God: to whom only wiſe, only powerfull, infinite, and our only Creator, be all honor and glory world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end, through <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> his only Sonne and our only Sauiour, who in the vnitie of the Holy Ghoſt, liueth and reigneth with him eternally. Amen.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:19245:86"/>
                     <head>The Almighty power of God and his will.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>Wherein is declared, how the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie power of God and of his will, ought to rule our faith in the receiuing of the holy Sacrament.</p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O binde vs to beleeue the Tranſubſtantiation of bread with the bodie of Ieſus Chriſt, our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries ſet before vs the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie power of God, who (they ſay)
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19245:87"/>
hath wrought as great miracles; whereupon wee ſay, That vſe wee ought to make of the Almightie power of God, is to beleeue that hee will doe all which hee hath promiſed in his word, but not to beleeue all that wee would imagine. By that way one may defend the moſt falſe and abſurd things in the world, in ſaying that God is powerfull enough to doe it: The power of God is not the rule of our religion, but his will.</p>
                     <p>For to know if the bread of the Euchariſt becommeth fleſh, and tranſubſtantiateth it ſelfe into the bodie of Ieſus Chriſt, one muſt not begin with the conſideration of the Almightie power of God; but wee muſt firſt informe our ſelues of his will in his word. And if wee finde that God will haue it
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19245:87"/>
ſo, we muſt beleeue it without all difficultie.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, we learne in the Goſpell, that Ieſus Chriſt hauing taken the bread, <hi>gaue it.</hi> He gaue bread then. But it is not giuen vntill after the Conſecration.</p>
                     <p>Alſo we finde, that Ieſus Chriſt giuing this bread, ſaid, <hi>This is my bodie.</hi> And to ſhew that that which he gaue was his bodie, hee addeth, that it is done in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of him. For ordinarily the Scripture calleth the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance or repreſentatiue ſigne of any thing of name, with that it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth and repreſenteth, in the ſame manner, as when we ſay, This is the King, when wee ſee but the portrait. If then this Sacrament be the commemoration of Ieſus Chriſt, it is not Ieſus Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: for a man cannot bee the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19245:88"/>
remembrance of himſelfe.</p>
                     <p>This appeareth cleerely by that which is added. For Ieſus Chriſt giuing the cup, ſaid, <hi>This cap is the new Teſtament in my bloud.</hi> From whence it appeareth, that this cup is not the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, for the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt is not in the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, and ſo cannot hee bloud of his bloud. If I ſay that Baptiſme is the new Teſtament in the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, by conſequence I ſay, that Baptiſme is not the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt. So Ieſus Chriſt ſaying, that the cup is the Teſtament in his bloud, alſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie cleerely ſaith, that the cup is not his bloud.</p>
                     <p>And euen as a man doth not find it ſtrange, that Ieſus ſaid, that the cup is an alliance, although the cup, nor that which is within is not
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19245:88"/>
tranſubſtantiated into an alliance, but only is the Sacrament of the alliance of Ieſus Chriſt; ſo we may not finde it ſtrange, if Ieſus Chriſt giuing the bread, hath ſaid, that it was his bodie, although it bee not tranſubſtantiated into his bodie.</p>
                     <p>And <hi>S. Matthew</hi> in the 26. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 29. Ieſus Chriſt hauing giuen the cup to his Diſciples, ſaid vnto them, <hi>Henceforth I will not drinke of the fruit of this vine:</hi> hee drunke then the fruit of the vine, and not of the bloud. For although that there had beene two cups, yet <hi>S. Matthew</hi> ſpeaketh but of one, and calleth not the fruit of the vine, the wine of one cup, he ſpeaketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it.</p>
                     <p>Alſo wee finde the Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul</hi> in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16. ſaith three times, <hi>We eat of this bread, and drinke
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19245:89"/>
of this cup:</hi> ſo we ſee it is ſtill bread that they did eat.</p>
                     <p>The ſame Apoſtle in the ſame chapter and 16. verſe ſaith, <hi>The bread which we eat is the communion of the bodie of Chriſt:</hi> he ſaith, <hi>The bread which wee breake:</hi> it is then bread when it is broken in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament: yet it is not broken but after the conſecration.</p>
                     <p>So in the 20. of the <hi>Acts</hi> 17. the Diſciples are aſſembled <hi>to breake the bread:</hi> It was bread then they broke amongſt them, and not fleſh.</p>
                     <p>Ieſus Chriſt ſaith in the 12. of <hi>S. Iohn</hi> 8. <hi>You ſhall alwayes haue the poore, but you cannot haue me alwaies.</hi> And in the 16. ver. 18. <hi>I leaue the world, and goe to my Father,</hi> And in the 10. <hi>I am no more of the world.</hi> This ſentence ſhould bee falſe, if we ſhould haue Ieſus Chriſt ſhut
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19245:89"/>
vp within a peece of bread, if hee were yet remaining in the world. For he ſaith, <hi>You ſhall not haue mee alwayes.</hi> Now may one anſwer, that we haue Ieſus Chriſt no more viſibly; which is nothing to the purpoſe: for to haue Ieſus Chriſt inuiſibly, is alwayes to haue Ieſus Chriſt. Hee ſhould bee a lier that ſhould ſay hee had no money, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his money was hid: or hee that ſhould ſay hee had no ſoule, becauſe it is inuiſible.</p>
                     <p>And it is a ſtrange libertie which the Doctors of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church take; for to make theſe texts of no value, they interpret them figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely, and for to ſhunne a naturall and vſuall figure in ſpeaking of the Sacraments, they introduce a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen of vnuſuall figures without example.</p>
                     <p>The action intirely whole of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19245:90"/>
Chriſt and of his Diſciples, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth for vs: for the Apoſtles ſate at the Table without any kinde of adoration, which ſhould haue been a very great irreuerence in them, to eat Ieſus Chriſt, and to ſacrifice him to God without making any adoration, which is ſo much more remarkable, becauſe the Apoſtles neuer gaue aſſiſtance in ſuch an action, and alſo becauſe it was the firſt inſtitution of this Sacrament, which is giuen for a patterne to the end to make them hereafter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable. Alſo we ſee not that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt maketh any eleuation of the Hoſt, hee preſenteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to God, but only to his Diſciples. To conclude, in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry action Ieſus Chriſt doth the contrary to that which is done in the Maſſe.</p>
                     <p>The text of the Maſſe maketh for
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19245:90"/>
vs, wherin the Prieſt, after the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, asketh of God that hee take <hi>this offering as acceptable as euer the Sacrifice of Abel was acceptable vnto him:</hi> a prayer that was good before Tranſubſtantiation was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued. But in theſe daies, is it not a great offence to God, to entreat him to accept the Sacrifice of his Sonne as acceptable, as a beaſt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by <hi>Abel?</hi> And which is more, the Prieſt deſireth of God that the Offring which he holdeth may be acceptable through Ieſus Chriſt: he beleeueth not then that hee hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>And to take away all doubt, the Prieſt long after the Conſecration, looketh vpon the Hoaſt and the Cup ſtanding vpon the Altar, and ſaith that <hi>theſe are goods which God hath alwaies created, which he viui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth and ſanctifieth through Ieſus
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19245:91"/>
Chriſt.</hi> All this may he ſay of bread and wine, but not one of theſe words can agree with the body of Ieſus Chriſt: for can the bodie of Ieſus Chriſt be called goods in the plurall? Doth God create alwaies Ieſus Chriſt? Doth God alwaies vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uifie Ieſus Chriſt, ſeeing that Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe ſaith, that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is life? Doth God create Ieſus Chriſt by Ieſus Chriſt? Truly if theſe things ſhould be ſpoken o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly before the people in the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar tongue, they would be much offended: &amp; that is the reaſon why they ſay their Seruice in an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne tongue, againſt the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Ieſus Chriſt, and againſt the ſaying of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. The Prieſt and the Reader ſpeake to a people in a tongue they vnderſtand not. The ſixt of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> maketh alſo for the truth which wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend;
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19245:91"/>
for although there is nothing ſpoken of the holy Sacrament of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> which was not then inſtituted; yet notwithſtanding he ſpeaketh there of the Communion of the Body of Ieſus Chriſt; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Ieſus Chriſt ſpeaketh in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that he manifeſtly ſheweth he ſpeaketh of a manducation, which is not by the mouth: for he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of a manducation, without the which no man can be ſaued; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>If you doe not eat my fleſh, you ſhall not liue.</hi> So you ſee hee ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not of a manducation by the mouth, without the which ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſons are ſaued, as the good theefe crucified with Ieſus Chriſt, holy <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> and infinite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                     <p>Alſo our Lord ſpeakes of a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, which how many ſoeuer participate thereof, haue eternall
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19245:92"/>
life; for he ſaith, <hi>He that eateth his fleſh hath life eternall;</hi> he ſpeaketh not then of the eating the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with the mouth, which many haue done, and yet eſcaped not damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, witneſſe <hi>Iudas</hi> and many moe Hypocrites. But wee may not ſo conclude nor ſay thereupon, of thoſe that eat the fleſh of Ieſus Chriſt worthily. For wee finde in <hi>S. Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. that ſome eat the bread vnworthily; but we ſhall not finde that the fleſh of Ieſus Chriſt can be eaten vnworthily: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, ſeeing that to eat the fleſh of Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; to drinke his bloud, is to beleeue in his incarnation and in his death; who knowes not that one cannot poſſibly beleeue in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt vnworthily, ſeeing in the beleefe of Ieſus Chriſt conſiſteth our dignitie.</p>
                     <p>But to eat and drinke is to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19245:92"/>
to beleeue; the Doctors and Canons of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſay with vs, and the holy Scripture is full of ſuch manner of ſpeaking; and Ieſus Chriſt in the ſame place ſaith, That <hi>whoſoeuer beleeueth in him, ſhall neuer thirſt;</hi> to the end we may know that this Thirſt is quenched in beleeuing, and not in drinking with the mouth. And a little after hauing ſaid, <hi>Who beleeueth in me, ſhall haue eternal life;</hi> thence he inferreth that he is <hi>the bread of life:</hi> and aduerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vs that theſe words of eating and drinking, are ſpirit and life, for if they bee not taken ſpiritually, they cannot viuifie.</p>
                     <p>Thereupon wee ought not to feare, if Tranſubſtantiation be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, the Sacrament ſhould become contemptible: For Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is not become contemptible,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19245:93"/>
but is more honoured in the Church of Rome, than the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, and is eſteemed a thouſand thouſand times more, albeit the water be not tranſubſtantiated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bloud. For they hold, Baptiſme is neceſſary to ſaluation, but not the Euchariſt. They hold, that by Baptiſme euery kinde of ſinne is wholly forgiuen; but the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt taketh away but veniall ſinnes, and thoſe which they haue freed their conſciences of before. The Sacraments ought not to be hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red but for IESVS CHRISTS ſake, which when you ſhall adore in heauen, whitherto hee is mounted, to returne againe at the laſt day, and ſhall ſerue him according to his word, we need not feare that the memorials which hee hath left in the Church, and by the which he worketh in our hearts, with
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19245:93"/>
efficacie, ſhould euer become con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible. We muſt honour the Sacraments, but wee may not put them in the place of things ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified.</p>
                     <p>All this aboueſaid, ſerueth to ſhew, that for to know the truth in Religion, wee muſt not beginne with the conſideration of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty power of God, but firſt of all enquire after his will; which when it is learned, then the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty power of God that can doe all, aſſureth vs, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to doe all, hee will doe that which hee willed, and that which hee teacheth in his holy word.</p>
                     <p>I will ſay more: It is the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours of the Church of Rome, that diſhonour and diſgrace, the power of the Almighty God, and of Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="64" facs="tcp:19245:94"/>For firſt of all, they make it ſerue to doe things more miraculous than the creation of the world, and yet notwithſtanding no profit commeth by it. For they hold, that Ieſus Chriſt hath eaten him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, for hee hath participated in the holy Sacrament with his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; and yet notwithſtanding they cannot declare vnto vs, to what end ſuch a prodigious and incomprehenſible thing ſerueth for; that a man hath his head and his body in his mouth, and that Ieſus Chriſt is entred into the ſtomacke of IESVS CHRIST.</p>
                     <p>Alſo they hold, that Miſe can eat the Body of the Lord. What a horrible ſhame and reproch doe they make the Sonne of God to be to the Church of God! For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that Ieſus Chirſt doe not
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19245:94"/>
ſuffer, yet hee is mightily diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured.</p>
                     <p>Alſo, they put Ieſus Chriſt vpon the Hoaſt, whereupon they ſay, that hee can neither open his eies, nor remoue the hands, nor breath, and therefore he hath not the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er which other men haue. Is this to magnifie the power of the Sonne of God? or is it to diminiſh it, to the end to lift vp the power of Prieſts? who haue the power giuen them, as they teach, to make Ieſus Chriſt; which is a thing, that the bleſſed Virgin Mary, and all the Angels, and Saints together, could neuer doe.</p>
                     <p>What ſerueth it for to the Church of God, that Ieſus Chriſt in the Hoaſt hath two eies, and that he is wholly intire in euery crum of the Hoaſt, and his Body intire in euery drop of the Cup? And that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19245:95"/>
in the Hoaſt it hath the length, and yet nothing long, as the Doctors of the Romane Church doe teach? We ought neuer to exalt the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty power of God in the employment of vnprofitable things.</p>
                     <p>And indeed, the examples which they bring to hold vp Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation, are examples of the workes of God, which haue beene profitable, and the vſe whereof is apparent. As when God created the world, and brought forth the light; and changed the rod into a Serpent; and conuerted water into wine.</p>
                     <p>It is needfull to conſider, that in theſe miracles of Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, God hath conuerted one ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance into another, which was not before the changing of it: For the rod of <hi>Moſes</hi> was changed into a
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19245:95"/>
Serpent, which was not ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the changing; and at the mariage in <hi>Cana</hi> in <hi>Galilee,</hi> the Lord conuerted water into wine, which was not ſo before the conuerſion. But they would that God ſhould heere conuert the bread into a body which is already: As if a man ſhould beget a man that is already borne; or ſhould turne money into gold which is already gold: Or who would goe about to make the Moone, vnleſſe it were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>made. Beſides, the word of God expreſly ſaith, that <hi>the water was conuerted into wine;</hi> but it ſaith not, that the bread was conuerted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to fleſh. In giuing the bread, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt ſaith, <hi>That it is his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> in ſuch ſort, as it was needfull it ſhould be bread, and alſo that it ſhould bee the body
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19245:96"/>
of Chriſt. For bread cannot be in ſubſtance the body of Chriſt, but it may well bee in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and according as the ſignes and memorials take the name, of that which they ſignifie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent.</p>
                     <p>We exalt the almighty power of the Sonne of God in this, that without deſcending from heauen he communicateth himſelfe vnto vs; but the Church of Rome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableth this power, in ſubiecting it to the will of a man, which diuers times happening is found no good man, who maketh Ieſus Chriſt when he will, and afterwards ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it; whereupon it happeneth that Ieſus Chriſt is ſometimes ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by his enemies, and alſo (as they ſay) euen by beaſts; if the Hoaſt be ſtollen, if it fall vpon the ground, if wormes and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19245:96"/>
get into it: if a lew ſtrike it with a knife and maketh it bleed, as it is painted in the Billettes of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris:</hi> if (as the cautions of the Meſſe and the penitentiall Canons ſay) the Prieſt or the ſicke man reuomit vp the Hoaſt through infirmity: All which redoundeth to the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe and diſhonour of Ieſus Chriſt, which is the eternall Sonne of God.</p>
                     <p>They ſay for excuſe, that the dogs licked vp ſome of the bloud of Chriſt Ieſus: but all that is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the purpoſe; for Ieſus Chriſt was expreſly heere in this world to ſuffer ignominie, and to be ſubiect to infirmities: but now he is exempt from all opprobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and infirmitie. And moreouer, all that hee then ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: was for our ſaluation. But one may well ſay vnto me, To
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19245:97"/>
what end ſerueth it that Ieſus Chriſt ſhould ſtill be ſubiect to ſo many indignities aboue ſpoken of? If a Mouſe hath carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Hoaſt, or the Cup bee ſpilt, what ſerueth that to our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation?</p>
                     <p>And if our Aduerſaries were asked, what becommeth of the Bodie of Ieſus Chriſt receiued into the ſtomacke: whether it goe out, or remaine alwaies there, or nothing commeth of it: alſo how Ieſus Chriſt hath one body like vnto ours, and of like nature, ſeeing it is in an hundred thouſand places at one time, and hee is wholly entire in euery part of the Hoaſt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the feete thorowout the Hoaſt, and the head thorowout the Hoaſt, and head and feet vnder one point, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19245:97"/>
hauing a humane body without extenſion, and a length vnder one point, and a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance without extenſion: where the Body which was at the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, a little after in the Garden, was afflicted and ſweat drops of Bloud: and he who in the ſame time was in the mouthes and ſtomacks of the Apoſtles, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred nothing and was impaſſible, and yet neuertheleſſe was but one body: I beleeue that they found themſelues much troubled; where ſince that <hi>Iudas</hi> hath eaten Ieſus Chriſt in the Euchariſt, and euen at the ſame time the deuill entred into him; can it bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient or poſſible to thinke that Ieſus Chriſt and the deuill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into one body together, and remained together?</p>
                     <p>One thing I thinke is very
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19245:98"/>
conuenient, that in euery Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as alſo at the ſacrifice, it is neceſſary that the thing which they adminiſter to the people, and that they offer to God, bee conſecrated: but in the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt of the Roman Church there is nothing of conſecrate which is adminiſtred to the people, nor which is offered to God: for is this the bread which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated? No way: for they ſay it is no more bread. Is it the body of Ieſus Chriſt? it is not: for Ieſus Chriſt cannot bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated, but it is he that conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crateth vs. Are theſe the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of bread which are conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated, that they call formes, that is to ſay, the roundneſſe, the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and taſte of the bread? It is not neither; for theſe things are not offered to God in ſacrifice:
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19245:98"/>
neither are they giuen to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for to ſanctifie them. But behold one Sacrament and one ſacrifice, where there is nothing conſecrated: where he doth make a Conſecration, but they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay what it is that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated.</p>
                     <p>All this abuſe commeth by the fault of ſome Prieſts, who could if they would, make vs all agree very eaſily in one way. For all confeſſe that Ieſus Chriſt hath inſtituted the holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament as it ought to bee, and that there is nothing to ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
                     <p>If then the Pope would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Holy Supper into the ſame forme wherein Ieſus Chriſt inſtituted it, in ſpeaking as hee did, and doing as hee did, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further diſpute, we ſhould
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19245:99"/>
all agree, and ſo wee ſhould all come to be of one aſſembly vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly to glorifie God. By this meanes, diuine ſeruice ſhould bee done in the vulgar tongue; there ſhould be no more priuate Maſſes: All ſhould communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate vnder both kindes; there ſhould be no more adoration of the Hoaſt, nor any eleuation of the ſacrifice: &amp; the Prieſts bending ouer the Altar ſhould not pray to God for ſaluation through the merit of Saints whoſe bones and reliques are hidden vnder the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar. But contenting our ſelues with the preſcribed ſimplicity of Ieſus Chriſt, wee ſhould reiect theſe additions which disfigure this Sacrament vnder the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of adorning it. God giue vs grace to ſee this happy time, and to that end diſpoſe of the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19245:99"/>
hearts of Princes and people, for the loue of IESVS CHRIST our LORD. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19245:100"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19245:100"/>
                  <p>COMFORTABLE INSTRVCTIONS for the SICKE: By <hi>Peter Moulin,</hi> Miniſter in the Reformed Church at PARIS.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T.S.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Pauier,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Iuie lane.</hi> 1623.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19245:101"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19245:101"/>
                  <head>Short and Familiar In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions to comfort the SICKE.</head>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>When the ſickneſſe appeareth not to be mortall: For the comfort of the party, one may thus beginne.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, it behooueth you firſt to acknowledge that this ſickeneſſe is not fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len vpon you by chance, but by the wiſe conduct and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Almightie God, our Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and Father, who ſo diſpoſeth of proſperitie and aduerſity, health and ſickneſſe vpon his children, that he neuer ſendeth either the one or
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19245:102"/>
the other, but to his owne glory, and the parties good and ſaluation. As the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom. 8.27. Wee know that all things worke together for good to them that loue God.</hi> He purpoſely ſpeaketh of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, wherein ſickneſſes are ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. Thoſe people loue God, who are firſt loued of him, and as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, <hi>called according to his owne determinated purpoſe.</hi> That you are of this number, you haue occaſion to take aſſurance by the faith which hee hath giuen you, in making you beleeue that he is your Father and Sauiour, in his Welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Sonne <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> our Lord, by which you receiue the ſpirit of adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is that that witneſſeth with our ſpirit, that we are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, Heires, and co-heires with Chriſt, <hi>Rom. 8.11.16.17.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You muſt alſo take aſſurance by the ſanctification of his holy ſpirit,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19245:102"/>
by which he hath brought you into his obedience: <hi>For thoſe that are led by the ſpirit of God, are the children of God.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>But to thoſe which are ſuch, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>that euery thing workes together for good:</hi> affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, ſickneſſes, euen death it ſelfe: all that they haue is turned, by the grace of God to their owne profit, and great good, and for the aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; furtherance of their ſaluation.</p>
                        <p>Three principall fruits, God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs gather of our maladies and afflictions.</p>
                        <p>The firſt is the amendement of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> our life, which awaketh vs out of our ſinnes. For both in health and proſperity, it is too ordinary to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and cheriſh our ſelues in ſinne, by reaſon of our great corruption in Nature, which maketh vs inclined to all euill, and vnprofitable to any
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19245:103"/>
good: it is therefore neceſſarie to looke about vs, and become more ſenſible of our ſinnes, to retire our ſelues, and to be diſpleaſed with them; which is made by the meanes of ſickneſſes, and other aduerſities of this life, occaſioned by ſinne, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry often purpoſely ſent from God to chaſtiſe and correct vs: and in that this good Father of Heauen ſheweth how much he loueth vs, hindering our vndoing, and confuſion, in our inordinate life; like a good Father, that very well loueth his Children, hee chaſtiſeth and correcteth vs, to hinder and draw vs backe againe, leſt we ſhould be loſt; as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, in the 1. of the <hi>Corin. 32.</hi> Verſe, <hi>When we are afflicted, we are taught by the Lord, to the end, we ſhould not be condemned with the world:</hi> and in another place he ſaith, <hi>Heb. 12. Ver. 6.7. and 11. That the Lord chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him he loueth, and beateth euery
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19245:103"/>
childe whom he auoweth:</hi> If you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure Chaſtiſement, God preſenteth himſelfe vnto vs, as to his Children; <hi>For, who is the childe that the Father correcteth not? and although that all diſcipline in the inſtant, ſeeme not to be of ioy, but of ſadneſſe; neuertheleſſe it brings a peaceable fruit of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe to thoſe that thereby are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed:</hi> It behooueth vs therefore firſt of all, to gather this excellent fruit of our ſickneſſes, to feele the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable number of our ſinnes and offences, wherof we are culpable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God; to aske pardon of him in all humility and repentance, and to make a holy proteſtation to liue bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hereafter; and to walke in his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and feare, by the grace of God, and the conduct of his holy Spirit: which we ought to aske with ardent prayers, and with an aſſured faith to be heard according to his promiſes. And ſo we may ſay with <hi>Dauid,</hi> that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19245:104"/>
excellent ſeruant of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>Ver.</hi> 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. <hi>&amp;</hi> 92. <hi>Before I was afflicted, I went aſtray, but now I haue kept thy word. It is good for mee that I haue beene afflicted, that I might learne thy ſtatutes.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Now we may behold the ſickneſſes of our Bodies, how they come to be by Gods grace wholſome medicines for our ſoules.</p>
                        <p>
                           <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond good which ſickneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes bring vs; is to vnlooſe, and pull away our hearts out of the earth, to lift them vp to heauen.</p>
                        <p>Experience teacheth, that our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections are but too much rooted and tyed here below, whileſt we are in health, and at our caſe, we would willingly neuer part from it, wee would be content that our ſoueraigne good &amp; felicitie were here aſſigned, ſo ſtupid and blinde wee are: But God who hath deſtinated vs to a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19245:104"/>
better life, maketh vs behold and perceiue how vaine and deceitfull the preſent imaginary ſweetneſſes and proſperities are: For when hee pleaſeth to viſite vs with any ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, then we begin to conſider the many miſeries and incommodities that lackey our liues along euen from the cradle to the ſepulchre, which maketh vs know, and cry out with <hi>Eſay, 47. v. 6. That all fleſh is like graſſe, and all the glory of it, no better then a flower of the field;</hi> And <hi>Dauid,</hi> Pſalme 90. That the flower of <hi>this ſhort life is ſuch, that wee are alwayes in paine and Martyrdome:</hi> And with <hi>Iob 14. That man that is borne of a woman, is but of ſhort life, and full of care.</hi> Which is the cauſe wherefore God maketh vs remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, principally when we feele our ſelues ſicke, or otherwiſe afflicted, to make vs contemne the world, and aſpire to heauen, making this miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19245:105"/>
life diſtaſtefull, that we may by meditation taſte of the Heauenly life, to the end that where our Treaſure is, there may be alſo our heart, and that our faith and hope being retyred from the world, and from the things of the world; wee may be lifted vp where they haue their true obiects; that is, to God, and to eternall life. For faith alſo is not of things viſible, but inuiſible, and Hope is not of preſent goods, but of goods to come, that is to ſay, of Heauenly and Eternall goods, purchaſed by Ieſus Chriſt; goods ſo great and incomprehenſible, which as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>1 Cor. 1.9. Eye hath not ſeene, nor eare hath vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, nor is not come vp into the heart of man, which God hath prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for thoſe that loue him.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> There is alſo a third fruit very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent which God maketh vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19245:105"/>
of ſickeneſſes which he ſendeth vs; for by this meanes we come to the tryall and proofe, for to purifie and amend our faith, making it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to his glory, and to the edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of our neighbour. For as by this meanes, our faith is excited, and raiſed vp from the world to God, from earth to heauen, from this life, to the moſt happy and permanent for euer: So is it by ſuch prooues examined and exerciſed, and euen as it were refined and purified; like gold that is tryed and purified in the fire: as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7. It is alſo brought in eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and to the light, with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, conſtancy, and other Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an vertues, which God hath put in vs, without the which wee ſhould not be knowne of any, and ſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of our neighbours ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine without all vſe or profit. And certainely wee ſhould neuer
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19245:106"/>
haue knowne what the patience of <hi>Iob</hi> had beene, of <hi>Abraham, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> and many other excellent ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God, if God had not made them paſſe through the fire of proofes and temptations, and at this day we ſhould not haue had ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny faire examples as we haue, to comfort and incourage vs to their imitation. It is the ſame of Chriſtian faith and patience, as of a Souldier and his valour, who neuer ſeeth well but in the middle of the combat; or of the cleareneſſe of Stars, which are not beheld but in the night; or the odour of incenſe, which is not ſmelt till it be caſt into the fire: So God maketh knowne to our brethren the courage which he hath giuen vs, when hee maketh it come to our hands, with ſome rude and violent ſickeneſſe: hee manifeſteth vnto them the cleareneſſe of our faith, when hee couereth vs with ſome
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19245:106"/>
night of affliction: he maketh them ſmell the odour of our patience, when he caſteth vs into any fire of aduerſity: and by this meanes our brethren are not onely inſtructed, edified, and comforted by this our good example; but likwiſe led to praiſe and glorifie God, who ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theneth and ſuſtaineth vs in the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of our fleſh, which demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrateth and accompliſheth his great vertue in our great infirmitie.</p>
                        <p>Now behold the principall and moſt notable ſpirituall fruits which God of his bounty propoundeth vnto vs, what we may gather of our corporall ſickeneſſes.</p>
                        <p>And therefore <hi>Sir,</hi> now that God doth viſite you with this maladie, and putteth you into this bed of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, it behoueth you to know and to acknowledge that this is his fatherly hand that handleth you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner, as one of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19245:107"/>
and by which he calleth you to reioyce in thoſe excellent fruits and profits, which haue beene declared for his glory, and for your good and ſaluation.</p>
                        <p>You muſt likewiſe acknowledge, that he would raiſe you out of your ſinnes and faults, and would haue you effectually feele a diſpleaſure within your ſelfe, that you may ſeeke for true pardon in Chriſts mercies; renouncing withall your heart your former euill life, with a ſound reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution hereafter to ſerue him, and to walke in his feare with more zeale and affection then you haue done heretofore, wholly relying vpon his grace; Is not this that you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Patient.</speaker>
                        <p>It is.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <p>Alſo conſider, it is his will by this meanes to make you feele the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19245:107"/>
of this life, that you may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne and tread down theſe world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vanities vnder foote, to the ende that with all your heart, you may aſpire to the heauenly and eternall life, and thereby to anſwere the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of that condition to which you are called, to be children of God, and not children of men, to haue your conuerſation as Citizens of heauen, and not of earth, and to follow after and ſearch, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, for <hi>Phil. 3.20. Col. 2.12. The things which are aboue, and not thoſe things which are below.</hi> Is not this alſo by Gods grace, your reſolution, to doe all the dayes of your life.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Patient.</speaker>
                        <p>It is.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <p>Acknowledge in the end, that the good will of God is by this ſickneſſe to examine &amp; proue you, to the end, that your faith and your patience
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19245:108"/>
may become more perfect, and that they may be ſeene and manifeſted to your Brethren and neighbours round about you, that thereby they may be comforted and edefied, and giue glory to God, to ſee you ſo pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently and conſtantly to carry the violences and ſorrowes of this affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and that you eſteeme your ſelfe to reſt with a peaceable and quiet minde, to receiue whatſoeuer elſe it ſhall pleaſe God to ſend vnto you: Is not this the reſolution which you take?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Patient.</speaker>
                        <p>It is.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <p>I beſeech God to giue you grace happily to accompliſh your holy promiſes, to his glory, and your owne ſaluation; alſo you muſt with all your heart, often beſeech him, and implore his grace, otherwiſe you ſhall neuer be capable of your ſelfe.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="15" facs="tcp:19245:108"/>But if you earneſtly and ardently deſire him, with a true and a liuely faith, in the Name of his bleſſed Son Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, doubt not but according to his promiſes hee will heare you, and at the preſent be with you, and fill your ſoule full of all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſolation, fortifying you with patience, and in like ſort comforting you as much as is fit for you, by which meanes he will binde you ſo much more to reioyce in his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and to glorifie his holy Name with all obedience. This is his owne ſaying, to all that are afflicted as you are; <hi>Call vpon me in the day of trouble, and I will heare thee:</hi> Is it not then your deſire that here wee call vpon him with you altogether, that he will be pleaſed to aſſiſt you with his mercy?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Patient.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:19245:109"/>
                     <head>A Prayer.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>O Lord our God and mercifull Father, we proſtrate ourſelues here, in all humility, at the feet of thy diuine Maieſtie, to acknowledge that it is too true, that we are vnworthy of thy fauour, and worthy of Hell, if thou ſhouldeſt deale with vs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy Iuſtice, for ſo many offences which we heare confeſſe our ſelues to be guilty of. But we beſeech thee remember thy infinite bounty, be mercifull vnto vs miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſinners, and take pity vpon vs, for the loue of thy bleſſed Sonnes ſake Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of vs in our ſelues, but in the perſon of this Sonne of thy delight, as members of his Body, reconciled to thy Maieſtie by the bleſſing of his death. And as thou art the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mercy, and God of all conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19245:109"/>
rich in compaſſion, and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to all thoſe that call vpon thee, and haue confidence in thee; we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee that thou wilt be pleaſed to ſhew thy ſelfe liberall in generall towards vs all, who now cry out for mercy, and particularly towards the perſon of this thy child and ſeruant, lying in this bed of infirmity: giue him firſt of all to vnderſtand, that no other hand hath ſtrucke him but thine owne, to the end hee may learne to ſubmit himſelfe to it in all humility and reuerence: And to this end, that he may remember that it is a fatherly hand and a gentle, who ſtrikes not to looſe but to ſaue; and after hauing wounded viuifieth, and woundeth by the ſame wounds which it hath made; make him feele that he is a miſerable and poore ſinner, not onely proceeding out of this maſſe of corruption, from whence we all doe come in <hi>Adam,</hi>
                           <pb n="18" facs="tcp:19245:110"/>
but alſo and principally, that ſince it hath pleaſed thee to giue him grace to acknowledge thee the onely true God, and him whom thou haſt ſent, Ieſus Chriſt, in whom conſiſteth eternall life, manifeſting by this meanes thy free adoption in thy welbeloued Sonne, receiuing him to thee, hauing alſo put him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ranke amongſt the number of thy children and ſeruants in thy Church; although he hath not well knowne the aboundant riches of thy mercy, to loue and ſerue thee with all his heart as he ought, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing the world and himſelfe, by reaſon of vnthankefulneſſe natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally bred in him and in vs all, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually rebelling and fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy great bounty and grace. O deare Father, touch him in his heart with a liuely feeling of all his infirmities and offences, to the ende that without flattering of himſelfe,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19245:110"/>
he may condemne himſelfe before thy Maieſty, that he may acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge all Righteouſneſſe to thee, and to himſelfe nothing but confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of face; make him renounce himſelfe wholly, and confeſſe that iuſtly and rightly thou bringeſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him theſe chaſtiſements; and that if thou ſhouldeſt deale with him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his deſerts, thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt binde him vp and throw him euen into eternall deſtruction. Good Lord alſo grant that this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement be alſo but to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him, and not to deiect him into the bottome of deſpaire, and ſo being of one ſide caſt downe, and laid vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ground by thy powerfull hand (not ſo much from the feeling of his ſickeneſſe, as from the feeling of his ſinnes) he may be on the other ſide, by the ſame bleſſed hand, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued and raiſed vp againe in aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red hope, by the conſideration of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19245:111"/>
this thy incomprehenſible mercy, whereof thou haſt giuen vs ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and ſo rich a pledge, as thy welbeloued Sonne Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, whom thou haſt not ſpared, but deliuered to death, euen to the ignominious and wicked death of the Croſſe, to redeeme vs from the ignominious malediction of ſinne: Good Lord, grant that from hence, thy poore diſtreſſed ſeruant may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue all his refuge, fortifie his faith, by the which hee may ſearch and finde in this death and holy obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of thy Sonne; the forgiueneſſe of all his ſinnes, and firmely em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the perfect Righteouſneſſe thereof, where withall being clothed, he may finde peace with thee, and glorifie himſelfe in the hope of thy glory amongſt all his tribulations. And that the ſorrow of his ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wherewith hee is corporally viſited, may be ſweetned with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19245:111"/>
and contentment of his ſoule. And if it be thy pleaſure to recouer him from this ſickeneſſe, to prolong his dayes, whereof thou doeſt giue vs ſome ſignes; good Lord giue him grace to vſe it to thy glory, perpetually beating in minde this thy grace, to conſecrate the reſt of his life with much more affection and zeale then heretofore hee hath done: And make him receiue this ſickeneſſe as a fatherly affliction to draw him from ſinne, and to make him take a holy reſolution by thy grace, all the dayes of his life, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the duty and obedience wherewithall he is bound to thee, to walke in thy feare more purely, and more feruently then euer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore. Bleſſe the remedies which thou art pleaſed to let him vſe, that he may receiue comfort in his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, moderate the ſharpeneſſe of his colour, and ſtay the courſe of it,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19245:112"/>
if thou Lord thinkeſt it fitting, to the end he may glorifie thy Name, and bee thankefull for thy mercy. But if it be thy will ſtill to continue or augment his paine, make that it may be for his good, and to giue him an increaſe of ſtrength and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy to beare theſe thy trials with a tranquile and ſweet ſpirit, without murmure or impatience: and alſo in theſe teſtimonies of his faith and patience, ſo Chriſtianly, we deſire that thou maiſt be glorified, and his neighbours edified and comforted. And that he may by the experience of this miſerable life, be taught to withdraw his heart and affection, and to raiſe them vp freely to the meditation and ſeeking of true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and to the incomprehenſible felicity, which is prouided for vs in Heauen to liue eternally: Grant al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo good Lord, the ſame graces to all other that are ſicke and afflicted;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19245:112"/>
Comfort them and fortifie them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their neceſſitie, and aboue all, giue them grace and a liuely faith, to embrace thy mercy in Ieſus Chriſt for their comfort. Heare vs, O Father of mercy, for the loue of thy welbeloued Sonne our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, euen as he himſelfe hath commanded vs to preſent our ſelues vnto thee: <hi>Our Father which art in Heauen, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>And foraſmuch, O Lord, as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith, we cannot be agreeable, or acceptable vnto thee, we beſeech thee ſo to increaſe it in this thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, and in vs all, that he may come to the laſt breath of life, and we with him, to perſeuere therein, and to be alwayes diſpoſed to render a pure confeſſion, with heart and mouth, as wee now preſent our ſelues vnto thee, ſaying, <hi>I beleeue in God, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>This is his faith, O Lord, and ours: giue vs grace to liue and dye
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19245:113"/>
herein, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, who in vnity of the Holy Spirit, liueth and raigneth with thee eternally, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>When there is apparencie that the ſickeneſſe is mortall, follow this forme.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Sir,</hi> It behoueth you to bee of good courage in the middle of your affliction, which it pleaſeth God ſtill to continue vpon your body; and be aſſured that he hath neither ſent or continued it, but for the good and ſaluation of your ſoule: to teach you by this meanes to vnderſtand your ſelfe, as being a poore ſinner; more and more to deteſt your ſinnes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne the world, to lift you vp to God, and to inuocate and call vpon him with much more feruour, with aſſurance to be heard, following his holy promiſes, and to obtaine of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19245:113"/>
him <hi>Chriſtian Conſtancy,</hi> which is moſt neceſſary for you in this tryall.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The aſſurance of the mercy of God in Ieſus Chriſt, the true ground of all Conſolation.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>That which ought moſt to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort you, and with courage and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to ſtrengthen you, is the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance which you ought alwayes to take; that God, for the loue of his welbeloued Sonne our Lord Ieſus, hath imbraced you into his loue and free fauour, hath pardoned your offences, hath adopted you and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued you amongſt the number of his children, to make you inherite the Kingdome of Heauen, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the purchaſe which Ieſus Chriſt hath made for you by the merit of his death, ſuch an aſſurance will make you alwayes certaine that nothing can happen vnto you,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19245:114"/>
whether it be in life or death, which can be any other then the fauour and bleſſing of your Heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo conſequently are aides and meanes ordayned by his wiſe prouidence, to conduct you to the bleſſed life.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>This aſſurance commeth from Faith.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>It is true that this aſſurance wee cannot take of our ſelues, it is our good God that giueth it, when by the vertue of his holy Spirit, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Word, he createth in our hearts a true and a liuely faith, with the which we receiue, and wee appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate the promiſes of his grace which he hath ordayned vs in the preaching of the goſpel. Which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes in effect are, <hi>That God hath ſo loued the world, that he hath giuen his onely Sonne, that whoſoeuer belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19245:114"/>
in him, ſhould not periſh, but haue life euerlaſting. Ioh.</hi> 3.16. If God then hath giuen you the grace to beleeue in his only Son; &amp; to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace him for your Redeemer and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, (as we gather hitherto by the profeſſion you haue made, and ſtill continueth in the Church) you may take from thence a holy aſſurance, that God, according to the infallible truth of his Word, hath receiued you into his loue, that you <hi>ſhall not periſh, but haue euerlaſting life.</hi> Now being ſo, what can you feare? <hi>Rom. 8.30.31. If God be with vs, who can be againſt vs?</hi> Hee, who hath not ſpared his owne Sonne, but deliuered him vp for vs all, how ſhall hee not with him alſo freely giue vs all things? Hee hath giuen you the moſt, that is his Sonne; hee will not euertheleſſe deny you any thing elſe that can be neceſſary for to keepe you from all ſort of euill, corporall
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19245:115"/>
and ſpirituall, as well in life, as in death.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Faith applyeth to all the faithfull, the promiſes of the Goſpell.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>This application whereof I haue ſpoken, which you muſt make to your ſelfe, from the promiſes of the Goſpel, to gather ſuch a holy aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, it is neceſſarily required by Faith. For to beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt, it is not enough to beleeue in groſſe, that there is a Ieſus Chriſt, and <hi>who beleeueth in him, hath eternall life:</hi> neither is it enough to beleeue that the promiſes of the Goſpell are altogether true; the Diuell beleeueth ſo much, yet notwithſtanding hee hath no true beleeuing faith: But to beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt, is, when the faithfull beleeueth that there is ſaluation in Ieſus Chriſt for him; which the Diuell cannot beleeue.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19245:115"/>
And the true iuſtifying faith, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the iuſt liueth, chiefely conſiſteth in that, that we apply and appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate vnto our ſelues, euery one in his own particular, the promiſes of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that euery one in his owne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, may ſay, that which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, in the perſon of euery one of the faithfull, <hi>Gal. 2.20. I liue in the faith of the Sonne of God, who hath loued me, and giuen himſelfe for me;</hi> and in the <hi>2 Tim. 1.2. I know whom I haue beleeued, and I am perſwaded that he is able to keepe that which I haue committed vnto him, againſt that day;</hi> and <hi>Rom. 8.37.38. I am aſſured that neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor Principalities, nor Powers, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can ſeparate vs from the loue of God, which he hath ſhewed vs in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> This faith doth not bring vs a ſimple opinion or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19245:116"/>
coniecture of our ſaluation, but a certaine knowledge, following that which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>5.14. Wee know that we are tranſlated from death to life,</hi> And <hi>Iohn 10. We know that we are of God, and I haue</hi> ſaith he, <hi>1 Ioh. 5.13. written theſe things to you which beleeue in the Name of the Sonne of God, to the end that you ſhould know that you haue eternall life.</hi> This faith freely lets vs goe to the treaſure of Gods grace, <hi>Heb. 4.10. With aſſurance,</hi> as hee ſaith in the <hi>10.22. euen with a true heart and a full aſſurance of faith,</hi> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Epheſ. 3.12.</hi> that, <hi>by Ieſus Chriſt we haue boldneſſe and acceſſe, in our beleefe, by the faith which wee haue in him.</hi> This faith is called, <hi>Hebrewes 11.1. the ſubſtance of things hoped for,</hi> that is to ſay, that maketh things beleeued and hoped ſubſiſt in our ſoules, neither more nor leſſe then if we were already in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19245:116"/>
the very Actuall poſſeſſion and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying. This Faith maketh vs finde peace and reſt in our ſoules and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, chaſing away the feares and terrours which ſinne would ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, with the apprehenſion of Gods iudgements, following that which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom. 5. Verſe 1. That being iuſtified by faith, we haue peace with God through Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord, by the which alſo wee haue beene led by Faith to this grace; wherein we hold our ſelues faſt, and glorifye our ſelues in the hope of the glory of God.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The gift of perſeuerance aſſured to the Faithfull.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>Moreouer, theſe paſſages pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound vnto vs this holy aſſurance of Faith, not onely for the preſent, but alſo to come, and containeth a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe which God giueth vs to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19245:117"/>
in this Faith, euen to the end. Otherwiſe, where ſhould be this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance which the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of, of not being able to be ſeparated from the loue of God in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt?</hi> Where ſhould be this ſubſiſtance of things hoped for? How ſhould wee haue in our ſoules a ſolid peace with God? How ſhould wee finde our ſelues firme in this grace? How can we glorifie our ſelues in the hope of the glory of God? Such is then the incomprehenſible bounty of this heauenly Father, that he beginneth not in vs the worke of our ſaluation, for to leaue it imperfect, according as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Philippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and in their perſons, ſpeaketh alſo to all truely faithfull, <hi>Phil. 1.6. I am aſſured, that hee that hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne this good worke in you, will perfect it, euen to the comming of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt:</hi> As alſo he ſaith in another place, <hi>Rom. 11.29. That the gifts
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19245:117"/>
and calling of God are without Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance:</hi> that is to ſay, hee gaine ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, nor euer goeth from his word.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Againſt the obiection that this aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Faith ſhould be a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>It may not be that this certainty of Faith be blamed in vs, and to be thought raſhneſſe and preſumption; for on the contrary, it ſhould be thought an extreame raſhneſſe and preſumption, if wee ſhould not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue ſuch excellent promiſes of our God: And it is Humility and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to receiue and reſt vpon it with reuerence; For it is ſaid, that <hi>he</hi> which hath receiued the Teſtimony of God, <hi>hath ſealed that God is veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, Iohn 3.33.</hi> that is to ſay, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, and giuen approbation to the truth of God, which he demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrateth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19245:118"/>
in the accompliſhment of his promiſes; and it is ſaid on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, in the 1 of <hi>Iohn, 5.10.11. That hee that beleeueth not God, hee hath made him a lyar:</hi> For hee hath not beleeued in the teſtimony which God hath witneſſed of his owne Sonne, and this is the teſtimony, that God hath giuen vs eternall life, and this life is in his Sonne.</p>
                        <p>Two things might make vs raſh and bolde in this aſſurance which we take of our ſaluation; the one is, if wee ſhould build vpon the merit of our workes, <hi>Rom. 3.20. For no fleſh ſhall be iuſtified before God, by the workes of the law; and all thoſe that ſeeke to be iuſtified thereby, are vnder malediction;</hi> ſo ſaith Saint <hi>Paul, 3.10.2. It is not by our owne righteouſneſſe, which is nothing, whereupon wee build ſuch an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but vpon the righteouſneſſe of him whom God hath made to be
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19245:118"/>
ſinne for vs, 2 Cor. 5.21.</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>a ſacrifice for ſinne:</hi> to the end that wee might be made the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God in him; and by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of whom we are made iuſt, in exchange of our diſobedience in <hi>Adam, which made vs all ſinners, Rom. 5.19.</hi> The other point which might make vs bolde in this behalfe; that if wee ſhould preſume to purchaſe ſuch a knowledge of our ſaluation by the ſubtilty of our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, as it is ſaid, <hi>that the Naturall man conceiueth not the things of God, 1 Cor. 2.14.</hi> But certainly, we make account to haue receiued, as the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>1 Cor. 2.12. Not the ſpirit of this world, but the ſpirit which is of God,</hi> to the end that wee ſhould know the things which haue beene giuen vs from God. Alſo hee ſaith in the ſame place, <hi>1 Cor. 2.9.10. That theſe things, which are altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible, God hath reuealed
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19245:119"/>
them by his holy ſpirit:</hi> Finally, hee addeth, <hi>1 Cor. 1.16. That by this meanes wee holde the intention of Chriſt. But by this ſpirit of God, are all thoſe conducted which are the Children of God,</hi> which the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom. 8.14.</hi> And hee is called, <hi>The ſpirit of adoption,</hi> and by him we cry <hi>Abba Father, Gal. 4.6.</hi> that is to ſay, wee cry and call vpon God as our Father. And alſo it is <hi>This ſame ſpirit,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 8.11.16. <hi>which giueth teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with our ſpirit, that we are the Children of God.</hi> In like ſort the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> ſaith, 1.13.14. <hi>That when we belieue in the Goſpell, we are ſealed with the holy ſpirit of promiſe,</hi> which is the earneſt of our inheritance, vntill the <hi>redemption of the purchaſed poſſeſsion, vnto the praiſe of his glory:</hi> by which wee learne that the teſtimony of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt receiued into our hearts
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19245:119"/>
with Faith, is like vnto a ſeale, which the holy Spirit imprinteth in our hearts, to aſſure vs of the promiſes of God, and to aſſure vs that we are his Children, and as men vſe in the Market, giuing of earneſt, that is to ſay, a part of the price agreed for, as well to beginne the payment, as to make the bargaine irreuocable, and aſſured, that it may be kept firme: Euen ſo the Holy Ghoſt, which through Faith begetteth peace and ioy in our hearts, <hi>is giuen vs for ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of the Kingdome of Heauen, Rom. 14.17.</hi> to the end to aſſure vs by this beginning of ſpirituall goods (which God hath promiſed to his children) that hee holdeth vs for his owne purchaſed poſſeſſion, to the praiſe of his glory, and that without euer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoking his promiſes, hee will at laſt gather vs to the full fruition of the Inheritance in Heauen.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:19245:120"/>
                     <head>It is needfull, if it be poſsible, to draw from the mouth of the ſicke perſon, confeſsion of his ſinnes, of his Repentance and his Faith; &amp; if hee haue not the vſe of his Tongue, but of his vnderſtanding, it is neceſſary for him to anſwere by ſome ſigne.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>Now Sir it behoueth you to take good courage, and willingly to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply this holy doctrine, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of your ſoule; this doctrine hath been declared vnto you by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpell, in the Church of God, whereof you haue beene a member; it hath alſo beene confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnto you by the vſe of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, with whom you haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated. Haue you not receiued it with Faith?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Patient.</speaker>
                        <p>I haue.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="39" facs="tcp:19245:120"/>Alſo doe you not beleeue, that God is not onely your <hi>Creator,</hi> (but ſinne hauing loſt you,) hee is your Sauiour in Ieſus Chriſt?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Patient.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <p>Doe you not acknowledge, that you are a poore and miſerable ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that if he ſhould reckon with you according to your ſinnes, of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie he ſhould make you periſh in death and eternall damnation?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Patient.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <p>Are you not very heartily ſorry and grieued ſo to haue offended, and doe you repent your ſelfe, euen with your whole heart?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Patient.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <p>Doe you not renounce all opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19245:121"/>
and truſt in our owne Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, for to repoſe your ſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely, and your hope in the mercy of God, by which he iuſtifieth and ſaueth vs, in his bleſſed Sonne Ieſus Chriſt?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Patient.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <p>Doe you not beleeue that he hath receiued you into his mercie, that he is pleaſed and appeaſed with you, and hath in grace reconciled you vnto him, in the fauour, and through the obedience and merit of the ſame Ieſus Chriſt his Sonne, who you firmely beleeue died for your ſinnes, and is riſen for your iuſtification?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Patient.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <p>Now I beſeech God to confirm &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe you more &amp; more in this faith, following the which, you need not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19245:121"/>
doubt a certaine aſſurance to be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified and ſaued, ſeeing that God hath giuen you this grace to beleeue with your heart to Righteouſneſſe, and to make confeſſion with your mouth to ſaluation. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.1.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>For the ſicke perſon to reſolue, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be for life or death, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Gods will.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>Being thus reſolued vpon this firme foundation of faith, now you muſt take a holy reſolution, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to attend without all feare, what the Lord will be pleaſed to ſend vnto you in this your ſickneſſe, with a firme perſwaſion that all will goe well with you; whether it bee you ſhall remaine here below, or that it be his pleaſure to make you more happy. If his pleaſure be to reſtore you to former health againe, as he is powerfull to draw the dead
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19245:122"/>
out of the ſepulcher, and make them liue againe: which will bee if hee pleaſe, for to make you more affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate to the honour and ſeruice of God, then euer heretofore you haue beene: But if it be his will to leade you by this ſickeneſſe, to the end of your courſe, it will be to receiue you into the poſſeſſion of that perfect fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity which the Sonne of God hath ſo dearely bought with the price of his blood. And therefore goe your wayes vnto him, with a holy cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe in the aſſurance of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. Reioyce your ſelfe in the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py exchange of your remouing from earth to Heauen, from this ſhort and miſerable life, to the bleſſed life for euer to endure; from theſe triuiall and periſhing goods, to thoſe that are heauenly and eternall, which <hi>eye hath not ſeene, nor eare hath heard, &amp; which are not yet come vp into the heart of Man, which God hath prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19245:122"/>
for thoſe that loue him.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Are you not then well reſolued in all this, to conforme your will to your Heauenly Father? to the end, <hi>that whether you liue, you liue to the Lord, or whether you dye, you die to the Lord, Rom. 14.8.</hi> being well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that Chriſt ſhall be alwayes to you to liue or to dye? <hi>Phil. 1.21.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Patient.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <p>God giue you the grace.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>For to aſſure and comfort the ſicke in the infirmitie of Faith.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>I am not ignorant that your faith, how great ſoeuer it may be, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it is both little in you and feeble: for whileſt the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of this life remaine, the Holy Spirit is not giuen vs, but in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19245:123"/>
meaſure, according to the which we know not but in part, and our ſpirituall renuing is yet but in the beginning; it is certaine that here below we cannot attaine to the perfection of faith; and therefore I doubt not but that your faith is yet weake, and infirme, and that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be moued with diuers temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and combated with diuers aſſaults of doubt and diſtruſt. But yet neuertheleſſe, it behoueth you to be of good courage; for this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat which you feele in your ſelfe, is the combat, which as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Galatians, 5. v. 17. is in the ſoule of euery faithfull, betweene the fleſh and the Spirit;</hi> and therefore this is a ſure teſtimony which you haue by faith. For as the fleſh figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in you through vnbeliefe, ſo doth the Spirit fight in you by faith: and this faith neuer faileth, being fortified by the Spirit of God, which
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19245:123"/>
maketh a man victorious, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer imperfection it hath, God will make it ſufficient to ſaluation; for it is not ſaid, Who ſhall perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeue ſhall be ſaued, but ſimply, <hi>Who ſhall beleeue.</hi> Moreouer, as you perceiue in your ſelfe, your faith fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and imperfect, alſo I doubt not, but you perceiue in your ſelfe a Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire that it may be encreaſed in you and made ſtronger, and that in your heart you make your prayers to God that it may be ſo; Is it not true?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Patient.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <p>But ſeeing it is ſo, and that this faith and deſire may encreaſe in you, and that this prayer which you make to God, proceed from the fruit of the Spirit, and not of the fleſh? and ſeeing theſe are the fruits which the Spirit of God bringeth forth in you? is it not a ſure teſtimony, that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19245:124"/>
you are conducted by the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and ſo conſequently the child of God? for all thoſe that are condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the Spirit of God, are the children of God, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom. 8.14.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Be of good cheere Sir, and boldly ſay with the Apoſtle in the middeſt of your combats, <hi>I am aſſured that nothing can ſeperate me from the loue of God, which he hath ſhewed mee in Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>For to aſſure the ſicke againſt the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frights and temptations of Conſcience.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>There are foure things to be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, which in this ſpirituall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat may affright you, ſhake your faith, and trouble the peace of your conſcience; which is the feeling of your ſinnes, the apprehenſion of death, the feare of the Diuell, and the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19245:124"/>
horror of Gods Iudgements; before whom wee muſt make our appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance at the going out of this life. But againſt the feare of all theſe things, the bounty of God, in the bleſſings of Chriſt, and in the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of his Word, furniſheth you with all ſufficient remedies, for to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you and truely to confirme you in inuincible conſtancy.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Againſt feare proceeding from the feeling of ſinne.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>Firſt of all, for the reſpect of your ſinnes, it is very neceſſary to haue a liuely feeling thereof, for to humble your ſelfe before God: but ſeeing yon proteſt to haue a ſerious and true repentance, and to ſearch and apprehend by faith the ſatisfaction and expiation in the blood of Ieſus Chriſt, aſſure your ſelfe, they can no way hinder the effect of your ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19245:125"/>
If you bee a ſinner, <hi>So Ieſus Chriſt is come into the world to ſaue ſinners, 1 Tim. 1.15. He is the Lamb of God that taketh away the ſinnes of the world, Iohn 1.29. It is his blood which cleanſeth vs from all iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, 1 Iohn 1.7.9. And whoſoeuer ſhall beleeue in him, ſhall receiue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of his ſinnes, through his Name, Acts, 10.43.</hi> And therefore he hath commanded, <hi>that repentance and forgiueneſſe of ſinnes ſhould bee preached in his Name, Luke 24.47.</hi> Hee himſelfe inuiteth vs to come to him, for to enioy this bleſſing: <hi>Come vnto me all yee that labour and are ouer-laden, and I will refreſh you, Matth.</hi> 11.28. Goe your wayes then vnto him, if you finde your ſelues grieued with the burthen of your ſinnes, in aſſurance to finde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for your ſoules. And for that very thing, euery day hee maketh himſelfe an Aduocate to the Father
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19245:125"/>
for vs. <hi>If we haue ſinned,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn 2.1.2. wee haue an Aduocate with the Father, that is to ſay, Ieſus Chriſt the Iuſt, who is the propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for our ſinnes.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Againſt the feare of Death.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>In regard of death, wherefore doe you feare it, ſeeing that your ſinnes are no more imputed vnto you? for ſinne was the cauſe that death en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the world, as Saint <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 5.12. and by conſequence, there where no ſinne is, there can be no death. And indeed concerning death eternall, which the Scripture calleth the ſecond death, you haue an entire and full freedome, by the meanes of this faith which God hath giuen you. <hi>In veritie,</hi> ſaith the Sonne of God, <hi>Iohn 5.24. I ſay vnto you, that he that heareth my Word and beleeueth in him that ſent mee, ſhall
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19245:126"/>
haue euerlaſting life, and ſhall not come to condemnation, but is paſſed from death to life.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>And as for the corporall death, of which we are aſſured, it is neuer a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony to the faithfull of the anger of God againſt them, as it is alwayes to the wicked; but a ſingular fauour of Gods bounty, bringing an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite number of bleſſings with it. Firſt of all, it deliuereth vs from all ſorts of dangers, putting an end to ſo many miſeries and griefes, which vexeth vs without ceaſe, both in our ſoules and Bodies during the courſe of this miſerable life, or rather of this continuall death, wherewithall wee languiſh here below: Alſo it taketh vs away from amidſt the throng of this wicked world, with the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof we cannot but be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, and ſo we come to be freed from this vnhappy neceſſitie of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full liuing, and from the daily and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19245:126"/>
hourely offending of our Heauenly Father who is ſo bountifull and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious a God vnto vs.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, this bodily death is an entrance to the true life, by the death of Ieſus Chriſt, whoſe ſacred ſelfe hath paſſed through this death, to make our paſſage ſafe and happy vnto vs: this is now an aſſured bridge to paſſe and make our trauaile from the world to God, and from the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieues of this life to the incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible Beatitude of eternall life; to that fulneſſe of ioy, which is as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſalme,</hi> 16.11. <hi>In the contemplation of the face of the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</hi> This is the good which your Soule ſhall enioy at the departing from your body: And as for your body, which ſhall be put into the earth, it ſhall not be there to periſh alwayes, but onely for a while to reſt, attending the happy reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which is the cauſe why death is
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19245:127"/>
called in the Scripture, <hi>A Sleepe,</hi> and and they are ſaide to be <hi>ſleeping,</hi> in regard of their bodies, which at the laſt day ſhal be awaked and riſe from duſt, to poſſeſſe together with their ſoules the glorious mortality, being made conformable to the glorious <hi>Body of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Phil. 3.21.</hi> He is the head, and they are the members: and therefore it beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth that the members be confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to their Head.</p>
                        <p>What finde you then in death that may affright you, ſeeing it deliuereth you from all euill, and will raiſe you to the height of all goodneſſe? Rather you ſhall not meete with any thing, but will giue you comfort and aſſurance, to confirme your atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance with reſolution and tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of ſpirit, euen to aſpire with all your hearr, when the Houre will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ome, to ſay with Saint <hi>Paul, My deſire is to be diſſolued, and to be with Chriſt.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:19245:127"/>
                     <head>Againſt the feare of the Diuell.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>For the feare that you may haue of the Diuell, you ſee now there is no great cauſe to doubt, ſeeing that death cannot annoy you, but by death, by which it domineareth. But the Apoſtle teſtifieth, <hi>that Ieſus Chriſt hath not onely deſtroyed death, but him alſo that hath the empire of death,</hi> which is the Diuell, <hi>Heb. 2.14.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Our Lord himſelfe ſaith, that the Prince of this world hath nothing in him; neither hath any thing in thoſe that are his Members, amongſt which number you are by the grace of God. Alſo this hath beene for vs and our profit, that the Sonne of God hath vanquiſhed and ouercome vpon the Croſſe, where <hi>He hath,</hi> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Colloſsians, 2.15. ouercome the principalities and powers of Hell, which hee hath pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19245:128"/>
brought in euidence, therein triumphing ouer them.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>I doubt not but the enemy of our ſaluation, maketh warre againſt you, for to aſtoniſh and trouble your Faith, for as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>1.5. Verſe 8.9. Our aduerſarie the Diuell walketh like a roaring Lyon, ſeeking whom hee may deuoure:</hi> Saint <hi>Peter</hi> addeth, <hi>being firme in faith, it behoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs to reſiſt him: Reſiſt the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell,</hi> as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, 4.7. <hi>and he will flie from you.</hi> But for to reſiſt and vanquiſh him, it behoueth you to be defended with the armour of God, whereof Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh to the <hi>Epheſians, Chap. 6. Verſe 16. Taking, aboue all,</hi> as hee ſaith, <hi>the Buckler of Faith, by which you ſhall be able to quench all the fiery darts of the wicked.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:19245:128"/>
                     <head>Againſt the Apprehenſion of the Iudgement of God.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>Now remaineth the feare which you may take of the Iudgement of God, before whom you muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. But whereupon ground you your apprehenſion, ſeeing that your ſinnes ſhall be no more imputed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, ſeeing you ſhall be no more condemned to death, ſeeing that it will nothing auaile Sathan to accuſe you, being thereby abſolued and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by the grace of God? It is the doctrine which the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> giueth vs, <hi>Rom. 8. Verſe 32.33. Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect? It is God that iuſtifieth, Who is he that condemneth? It is Chriſt that dyed, yea, rather that is riſen againe, who is euen at the right hand of God, who alſo maketh inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion for vs.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="56" facs="tcp:19245:129"/>Euen ſo ought we to come before God, but not as before a ſeuere and rigorous Iudge, but as before a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that is well-pleaſed with you through the interceſſion of Ieſus Chriſt: of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> I ſay, who is both your Interceſſor and Aduocate to God the Father. Hee will not be refuſed of the Father in his requeſt for you, by <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> whereof you are a Member: <hi>For there is no condemnation to thoſe that are in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul, Rom. 8.1.</hi> By Ieſus Chriſt, in the end, in whom you beleeue, <hi>But he that beleeueth in me,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall haue eternall life, and ſhall not come to condemnation, but is paſſed from death to life.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Is not this then Sir your Faith, and firme beliefe, <hi>which by the benefit of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, you haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of your ſinnes, Iohn 5.24.</hi> That you are ſaued from eternall death, and freed from the rigour of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19245:129"/>
Gods iudgements, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, Sathan cannot annoy you by his accuſations and temptations, and that this corporall death can be no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto you, but profitable, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery way happy.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Alſo a proteſtation of charity, muſt be drawne from the ſicke party to his Neighbour.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>As for the reſt Sir, you know Faith worketh by Charity, and neceſſarily bringeth it forth, ſeeing it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God to vnite you vnto him by Faith, alſo of neceſſitie you muſt be vnited to all your Brethren and Neighbours by a true chriſtian Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. And therefore tell vs if you free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly renounce not all hatred, rancour, and enmity with euery one without exception, and deſire the good and ſaluation of all in generall, and euery
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19245:130"/>
one in particular, euen as of your owne?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Patient.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <p>Doe you not pardon with all your heart, all thoſe that might haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended you in any ſort, as you like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe require pardon of all thoſe that might haue beene offended by you?</p>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Patient.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <p>Now Sir it behooueth vs to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe our prayer to God, to the end that he will be pleaſed to fortifie you in faith, which hee hath giuen you, and to make his graces more and more abound in you; and it is your part to humble your ſelfe with vs before him, and to lift vp your heart to him, to implore his Mercy from the bottome of your Heart.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:19245:130"/>
                     <head>A Prayer for the ſicke when there is any ſigne of death.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>O Lord our God, &amp; Mercifull Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we are very vnworthy to lift vp our eyes vnto thee, our ſins and wicked deedes are ſo many, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with wee are ſo polluted before thy face; neither is this out of the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of our owne worth to be thus bolde to preſent our ſelues at the feete of thy diuine Maieſty, but in the aſſurance of the great Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and perfect obedience which thy welbeloued Sonne <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> our Lord hath made for vs; with the righteouſneſſe whereof, wee beſeech thee couer vs with thy grace, to the end wee may be by his fauour made agreeable and reconciled vnto thee. But wee beſeech thee O good God, particularly vouchſafe thy great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to this thy poore ſeruant, ſo fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19245:131"/>
mightily deiected vnder thy powerfull hand: poore ſinner remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vnder the weight and rigour of thy high Iuſtice, if thou doeſt not extend thy great clemency towards him.</p>
                        <p>Giue him grace, good Lord, to enter more and more into a ſerious exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and acknowledgement of his faults, to conceiue that true deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which alwayes bringeth forth true repentance, and ſet him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward intirely to renounce himſelfe and his owne way, to haue all his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge in thee, and in thy bounty: In the meane while receiue him grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, O Lord, ſhew him the face of a father and aſſure and comfort him: Say to his ſoule, <hi>Soule, I am he that can warrant thee. Diſpoſe of his heart,</hi> patiently to receiue with Action of graces, this Fatherly correction, which thou haſt ſent him, and to put himſelfe wholly into thy hands, to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19245:131"/>
ſubmit himſelfe peaceably vnder all that thou ſhalt pleaſe to lay vpon him by thy holy prouidence. Lord thou knoweſt better then he himſelfe, or any of vs what is moſt conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, whether he ſhall liue or die: If thy good pleaſure be that hee ſhall liue, let it be that he may onely liue to thee: in ſuch ſort that hauing profited well by thy chaſtiſements, he may learne to loue thee, honour and ſerue thee, all the dayes of his life in thy Church; perpetually ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying to bring ſorth fruits of piety and holineſſe, worthy of thy Goſpel, and conuenient for a childe of ſuch a Father; ſo that in him thou maiſt be glorified, and his neighbours edified. But contrarily of the other part, it be thy pleaſure, to take him out of this miſerable world, aſſure him that it ſhall be to put him into the poſſeſſion of thy Heauenly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which thou haſt prepared
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19245:132"/>
before the foundations of the world, and which thy Sonne hath purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the merit of his death. To this end, O Father of light, from whom proceedeth euery good gift, that thou wilt be pleaſed to giue him a true and a liuely faith, with the which he may ſearch, find, and apprehend the propitiation for his ſinnes, and the true righteouſnes in the obedience of thy welbeloued Sonne Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, who hath ſuffered for our ſinnes, and riſen againe for our iuſtification, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended into Heauen to take poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in our Name, and by this meanes, giueth vs acceſſe and entrance, which ſinne had baniſhed vs from. Imprint in his heart a full aſſurance of all theſe thy graces, to the end that by this meanes, he may peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably repoſe himſelfe in thy mercy, and happily ouercome all the ſnares and temptations which Sathan and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19245:132"/>
his owne fleſh would put before him, to trouble the clearneſſe of his faith, and tranquility of his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. That his ſinnes then may not make him deſpaire, becauſe thy Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice hath been ſo well payed, not with gold or ſiluer, but with the pretious blood of thy Chriſt, as of the Lambe without ſpot or blemiſh. Let not death affright him, ſeeing ſinne is aboliſhed and deſtroyed in him, which is the ſting of death, who now is diſarmed and without all power: that his ſpirit being ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the body by this corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall death, it ſhall be to come trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantly to thee, and deliuered from the captiuity of ſinne, to the end to taſte of the enioying the moſt happy life, which he neuer taſted in this world, but by hope: leauing his body in the earth, but not for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, but to be refined, transformed, &amp; in time conuenient made confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19245:133"/>
to the glorious body of his Redeemer by the benefit of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. So Sathan ſhall no more aſtoniſh him but by ſinne and death, which he hath vtterly loſt all power in ouer our viſited Brother. Aſſuring him in the end that this accuſer can intend nothing againſt him, before the Throne of thy iuſtice, ſeeing hee is abſolued &amp; iuſtified by thy grace, there is no iudge that can condemne him. That thou wilt alſo be pleaſed, O good God, to be likewiſe mercifull to all other ſicke ſoules, comfort and fortifie them according as thou knoweſt them needfull: and aboue all, giue them grace alwayes to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace with a true and liuely faith, thy mercy in Ieſus Chriſt, wherein they may euer be comforted. Good Lord vouchſafe vnto vs all this grace, that this example may profite and teach vs to renounce the world and our ſelues, to imploy that time
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19245:133"/>
we haue here below, to meditate thy wiſedome, walke carefully in thy feare, retyre our hearts from the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of this life, to raiſe them vp to attend and meditate vpon the Heauenly life, and to this end to be alwayes prepared to appeare before thee, with aſſurance to be gathered and receiued into thy mercy, for the loue of thy welbeloued Sonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord: In whoſe name we beſeech thee, O Father of mercy, heere vs in theſe things, and in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things which thou knoweſt better to be neceſſary for thy poore ſeruant, and for vs, then we doe our ſelues; as we doe now requeſt thee in that prayer which thou haſt commanded vs to preſent our ſelues before thee: <hi>Our Father which art in Heauen, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Lord giue vs a good increaſe of Faith, which thou haſt planted in the heart of this thy childe and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant:
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19245:134"/>
defend him as with a Buckler, by the which he may extinguiſh all the fiery darts of the Diuell, and make him perſeuere conſtantly ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, vntill the very laſt breath of his life, and that hee may alwaies, at the leaſt in his heart, render vnto thee a pure and Chriſtian confeſſion, as we now preſent with heart and mouth: <hi>I beleeue in God the Father Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>This is his Faith O Lord, and ours, giue vs grace to liue and dye in it, through Ieſus Chriſt thy Sonne our Lord, who in the vnitie of the Holy Spirit, liueth and raign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with thee God eternally, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>If the ſicke perſon continue long, and ſtill in danger of death, it will be conuenient to repeat at times neceſſary, the aboueſaid Comforts, but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially thoſe which are to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19245:134"/>
and fortifie againſt the temptations and combats of Conſcience.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>And if it happen the ſicke party be troubled with idle talke, or can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not vnderſtand a long diſcourſe: vſe ſhort ſentences, ſuch as hereafter fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth; ſpeaking but at ſometimes.</p>
                        <p>Sir, it behooueth you to take good courage; it is the fatherly hand of God that viſiteth you for your good and ſaluation: For to thoſe whom God loueth, all things worke toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for good.</p>
                        <p>Lift vp your heart to God, and confeſſe your ſinnes and offences, and imbrace by faith his mercy in Ieſus Chriſt, which hee hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to all thoſe that repent, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in him.</p>
                        <p>Haue you not alwaies a good aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the mercy of God, &amp; a firme
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19245:135"/>
faith in Ieſus Chriſt your Sauiour?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Patient.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <p>Doe you not beleeue that Ieſus Chriſt is dead for your ſinnes, and riſen againe for your iuſtification?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Patient.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <p>Doe you not beleeue that hee hath before the Father, beene your wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, righteouſneſſe, ſanctification, and redemption?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Patient.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <p>Doe you not thinke that hee hath freely iuſtified you by the grace of God, through the redemption which is in Chriſt Ieſus?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Patient.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="69" facs="tcp:19245:135"/>Following this your faith, doubt not, but God will warrant you from all perdition, and giue you euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>For God hath giuen his Sonne, to the end that whoſoeuer ſhall beleeue in him, ſhall not periſh but haue eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life,</hi> Ioh. 16.</p>
                        <p>Feare not death, ſeeing by faith you imbrace Ieſus Chriſt, who is your life. <hi>I am,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and the life, who ſhall beleeue in me, although he be dead, ſhall liue: and whoſoeuer liueth and beleeueth in me, ſhall neuer dye,</hi> Ioh. 11.25.26.</p>
                        <p>If your ſinnes doe afflict you, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe your ſelfe alwaies by faith, and runne to Chriſt Ieſus, and you ſhall finde reſt to your ſoule; <hi>Come to mee,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Matthew, 11.28. all you that labour, and are ouer-laden, and I will eaſe you:</hi> Doubt not the rigour of Gods iuſtice; <hi>for there is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation to thoſe that are in Chriſt
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19245:136"/>
Ieſus,</hi> as the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom. 8.1. And who is he, Rom. 8.32.33. that will bring in accuſation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the elect of God? God is hee that iuſtifieth, who will be hee that ſhall condemne? Chriſt is he which is dead, and which is more, is riſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: who is alſo at the right hand of God, and maketh interceſsion for vs.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Be not ſorry to leaue this miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble life, which as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, 4.14. <hi>is but a vapour, which appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a little while and afterwards va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth;</hi> beſides, in exchange thereof, euerlaſting life ſhall be giuen vnto you, and in that the very height of felicity, ſo great and incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, <hi>That eye hath not ſeene, nor eare vnderſtood, and is not come vp into the heart of man, that which God hath prepared for thoſe that loue him.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>When the ſicke perſon is apparantly
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19245:136"/>
at the point of death, or ready to yeeld vp the Ghoſt, it is neceſſary to repeat this ſhort conſolation fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, with prayer.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>Comfort your ſelfe Sir, you now approach neare vnto the end of the Combat, which cannot be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe but happy vnto you, aſſure your ſelfe, the victory is of your ſide, by meanes of your faith, which is the victory that ouercommeth the world, and the Prince of the world. Ieſus Chriſt your head and Sauiour extendeth forth his hand, and ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for you at the end of the liſts, to preſent vnto you the incorruptible Crowne of glory, which he hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed with the price of his bloud, commend your ſelfe vnto him now with all your heart: goe vnto him with ioy: throw your ſelfe into his Armes, and ſay, <hi>Into thy hands I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my ſoule, for thou haſt bought
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19245:137"/>
me O God of truth. Pſal.</hi> 31. Let vs againe pray to God that he will giue you his grace.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A Prayer.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>O Lord, Father of Mercy, &amp; God of all Conſolation, let fall thy mercies and comforts vpon this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, vpon this perſon, thy poore childe and ſeruant: Make him now gather and apply vnto himſelfe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and abundant profit of the holy Inſtructions which in thy ſchoole thou haſt taught him during the courſe of his life: giue him an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible faith in this Combat.</p>
                        <p>Arme him with all thy ſpirituall Armour, that hee may reſiſt all the Temptations of Sathan: and hauing ouercome all, make him remain firme.</p>
                        <p>If thy Iuſtice aſtoniſh, let thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie aſſure and comfort: if his ſinnes accuſe him let the obedience of thy welbeloued excuſe and iuſtifie him, if
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19245:137"/>
the apprehenſion of death, trouble him, make him contemplate the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen gate of euerlaſting life, to which thou goeſt to make him enter. Thou haſt giuen him it in thy Sonne, make it perfectly happy to him. Hee is of the flocke of this great Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, let it not be taken from him. Thou haſt begun his ſaluation, let not the worke remaine vnperfect. And now that thou haſt brought him to the end of his ſorrowfull courſe, now receiue his ſoule into thy hands, and bring it into thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly paradice, into the fulneſſe of repoſe and beatitude, into the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of thy bleſſed Angels, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſoules of thine Elect, which thou haſt gathered for euer to enioy toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the perfection of all ioy, which conſiſteth in the contemplation of his face. Heare vs, O Father of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, for the loue of thy welbeloued Son Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, who in
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19245:138"/>
vnity of the holy Spirit, liueth and raigneth with thee God eternally, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>A ſhort comfort for thoſe that are friends of the deceaſed, to be giuen after the body is interred.</head>
                     <sp>
                        <p>Friends, it is needfull in this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for you to remember, of the holy Chriſtian inſtruction which you haue receiued in the ſchoole of Ieſus Chriſt, for to make your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit in bearing your affliction with patience, and in humility, reſting in a quiet Spirit at the will of God, to which we ought alwayes to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect and conformable. Our Nature in ſuch accidents leadeth vs to teares, but the Spirit of God, author of all Regeneration, teacheth vs to keepe meaſure, and not to afflict our ſelues, like thoſe that haue no hope <hi>(1 Theſſ. 4.13.) If we be men in wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping,</hi> yet wee muſt ſhew our ſelues
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19245:138"/>
Chriſtians, adorned with faith and hope, to aſſure vs that this corporall death, is no other to the faithfull children of God, but a happy port to enter into eternall life, <hi>Ioh. 5.28.29.</hi> and as for the body it muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in earth, vntill that day when they ſhall heare the voyce of the Lord, which ſhall make them riſe out of the graue, <hi>into the reſurrection of life.</hi> That the deceaſed is of the number of Gods children, the marks and teſtimonies which God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him, by the good profeſſion of piety and wiſedome, which hee hath made in the Church, vnto the laſt breath of his life, neede not leaue vs in doubt. He hath liued to the Lord, and is dead to the Lord, by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is happy, <hi>and reſteth from his labour, Apoc. 14.13.</hi> by the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly teſtimony of the Spirit of God himſelfe. You haue no cauſe to weep ouer him, for the condition he is in,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:19245:139"/>
being in euery kinde thrice happy. He hath alſo a great aduantage of vs, that remaine in this world behinde him. For he is arriued at the port of ſaluation, where as we are ſtill bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with the ſtorme and torment of the confuſed and dangerous ſea of this miſerable world. And therefore it is much better to aſpire to go with him, then to wiſh him to remaine here below with vs; for the diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity that you may receiue by his abſence, it behoueth you to conſider, that God that gaue him to you, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth ſtill with you, who is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for vs without all other things, whereas all other things without him are nothing: It is hee that will continue alwayes ouer you the care of his fatherly prouidence, if you continue alwayes to walke in his feare. I beſeech God to giue you grace, and fortifie you with a holy and conſtant reſolution. Amen.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19245:139" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
